<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A practical discourse upon charity in its several branches and of the reasonableness and useful nature of this great Christian virtue / by Edward Pelling ...</title>
            <author>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 236 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 152 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53959</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1086</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21750</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12226880</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12226880</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56571</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53959)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56571)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 924:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A practical discourse upon charity in its several branches and of the reasonableness and useful nature of this great Christian virtue / by Edward Pelling ...</title>
                  <author>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 292 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E.J. for W. Crooke ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
                  <note>Table of contents: p. [3]-[4]</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:56571:1"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:56571:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
A Practical Diſcourſe UPON CHARITY, In its ſeveral Branches: And of the <hi>Reaſonableneſs</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeful Nature</hi> of this Great CHRISTIAN VIRTUE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> EDWARD PELLING, <hi>D. D. Chaplain in Ordinary to Their Majeſties, and Rector of</hi> Petworth <hi>in</hi> Suſſex.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>E. I.</hi> for <hi>W. Crooke</hi> at the <hi>Green-Dragon</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar,</hi> 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:56571:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56571:2"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>THE Introduction. <hi>Page</hi> 1.</item>
                  <item>The Nature of Chriſtian Charity, what it is, and how it differs from Juſtice. 6</item>
                  <item>The Benefit that comes to ones Mind by a Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Temper. 25</item>
                  <item>The Reſemblance it bears to the Nature of God. 34</item>
                  <item>How it ſerves to anſwer the Great Ends of the New Covenant. 47</item>
                  <item>How it fits and prepares us for an Happy State hereafter. 61</item>
                  <item>How we are to expreſs our Charity. 75</item>
                  <item>Several ways of expreſſing it, according to the Characters given of Charity by St. <hi>Paul.</hi> 76</item>
                  <item>Charity muſt be expreſs'd by not being Angry on a ſudden. 79</item>
                  <item>Charity muſt be expreſs'd by moderating Anger. 82</item>
                  <item>Directions for the Government of this Paſſion. 92</item>
                  <item>We muſt expreſs our Charity by all manner of Kindneſs, <hi>p.</hi> 104. To another's Soul, <hi>p.</hi> 111. To his outward Wants, <hi>p.</hi> 112. And to his Credit alſo, <hi>p.</hi> 116</item>
                  <item>Charity forbids us to be Envious; and why. 119</item>
                  <item>Charity forbids us to be Precipitant and Raſh. 128</item>
                  <item>Directions to keep us from being Raſh. 131</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:56571:3"/>
                  <item>We muſt expreſs our Charity by our Humility, and why. <hi>Page</hi> 134</item>
                  <item>'Tis inconſiſtent with Charity to do any Thing that is Foul, or Indecent. 145</item>
                  <item>We muſt expreſs our Charity by ſeeking the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Good, <hi>p.</hi> 157. Eſpecially Peace, <hi>p.</hi> 162</item>
                  <item>Charity forbids us to be Suſpicious and Jealous-headed. 178</item>
                  <item>Charity forbids us to Rejoyce at other Men's Sins, <hi>p.</hi> 188. And at other Men's Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, <hi>p.</hi> 194. Directions as to this, <hi>p.</hi> 195</item>
                  <item>We muſt expreſs our Charity by our Zeal for the Proſperity of true Religion, <hi>p.</hi> 200. Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions as to this, <hi>p.</hi> 203</item>
                  <item>We muſt expseſs our Charity by concealing other People's Faults, <hi>p.</hi> 209. And why, <hi>p.</hi> 212. Directions, <hi>p.</hi> 219</item>
                  <item>We muſt expreſs our Charity by Believing the beſt of others in all Doubtful Caſes, <hi>p.</hi> 224. Directions as to this, <hi>p.</hi> 228</item>
                  <item>Charity requires us to Hope well of others, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially as to their future State, 234</item>
                  <item>Chriſtian Charity muſt be expreſs'd by Patience in all Caſes, <hi>p.</hi> 247. By Patience in a Suffering Condition, <hi>p.</hi> 250. And in caſe of Difference in Matters of Opinion, <hi>p.</hi> 261</item>
                  <item>The Concluſion. 275</item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56571:3"/>
            <head>A Practical Diſcourſe UPON CHARITY.</head>
            <p>THAT infinitely Wiſe and Beneficent Being that made the World, to communicate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to his Creatures, and to make them Partakers of his Goodneſs, hath given ſuch Laws of Virtue to Mankind, as ſerve, not only to prepare us for the endleſs Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities of another Life, but alſo to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:56571:4"/>
make us in a great meaſure happy in this. For thoſe Virtues are Copies of God himſelf, Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripts of his own moſt Bleſſed Nature; and therefore they muſt neceſſarily tend to make us hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, becauſe God himſelf is happy in them. God's Happineſs conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in the admirable Perfections of his Nature; and the higher we riſe in theſe Perfections, the greater degrees of Happineſs we muſt needs attain to, becauſe we approach the nearer unto God, in the reſemblance of whom the true and ſolid Happineſs of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind doth conſiſt, though the corrupt part of the World doth evermore place it in other Things.</p>
            <p>Thoſe Virtues I now ſpeak of are the Divine Perfections which are the Rule of God's Actions to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Mankind: As, the Purity
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:56571:4"/>
and Holineſs of his Nature, by means whereof he hateth all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Iniquity; his Eſſential Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racity, by reaſon whereof he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not lye; his Faithfulneſs in the performance of all his Promiſes, upon which account he is empha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically called, <hi>The faithful God, Deut.</hi> 7. 9. His Patience and Long-ſuffering towards the greateſt Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minals, <hi>not willing that any ſhould periſh;</hi> the exact Rectitude of his Will, by means whereof he offers not the leaſt Injury to any part of the Creation, but is Righteous and Juſt in all his Proceedings: But above all his infinite Compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, (a God <hi>full of Compaſſion</hi> he is called, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 86. 15.) by virtue whereof he is Gracious, Merciful, ſlow to Anger, and plenteous in Goodneſs. Theſe Perfections the ever-bleſſed God communicates
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:56571:5"/>
to Mankind, according to their Capacities; and in the exerciſe of theſe Virtues doth our true Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs conſiſt. It is not Riches or Greatneſs, or any Worldly Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that make our Minds or our Lives happy: Then are we happy indeed, when we are holy as God is Holy; when we are Sincere and Upright, Conſtant, Patient and Juſt as God is; and above all, when our <hi>Mercy rejoyceth over Juſtice,</hi> as God's doth; when we put on Bowels of Mercy; when we are Kind, and Good, and Tender-hearted towards one another; when we forbear one another, and forgive one another; in ſhort, when we love one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as God himſelf loves us all. This is our greateſt Perfection: a Perfection recommended to us in the Scripture under ſingular Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56571:5"/>
above Faith, or Hope, or any other Grace: And in the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of this Virtue our trueſt Happineſs muſt needs conſiſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it carrieth the greateſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance of the Divine Nature. <hi>God is Love,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4. 8. that is, the Perfection of Love, Goodneſs, and Charity is in him.</p>
            <p>In diſcourſing upon this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, <hi>Charity,</hi> as it relates to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, it will be neceſſary,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Firſt,</hi> To explain the true Nature of it.</item>
               <item>2. To conſider the Motives which ſerve to make it Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical.</item>
               <item>3. To ſhew the Way and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, after which it is to be expreſs'd.</item>
            </list>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:56571:6"/>
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>1. As to the Nature of <hi>Charity:</hi> It is ſuch a Principle of Kindneſs and Benevolence, as doth diſpoſe us to do others all the good we can, over and above that which is their due by the Laws of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Juſtice. This is to be noted carefully, that we may underſtand the difference between <hi>Juſtice</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſo called, and true <hi>Chriſtian Charity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Office of Juſtice is to do thoſe Things which a Man hath a Civil Right unto; Things which he can claim and challenge; Things which cannot be denied him without manifeſt Wrong and Injury. Now this, even Irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and Hard-hearted People are capable of doing; nor is this
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56571:6"/>
always a Virtue, becauſe it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth many times not from Choice, but Neceſſity. Charity is a Tenderneſs and Goodneſs of Mind, which conſtrains us to do more than what Humane Laws oblige us to. 'Tis a Virtue that ſtirs the Bowels, that moves and works upon the Affections, that extends our Compaſſion, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larges our Hearts beyond the common Limits: A Virtue that inclines us to be Benevolent unto all Men; to wiſh them all the Good their condition calls for; to be Supplicants for it on their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half at the Throne of Grace; to aid and aſſiſt them towards the obtaining of it; and for the Love of God and for Religion-ſake to help them, not only to thoſe Things which are really due from <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> but to thoſe Things alſo which
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56571:7"/>
are neceſſary, fitting, and proper for <hi>Them,</hi> tho' they be not Debts in a ſtrict Senſe and Conſtruction. In a word, it is a Generoſity of Temper, that is apt to ſuit it ſelf to the condition of others, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the moving Nature of their preſent Circumſtances.</p>
               <p>The Rule of Righteouſneſs is, <hi>To render every Man his own;</hi> But this may be without Charity; and therefore this alone is beneath the Generous and Noble Diſpoſition of a Chriſtian; it doth not come up to the perfect Law of Chriſt: Charity, though it hath a mixture of Juſtice in it, yet it is a great deal more: and that it may be compleat, as it ſhould be, theſe two Qualifications are very neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:56571:7"/>
Firſt, That it be of the ſame Nature with that Affection which we have for our ſelves.</p>
               <p>Secondly, That it reſemble that great Love which the Lord Jeſus expreſs'd for us all.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Our Charity to others muſt be of the ſame <hi>Nature</hi> with the Affection we have for our ſelves. This is the true Rule of Charity, eſpecially as it is heightned and improved by the Chriſtian Religion, <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as thy ſelf;</hi> that is, with the ſame good natur'd and kind Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, though it may be not in the ſame Meaſure and Degree.</p>
               <p>There is indeed a ſort of Self-love that is ſinful, an Affection that begins and ends at home too; when a Man is for pleaſing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56571:8"/>
only, when he ſeeks his own only; when he makes himſelf the ſole end of all his Actions; and would fain engroſs to himſelf all that is good and deſirable in this World, begrudging his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour any conſiderable Share or Proportion of it. Now this is ſo far from being a Rule of Charity, that there is nothing of Charity in it; nothing more oppoſite to the true Spirit of Charity, than ſuch a ſelfiſh Temper.</p>
               <p>But there is too an innocent kind of Self-love, which neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily riſeth out of a Natural Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Self-preſervation; when a Man, notwithſtanding the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and largeneſs of his Mind, doth conſult the Good of others ſo, as not to neglect his own, but takes a due Care of himſelf in the firſt place. This Natural Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:56571:8"/>
every one hath for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and it is attended inſeparably with theſe two Properties;</p>
               <p>Firſt, Every one loves himſelf <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfeignedly</hi> and <hi>Sincerely.</hi> To be ſure, there is no Flattery, no Pretence, no Compliment in this caſe. Our Affections may be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd and truſted, when they ſpeak favourably on our own ſide; for <hi>no Man ever yet hated his own fleſh:</hi> We cannot but wiſh our ſelves well, and thoſe Wiſhes always come from our very Hearts. And according to this Rule the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Law obligeth us to meaſure out our Charity to others: It muſt be <hi>Love without diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> Rom. 12. 9. <hi>Love unfeigned,</hi> 2 Cor. 6. 6. <hi>Love, not in word, or in tongue only, but in deed, and in truth,</hi> Jam. 3. 18. Under colour
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56571:9"/>
of Affection to contrive or help one anothers Misfortunes, is like the Charity of him, who betrayed the Lord Jeſus with a Kiſs. People are not wont to be Traytors to themſelves after ſuch a manner: Though in the Conſequence and Event they many times prove their own Enemies, and the worſt Enemies they have; yet no Man betrays himſelf with <hi>Judas</hi> his <hi>Purpoſe;</hi> the Intention on which we all act is ſtill levelled at that which we believe or ſuppoſe to be good for us: And this is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly to love our Neighbour <hi>as ones ſelf;</hi> to be as really ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous for his Welfare in all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, as for ones own; to have the ſame reality and ſincerity of Purpoſe; to be influenced and animated with the ſame quality and truth of Affection, though
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:56571:9"/>
the Caſe may admit of a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence as to proportion.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Another Property that attends all innocent Love of our ſelf is, that it is <hi>firm</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.</hi> Becauſe it flows from an innate Principle of Self-preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it muſt of neceſſity hold and continue as long as Nature it ſelf laſteth; nor can any Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, Events, or Diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments alter any Man's Temper ſo, as to render him fickle and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteady to himſelf; much leſs diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve the ſtrict Band which ties his own Heart to him, faſter than that which was between the Souls of <hi>Jonathan</hi> and <hi>David.</hi> Why thus too muſt <hi>Brotherly Love con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue,</hi> Hebr. 13. 1. becauſe the Reaſons of Charity are ever the ſame, <hi>viz.</hi> The Obedience we
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:56571:10"/>
owe to the Law of God, and the common Wants among Mankind, which always call for our mutual Pity and Aſſiſtance; there is a conſtant neceſſity for our Minds to be always benevolently and tenderly diſpoſed. And though Reſentments may and oftentimes do unavoidably happen, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Ignorances of ſome, the Paſſions of others, and the Hereditary Infirmities of us all; yet no Provocations or Injuries muſt affect Men ſo, as to harden their Spirits, or fill their Bowels with Gall and Wormwood: Since the fix'd Rule is, that we muſt Love <hi>our Neighbours as our ſelves,</hi> we are no more permitted to be weary of our Charity to other Men, than we permit our ſelves to be weary of doing good to our own Souls.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:56571:10"/>
But there is a higher and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler Rule of Charity yet; and that is, to <hi>Love one another, as the Lord Jeſus himſelf hath loved us.</hi> Becauſe the Love even of ones ſelf may be defective, imperfect, and mixed with ſome Alloy; therefore the great Lover of all our Souls hath made his own Charity to be the Standard and Meaſure of ours. Upon which account he calls it, <hi>A new Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment: A New Commandment give I unto you, that ye love one another; as I have loved you, that ye love one another,</hi> John 13. 34. In reſpect of the Matter of it, the Law of Mutual Charity is an old one; for it hath been written in the Hearts of Men from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, and it was expreſly given to the Jews, <hi>Lev.</hi> 19. 18. It is a New Commandment in reſpect of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:56571:11"/>
that High and Eminent Degree, to which our Bleſſed Saviour hath raiſed it. Men's Charity now muſt bear a Reſemblance of his; Love one another <hi>as I have loved you:</hi> This is the thing which makes it a <hi>New</hi> Commandment indeed.</p>
               <p>The Scripture ſpeaks of three Things eſpecially, which were pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarly remarkable in the Love of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That he extended his Love to open and declared Enemies. The <hi>Old</hi> Commandment which required the Jews to Love their Neighbour as themſelves, permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them to Hate an Enemy; nay, in ſome caſes bound them to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs all manner of Hoſtility a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch as were Aliens to the Faith, and to the Commonwealth
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:56571:11"/>
of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> But ſaith the Apoſtle, God commended his Love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, in that while we <hi>were yet Sinners,</hi> Chriſt died for us; and when we were Enemies, we were reconciled to God by the Death of his Son, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 8, 10. And again, when we were <hi>alienated,</hi> and <hi>Enemies</hi> in our Minds by wicked Works, <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 21. That is, this was a ſtupendous, a moſt amazing Expreſſion of Chriſt's Love, that he undertook the great Work of Redeeming a profligate World, wretched Creatures that had bid God defiance, that were Haters of all that is Good and Holy, and thereby had brought themſelves into a loſt and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable condition: And yet this he did voluntarily, and of his own accord, when there was nothing in the World to move him to it
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:56571:12"/>
but his own infinite Compaſſion, and Tenderneſs only.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond thing that was Peculiar and New in the Love of Chriſt, was, that he was before-hand with his Enemies in theſe Expreſſions of his Goodneſs to them. <hi>Ye have not choſen me, but I have choſen you,</hi> John 15. 16. And, <hi>Herein is Love, not that we loved God, but that he loved us,</hi> 1 John 4. 10. Meaning, that this is a clear and aſtoniſhing demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of his Goodneſs, that in tranſacting the myſterious buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Reconciliation, he was pleaſed to have the firſt hand; that he prevented us with his own early Offers; and ſurpriſed us with Terms of Peace and Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, when no ſuch thing was either deſired, or expected, or
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:56571:12"/>
ſo much as thought of by the World.</p>
               <p>But Thirdly, That which was moſt peculiar of all, moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and wonderful in the Love of Chriſt, was his Dying for his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: There is not in the <hi>Old Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment</hi> a Syllable of any Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations to ſuch an high degree of Charity as this is, of laying down their Lives, no not for their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. And one Reaſon of it is, becauſe length of Days, and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Felicity was the great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, that was plainly and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly promiſed under the Law to ſuch as kept it: And therefore they were not bound by any Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of pure Charity, to part, for any Man's ſake, with that, which was the greateſt Bleſſing the Law could give them. So that Chriſt's
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:56571:13"/>
dying as he did, <hi>the Juſt, for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt;</hi> was the ſublimeſt act of Love that could be; for greater Love than this hath no Man, that a Man <hi>lay down his Life for his Friends,</hi> John 15. 13. Only our Saviour's own Charity was far greater, in laying down his moſt precious Life even for his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
               <p>His Commandment therefore, that we ſhould love one another <hi>as he himſelf hath loved us,</hi> is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together a new one, ſuch Charity was never before required of the World; ſuch Charity was never heard of before: Charity of ſuch a vaſt height and meaſure was quite a new thing. Scarcely for <hi>a Righteous Man will any one die;</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle: <hi>Though perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture for a good Man ſome would even dare to die.</hi> Yet God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:56571:13"/>
his Love towards us, (it was infinitely beyond all the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity that ever had been among Men) <hi>in that while we were yet Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, Chriſt died for us,</hi> Rom. 5. 7, 8.</p>
               <p>By what hath been thus briefly ſpoken, we may now eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the true and genuine Nature of that Charity, which is proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called Chriſtian: It is ſuch a benevolent and tender diſpoſition of Soul as inclines us to do, not thoſe Things only which the Laws of Common Juſtice require us to do, but moreover all ſuch kind and obliging Offices as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes Creatures of the moſt compaſſionate Hearts, and God-like Tempers: To be affected with the ſenſe of other Men's Wants, as well as our own; to pity them as our ſelves; to wiſh and promote their Good with
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:56571:14"/>
ſuch unfeigned Deſires, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearied Endeavours, as if our own Welfare were concern'd: And becauſe the Lord Jeſus vouchſafed to expreſs a common Love to us all, we are to follow his moſt bleſſed Steps, in expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing our Charity to Mankind, as long as we live in the World; to Bleſs and Pray for, and to do good to our very Enemies; to offer them Terms of Accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation; to give them Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of a Reconcileable Temper; to encourage and provoke them to be Reconciled by our own Example; by ſhewing them our own Bowels, and by letting them ſee how kind, humble, meek, long-ſuffering, and patient we our ſelves are; and how ready to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give them. Briefly to have ſuch ardent Affections unto all Men,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:56571:14"/>
and eſpecially to thoſe <hi>who are of the Houſhold of Faith,</hi> as to ſerve them willingly, not only with our Wiſhes, and Labours, and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, but (when need requires) with our very Lives alſo. Tho' Life be ſo dear a matter, that <hi>Skin after Skin, and all that a Man hath he will give for it;</hi> yet upon great Occaſions, and in preſſing Circumſtances, and for weighty and noble Ends, to be ready as the Lord Jeſus was to die for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, after all other Services done for them; this is to have that fervent, and perfect, and true Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which the Chriſtian Religion recommendeth to us <hi>above all Things.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>2. The Quality and Extent of <hi>Chriſtian Charity</hi> being thus ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:56571:15"/>
Explain'd, I proceed now in the ſecond place, to conſider thoſe Motives and Reaſons which ſerve to make it Practical.</p>
               <p>Now to digeſt this Matter into as clear a Method, and under as few Heads as may be, I ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe theſe four Things in general to be conſidered.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. What great Good a Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Temper doth to a Man's own Mind.</item>
                  <item>2. How effectually it helps us to anſwer the Ends of the <hi>New Covenant.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. How near it brings us unto God even in this World.</item>
                  <item>4. How it prepares and fits us for the Everlaſting Happineſs of another.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:56571:15"/>
1. What great Good a Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Temper doth to a Man's own Mind; Though a <hi>Crown</hi> of Righteouſneſs (a Glorious and Perfect Reward) be laid up and reſerved for us againſt the Day of Judgment; yet all Virtue brings us ſomething of a preſent Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. As it cleanſeth the Spirit from the Corruptions of the World, and from the Filthineſs of the Fleſh, ſo it repleniſheth the Soul with the greateſt Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Pleaſure; and by theſe means, as well the Holineſs, as the Joy of a future State, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth here. Now of thoſe Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which at once <hi>purifie,</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light</hi> the Mind, a Spirit of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is One, and perhaps the Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt. It rids the Soul of ſeveral Vices which affect the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:56571:16"/>
with the greateſt Guilt, and therefore muſt of conſequence bring the greateſt Plague; Vices which Crucifie the very Soul, and make every one his worſt Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentor; as Pride, Envy, Malice, and ſuch like. Theſe are pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly called the Sins of the very Devil; and therefore it is fit they ſhould carry a Hell with them. It is impoſſible for ſuch ſcurvy Qualities, to reign in a Breaſt where a Charitable Heart lies. Kind Spirits are not wont to be Haughty, Imperious, and Tyrani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal; eſpecially towards thoſe they really love: Much leſs are they wont to be griev'd, and afflicted at their Proſperity; or to ſeek their Hurt. Such Vices are alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether inconſiſtent with Charity; and they always grow out of ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nature, like Nettles out of a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:56571:16"/>
Dunghil; and methinks Men ſhould ſhun them the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they always ſting the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Mind that is their Nurſery. Hearts that are the proper and kindly Soyl of Virtue, are never ſenſible of this Smart; becauſe they are free from the Cauſes of it; and were the inſides of Men to be throughly diſcovered, I am confident it would be found, that none are ſo eaſie and quiet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, ſo ſatisfied in their Minds, as thoſe that have generous Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for all Mankind: If in ſuch Breaſts there be any Diſſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, it is becauſe their kind En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours are not ſucceſsful; or elſe becauſe they are not able to do all the Good they would. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable Wretches know not the Pleaſure of doing Good; nor what Peace and Complacency re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:56571:17"/>
into ones Boſom by every Charitable Action; nay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by a bare Charitable Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and Deſign, when ſome croſs Accident hinders the Execution of it. Indeed, theſe inward Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts cannot be ſenſibly known, but by Experience; and therefore Arguments of this kind may ſeem very feeble and impertinent to thoſe who love themſelves only, and delight themſelves in ways of Frowardneſs.</p>
               <p>Yet the moſt unexperienc'd People may obſerve very much to this purpoſe, from two palpable Inſtances we find in the Holy Scripture; the one in <hi>Haman,</hi> the other in St. <hi>Paul:</hi> Setting aſide the Story of <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, we meet not with ſuch an Account as that of <hi>Haman;</hi> of his Riches; of his Honour, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:56571:17"/>
of his great Power, as well over <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> himſelf, as over all his Subjects. And yet his Pride, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, and Malice (the Vices I men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd before) over-top't, and bore down all this Greatneſs: One Thing he wanted ſtill, and that was the Compliment of <hi>Morde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cai</hi>'s Knee; and for want of that, nothing would ſatisfie him but the Deſtruction of poor <hi>Mordecai</hi> himſelf, and all the Jews; Rancour and Revenge in the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and that which argued Pains, Griefs, Agonies, and Tortures in his Mind, of the higheſt degree too. So that though the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Wretch boaſted of his Wealth, Glory, and Authority over all the King's Princes; <hi>yet,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>all this availeth me nothing, ſo long as I ſee Mordecai the Jew ſitting at the King's gate,</hi> Eſth. 5. 13.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:56571:18"/>
Strange Torment ſurely, that No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could allay; that all his Splendor was nothing in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of; that neither the Gallows he had provided for <hi>Mordecai</hi> was any thing, if compared with the Rack in his own Breaſt.</p>
               <p>A Spirit of Charity would have ſaved him all that expenſive Vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which his ill Nature put him to, amidſt all his Honours: Half that Charitable Temper, which was ſuch a great Bleſſing to St. <hi>Paul</hi> amidſt all his Troubles; no meer Man ever loved the Souls of People more than he: None was ever more Compaſſionate to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a needy World. None that fled over Land and Seas, with that vigorous Zeal to ſerve Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> did; none that ſuffered ſo much for his great Charity. A ſhort Inventory of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:56571:18"/>
his Hardſhips he himſelf gives us, 2 Cor. 11. <hi>In Labours abundant, in Stripes above meaſure, in Priſons frequent, in Deaths often; of the Jews five times received I forty Stripes ſave one: Thrice was I beaten with Rods, once was I Stoned, thrice I ſuffered Shipwrack, a Night and a Day I have been in the Deep: In Journeying often; in Perils of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; in Perils of Robbers; in Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils by my own Country-men; in Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils by the Heathen; in Perils in the City; in Perils in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; in Perils in the Sea; in Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils among falſe Brethren.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Throughout this whole Series of Hardſhips, we never find the Apoſtle caſt down, or diſconſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late; but on the contrary, always Glorying of his Sufferings, and of his Sufferings only; as <hi>Sorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:56571:19"/>
(ſaid he) <hi>yet always rejoycing,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 10. And the Ground of his Rejoycing was this, the <hi>Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of his Conſcience, that in ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity and godly ſincerity he had had his converſation in the world;</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 12. The comfortable Conſideration, that with an up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right and honeſt Heart he had endeavoured to ſerve Mankind; and to expreſs his great Care of the Churches, which were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to his Charge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> could obſerve, <q>That neither Riches, nor Honour, nor Power, <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> nor any thing elſe, can bring a Man ſuch <hi>Serenity and Divine Pleaſure, as a pure Soul: A Soul from whence good Actions flow, like a gentle and limpid Stream from a clean Fountain.</hi> Though Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes from abroad may af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:56571:19"/>
ſuch a Man, yet compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively they are not ſharp, and right Reaſon can help to take away that little Acrimony that is in them. <hi>It is</hi> (ſaith <hi>Plutarch) an evil Conſcience that is truly do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorous and galling; it is this that creates Griefs from within; Griefs that are more heavy and afflictive than any Accidents from without: As a Feavour in the Blood is far worſe, and much more troubleſom, than the Heat of the Sun.</hi> And therefore the true way to have ſolid Peace within, is to have Minds full of <hi>Probity;</hi> and in ſtead of entertaining any diſhoneſt Purpoſes, to be always Virtuouſly diſpoſed; and above all, to be kindly, and benevolently incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and to do all the Good that lieth in our power.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:56571:20"/>
2. One great Reaſon, why a benign and gracious Temper brings ſuch Advantage to ones own ſelf is, becauſe it is a Ray of the Divine Nature; ſo that by ſearching into his Heart, the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable Perſon cannot but be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted with an humble and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Aſſurance, that he hath much of God himſelf in him. And this is the ſecond Thing we are to conſider, for the exciting of a Spirit of Charity in us; how near it brings us to the ever-bleſſed God, even while we ſtay in the World. <hi>God is Love,</hi> ſaith the Scripture, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4. 8. Not only becauſe all Love is of God, as the Origine and Fountain of it; but becauſe it is one of the infinite Beauties, and Glories of his Nature; ſo eſſential to him,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:56571:20"/>
and ſo perfect in him, that he is the moſt tranſcendent and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Exemplar of Love; made up of it ſo, that he may be well cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>Love it ſelf.</hi> By reaſon of this Love, God extendeth his Goodneſs to all his Creatures, and eſpecially to Mankind; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending and ordering all Things here for their Good: Threatning and Admoniſhing, Commanding and Forbidding, Aſſiſting and Strengthning, Cheriſhing and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtizing them, in order ſtill to that great End, their own Good; and in all the Methods and Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his Providence, expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his Mercy and Tenderneſs towards us, as it is moſt agreeable to his Wiſdom, and as far as it is conſiſtent with the Honour and Authority of a Lawgiver. Nor are the wicked'ſt Men denied a
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:56571:21"/>
Share and Portion of his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. For though by the Rules of ſtrict Juſtice, he might with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any more ado conſign them to everlaſting Miſery, and cut them off in the midſt of their Impieties; yet he offers to all Peace and Reconciliation in, and by, and for the ſake of his Son, whom he ſent into the World to ſeek and to ſave that which was <hi>Loſt,</hi> that whoſoever <hi>believeth in him ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting Life:</hi> And, to expreſs the ſincerity of his Deſire, that none ſhould periſh, but that all ſhould come to Repentance; he daily ſhews the Riches of his Goodneſs, and Forbearance, and Long-ſuffering; that thereby he may lead Wicked Men to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, not to be repented of. Nay, they have their Portion, even of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:56571:21"/>
the Things of this Life too; the the Rebel, and the Runagate, is taken care of, as well as the Heir; nor are any caſt out of the hands of that Provident and Supreme Governour of all Things, who cauſeth <hi>his Sun to ſhine upon the evil and upon the good, and ſendeth Rain on the juſt and the unjuſt,</hi> Mat. 5. 45.</p>
               <p>This great Goodneſs of God towards us all, our Saviour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf makes uſe of, as a powerful Argument and Motive for our Charity and Tenderneſs towards one another. And truly, if we conſider the infinite <hi>Perfections</hi> of God, by reaſon whereof he ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not in the leaſt need of any, nor of all his Creatures; the infinite Greatneſs of his <hi>Majeſty</hi> above us, and its Diſtance from us: By reaſon whereof, he might
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:56571:22"/>
look down upon us with Scorn and Contempt; His infinite <hi>Power</hi> over us, by reaſon whereof, he might eaſily caſt us down into the bottomleſs Lake upon any Provocation: His infinite <hi>Holineſs</hi> and <hi>Excellency,</hi> by reaſon whereof every Provocation comes to be of infinite Demerit; and toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with all this, if we conſider the infinite diſproportion that is between the Sins acted againſt him, and the Faults we commit againſt one another, who ſtand all of us upon the ſame Level, and need all of us each others Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; nor have we any Power over one another, but what is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and precarious: Nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke one another but with Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that are Reciprocal: And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all our mutual Follies, are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to one another too, as
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:56571:22"/>
well for asking, as for accepting each others Pardon; If, I ſay, we conſider all this, we muſt needs diſcover a great deal of Force in this Argumentation, that ſince God ſo loveth us, ſo pitieth us, ſo forbeareth us, ſo expreſſeth his Mercy and Compaſſion to us; certainly we ought alſo, and the rather by much, to Love, and Pity, and forbear and ſhew Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion and Kindneſs unto one another. Love and bleſs, and do good even to them that hate you; <hi>that you may be the Children of your Father which is in Heaven,</hi> ſaith the great Exemplar of Charity, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 45. By the Children of God are meant, (according to the uſual Scripture Senſe of the Phraſe) ſuch People as partake of the <hi>Divine Nature;</hi> ſuch as reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble God, and are like-minded;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:56571:23"/>
ſuch as expreſs a Similitude of thoſe imitable Perfections, which are moſt eminently in Him: For, as our Diſpoſitions and Tempers are, ſo is our Alliance. Thus our Saviour told thoſe wicked Jews in <hi>John</hi> 8. 44. <hi>Ye are of your Father the Devil;</hi> And the Reaſon was, becauſe they did the <hi>Deeds,</hi> and the <hi>Luſts</hi> of the <hi>Devil,</hi> were of Deviliſh Spirits and Inclinations, reſembled the Devil himſelf by their Wickedneſs. Some Sins (as I told you before) are aſcribed unto the Devil after a more pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar manner; as <hi>Pride,</hi> the Sin that caſt him out of Heaven: And <hi>Lying;</hi> for which reaſon he is called a <hi>Lyer,</hi> and <hi>the Father of it,</hi> Joh. 8. 44. And ſo <hi>Slandering;</hi> for which reaſon he is called the <hi>Accuſer of the Brethren,</hi> Rev. 12. 10. So alſo are <hi>Envy</hi> and <hi>Malice</hi> the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:56571:23"/>
Devil's Sins; for which reaſon he is called a <hi>Murderer from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> John 8. 44. And is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to a <hi>Lion that walketh up and down, ſeeking whom he may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour,</hi> 1 Pet. 5. 8. Now, though People that are of ſuch wicked Spirits, may flatter themſelves with a Perſwaſion that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to God; yet in God's own account, you ſee, they are of the Devil's Family, the Devil's Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and conſequently Heirs of the Devil's Damnation; becauſe their Minds are of the ſame Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomous Temper, and of the ſame ugly Hue and Complexion, as if they had been Caſt in the ſame Mould.</p>
               <p>For the ſame Reaſon, they whoſe Souls are pure and upright, full of Grace and <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> are called the <hi>Sons of God,</hi> becauſe
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:56571:24"/>
they communicate of his Divine and Perfect Nature, and reſemble him in the Qualities and Diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of their Minds, as Children are wont to reſemble their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, in the Features and Linea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of their Bodies. Nor can any Man reſemble him better, than by a kind and benevolent Diſpoſition. Becauſe the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth up and down, repreſent this as one of God's chief and moſt glorious Perfections; a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection wherein he himſelf ſeems moſt of all delighted: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Saviour diſcourſing of Mercy, Charity, and an Univerſal Love, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. ſingles out this as the ſtrongeſt Argument to inforce the Practice of it; that we may be the <hi>Children of our Father in Heaven;</hi> and that we may be <hi>perfect, even as our Father which is</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:56571:24"/>
                  <hi>in Heaven is perfect.</hi> 'Tis not any formal Profeſſions that bring us near unto God; 'tis not any dry Superſtitions, or empty Performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; much leſs is it a furious Zeal for Notions and Opinions, (alas! all this may be conſiſtent with a Deviliſh Temper and Mind:) No; it is a God-like Temper; a Divine frame of Heart; and chiefly, a kind, charitable, and beneficent Diſpoſition: It is this, this, that ties us into a ſtrict Relation to God, into ſuch a cloſe Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Communion with him, as maketh us his indeed: As that Diſciple obſerves, whom the Lord Jeſus particularly loved, and who breathed nothing but Love him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: 1 Joh. 4. 7. <hi>Love is of God; and every one that loveth is born of God, and knoweth God:</hi> And again, V. 12. <hi>If we love one another, God</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:56571:25"/>
                  <hi>dwelleth in us, and his Love is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in us.</hi> And again, V. 13. <hi>Hereby we know, that we dwell in him, and he in us, becauſe he hath given us of his Spirit;</hi> (meaning that Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and Affection which is ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in him. And again, V. 16. <hi>God is Love, and he that dwelleth in Love, dwelleth in God, and God in him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here then Men ſhould lay their Hands upon their Hearts, and examine how they beat; what they are full of; and how they are affected: If Wrath and Bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Malice and Rancour, Spight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and Uncharitableneſs, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them; If Self-love, Unmerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and Cruelty <hi>hardens</hi> them; if the Wants and Miſeries of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers make no, or very little Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions upon them; theſe are very bad Symptoms, plain Signs, that there is very little, if any thing
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:56571:25"/>
at all of God in ſuch Hearts; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what ſavours of a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Spirit, of a mean, ſordid, and bruitiſh Nature. Humane, Rational Souls ſhould have more exalted Faculties; Souls that are of a Noble and Heavenly Extraction; Souls that are ſo many Rays of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity; What can ſo become ſuch Beings, as Thoughts that are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial like the Sun-beams? Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions that are as large as the Univerſe? Motions and Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, like his who was the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer of Souls; whoſe whole Life was, <hi>to go about doing Good?</hi> His Miracles, as well as his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons and Laws, were Charity: And by thoſe Charitable Works he ſhewed <hi>himſelf</hi> to be the Son of God; Nor may we think, we can give the World, or our own ſelves, any ſatisfactory Evidence
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:56571:26"/>
of our Relation to his Father or him, but by Works of Charity as his were; by doing Good to every Man as it lies in our power, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Diſcrimination; by Intreating them gently; by bearing Wrongs and Indignities with meekneſs of Spirit; by putting our Cauſe into God's hands without Self-revenge; by bleſſing and wiſhing well to our very Enemies; and by expreſſing our ſincere Affections to all Mankind.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Theſe Things do naturally carry a great deal of Force with them: So that if no Obligations were upon us from any Laws to this purpoſe, the Divine Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of theſe Actions would Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend them to our Practice, becauſe they are God-like Actions; and therefore muſt needs be of the higheſt Excellence in their
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:56571:26"/>
own Nature. But beſides this, we are to conſider yet, in the third place, how helpful a Spirit of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is to us, in anſwering the great Ends of the New Covenant. <hi>The grace of God</hi> (or the Goſpel) <hi>that bringeth Salvation, hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared unto all Men, teaching us, that denying <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodlineſs and World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Luſts, we ſhould live ſoberly, righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly and godly in this preſent World,</hi> Tit. 2. 11, 12. Which ſhews, that the deſign of the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Covenant is, to reclaim Mankind to the Love and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of all manner of Virtue. Becauſe God is a moſt perfect Being himſelf, of infinite Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Rectitude in his Nature; his bleſſed Purpoſe is to imprint upon our Souls his own Image, according to the Capacity of our finite Faculties. And in order
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:56571:27"/>
hereunto he hath given us by his own Son, (the brightneſs of his own Glory) not only the moſt excellent Promiſes; all confirm'd and ſeal'd with his Blood upon the Croſs; but moreover the moſt perfect Example, and the moſt perfective Duties. Now of theſe Duties, this of Univerſal Charity and Love is the Chief. For Love being ſuch a Divine Affection, the Fruits of it muſt needs be Divine too, if it be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere and zealous. As for Inſtance; If our Love to God be pure and hearty, it cannot but move us to a ſolicitous Care, of doing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is repugnant to God's Will and Holineſs; becauſe this Affection is naturally attended with an earneſt deſire to pleaſe and imitate its Object, or the Party we intirely love. So alſo,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:56571:27"/>
if a Man's Love to himſelf be Rational and Regular, it muſt needs put him upon doing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf all the Good, eſpecially all the Spiritual Good, he can; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his Spiritual Part, the Soul, is to live for ever, and therefore requires his tendereſt Care, that it may be everlaſtingly Happy. The ſame Inclination doth true Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity work in us towards all other Men; to be beneficial to them likewiſe, for it always operates ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the nature of the Thing, and according to the condition of the Object. It cannot poſſibly be of any advantage to our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, becauſe he is out of the reach of our Charity, and too high for it. <hi>Can a Man be profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table unto God, as he that is wiſe may be profitable unto himſelf? Is it any pleaſure to the Almighty, that thou art</hi>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:56571:28"/>
                  <hi>righteous? Or is it gain to him, that thou makeſt thy Ways perfect?</hi> Job 22. 2, 3. And again; <hi>If thou be righteous, what giveſt thou him? Or what receiveth he of thy hand?</hi> Job 35. 7. No; all our Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <hi>extendeth not to him,</hi> Pſ. 16. 2. He neither needs it, nor is he ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of being benefited by it; becauſe he is infinitely perfect and happy in himſelf. But our Love to God hath this Effect; it makes us admire and adore him, ſerve and worſhip, and endeavour to pleaſe him, and to be like unto him; and ſo, it is an Inſtrument of <hi>Godlineſs,</hi> as well as of <hi>Sobriety</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs.</hi> In this reſpect it may be ſaid to be a Fulfilling of the <hi>whole</hi> Law, even the firſt Table of it; though indeed it ſerves moſt directly to Fulfil the <hi>Second.</hi> And thus the Apoſtle argues,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:56571:28"/>
Rom. 13. 8, 9, 10. <hi>He that loveth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, hath fulfilled the Law: For this, Thou ſhalt not commit Adultery; thou ſhalt not Kill; thou ſhalt not Steal; thou ſhalt not bear falſe Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; thou ſhalt not Covet; and if there be any other Commandment, it is briefly comprehended in this ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> viz. <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as thy ſelf. Love worketh no ill to his Neighbour; therefore Love is the fulfilling of the Law.</hi> We cannot be Injurious to our own Souls, or to the reſt of Mankind, or to God himſelf, but it muſt proceed from the want of thoſe enlarged Hearts, and thoſe fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, and tender Affections, which the Goſpel requires of us all. Here then we ſhould employ our great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Pains, and uſe our utmoſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, to kindle in us a true Spirit of Charity: For it is <hi>the end</hi>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:56571:29"/>
                  <hi>of the Commandment,</hi> 1 Tim. 1. 5. And becauſe it is the moſt Perfective Grace, the Scripture ſets it above all Things, even above Faith and Hope; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 13. <hi>Now abideth Faith, Hope, Charity, theſe three; but the greateſt of theſe is Charity.</hi> The great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, not only becauſe it is moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to others, which the other two Virtues are not; for Faith and Hope keep at home; a Man belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth for himſelf, and hopeth for himſelf; nor is ones Neighbour the better for them: 'Tis this, that is the active, the diſpenſing Grace, that walks about doing good, and every one fares the better for it:) But 'tis the greateſt Virtue too, becauſe of the three, it is the moſt beneficial to ones ſelf alſo: It gives him ſolid Reaſons for his Hope, which otherwiſe would be groundleſs; and Perfection to his
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:56571:29"/>
Faith, which otherwiſe would be fruitleſs, and conſequently unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable even at home: <hi>The Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite's Hope ſhall periſh; And his Truſt ſhall be as a Spider's Web; Job</hi> 8. 13, 14. A ſorry weak Thing to bear ones Heart up, eſpecially on a Death-bed. For Hope, if it be right, muſt be built upon ſome Promiſe, nor can it go further than the Promiſe it ſelf goes; for if God hath not promiſed me his Mercy, how can I reaſonably hope for it? Now it is plain, that there is no Promiſe of that Nature, but on condition of Charity on our part. The Texts are ſo clear, that they need no Comment: 1 <hi>John</hi> 3. 10. <hi>In this the Children of God are manifeſted, and the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Devil: whoſoever doth not Righteouſneſs is not of God, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he that loveth not his Brother.</hi>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:56571:30"/>
And again, V. 14. <hi>He that loveth not his Brother, abideth in Death,</hi> (or is in a deadly State.) And again, V. 15. <hi>Whoſoever hateth his Brother, is a Murderer; and ye know, that no Murderer hath Eternal Life abiding in him.</hi> Nay, to ſhew how extenſive our Charity muſt be, for our hopes of Mercy at God's hands, our Saviour himſelf hath paſſed this Decretory Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, That there is no Mercy for us, unleſs we ſhew it our ſelves, and that even to our Enemies; <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 15. <hi>If ye forgive not Men their Treſpaſſes, neither will your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forgive your Treſpaſſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for <hi>Faith,</hi> great Things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed are ſpoken of it in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; but withal we are told, that <hi>without Works it is dead;</hi> ſuch a ſpiritleſs, empty Thing without a Life of Virtue, that it no more
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:56571:30"/>
deſerves the Character of a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Faith, than a dead Carkaſs deſerves the Name of a Man. Faith, as it is diſtinguiſhed from Works, ſignifies here an Act of the Underſtanding, whereby a Man owns the Authority of Jeſus Chriſt, and aſſents to his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines. Now this Aſſent of the Mind is required, in order to the Practice of Chriſt's Religion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not imaginable how People can be brought to obey his Laws ſincerely and univerſally, unleſs they be firſt perſwaded in their Hearts, that he was the Son of God, the very Chriſt, ſent by his Father from Heaven to help Mankind thither. This puts a Divine Stamp upon the whole Chriſtian Religion; it gives it an unqueſtionable Credit, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders every the moſt difficult Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:56571:31"/>
of it worthy of all Accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe it came from God, and was revealed by the Son of God; and therefore muſt needs be infallibly true. Upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, the belief of Chriſt's Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and of the Truth, and certainty of his Religion, is the firſt thing neceſſary: And for this Reaſon it was, that his firſt Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples took ſuch pains every where to prove him to be the very Chriſt, and inculcated the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Faith in him: For this was the ready way to bring the World in Obedience to him; and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but this could prevail with Men, to obſerve Chriſt's Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with ſuch ſtrictneſs, as the Primitive Chriſtian did, and for the ſake of it to venture and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo upon all Occaſions the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter loſs of all.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:56571:31"/>
Faith then being required to produce Obedience, as the proper Means in order to this noble End, cannot poſſibly ſtand us in ſtead, if it be only a Notion in our Heads; if it be a liveleſs and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitful Perſwaſion; if it be naked and alone; if it hath not that ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and power upon our Souls, as to bring on the Love and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of thoſe other Virtues and Graces, for the Production where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of it hath been all along intended. Now of thoſe Virtues and Graces, Charity is the very chiefeſt; this muſt accompany our Faith, to make it as it ſhould be, ſuch a Faith as we may ſafely rely on; and therefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> deſcribing that Aſſent of the Mind which availeth indeed, calls it, <hi>Faith which worketh by love,</hi> Gal. 5. 6. Or, as ſome Learned Criticks would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:56571:32"/>
render it, <hi>Faith which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummate and perfected by Charity.</hi> The truth is, all our Notions are very imperfect Things without this; and though theſe Notions be never ſo right and Orthodox, yet are they vaſtly ſhort of our true Duty till they reach our Hearts, and make us to open our Bowels towards other Men, and to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe our Hands in Offices of Love. And therefore, ſince without a Spirit of Charity nothing will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail us, nor anſwer the great Ends of Chriſt's Religion, no not our very Faith, (according to that of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. <hi>Though I have all Knowledge, and all Faith, and give away Goods, Body, Life and all, and have not Charity, it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth me nothing:</hi> Since, I ſay, it is thus) it is of infinite Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to us all, ſo to ſubdue our
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:56571:32"/>
Minds and Paſſions, as to approve our ſelves in this reſpect the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Diſciples of a meek and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Jeſus. Many Voluminous Diſputations have been written, which might have been better ſpared about Faith, and Works, and Juſtification, whether we are juſtified by the one, or the other, or by both; and great Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours have been uſed to Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile St. <hi>Paul</hi> and St. <hi>James</hi> upon this Point: Rather I might ſay, to ſet them at Variance; for their Senſe is the ſame touching the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Works Evangelical; as Piety, Humility, Meekneſs, Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and the like; and very plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and particulary upon the Point of Charity. Here the moſt vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Eye may ſee their clear Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: In Jeſus Chriſt <hi>neither Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion availeth any thing, nor</hi>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:56571:33"/>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion, but Faith which worketh by Love,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> Gal. 5. 6. And, <hi>He ſhall have Judgment without Mercy, that hath ſhewed no Mercy,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>James,</hi> Jam. 2. 13. Therefore in a Caſe, that is ſo poſitively and fully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cided, we ſhould leave Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, and fall to Practice; and ſtudy how to be fruitful in good Works, rather than how to make our Brains Prolifick: This is the right way of performing the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of the Evangelical Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and of bringing Peace and Comfort to our own Minds. I am ſure when we come to die, it will turn to far better account for our poor Souls, than all the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputes, which we ſhall leave be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind us; and which we ſhall leave too, with this great Queſtion which perhaps will never be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:56571:33"/>
Whether Men have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged them with as much Truth as Uncharitableneſs?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Fourthly, A Charitable Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſerves to prepare and fit us for the Everlaſting Happineſs of another Life. Many Virtues are required to diſpoſe us for the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of that Happineſs, to make us capable of it; to render us <hi>meet to be partakers of the Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance of the Saints in Light,</hi> Col. 1. 12. Neither will the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, nor the Power, nor the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God, bring us to that Frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, without due Qualifications on our part; becauſe there can be no true Happineſs but where there is a Correſpondence and Suitableneſs between the Mind and the Thing; if a Man be not pleaſed with what he Enjoys, nor
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:56571:34"/>
finds any delightful Reliſh in it; it is impoſſible for him to be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py by enjoying it; nor can Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it ſelf be a place of Pleaſure to thoſe, whoſe Minds have as little Taſte of thoſe Divine Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factions, as a vitiated Palate hath of the moſt pleaſant Meats and Drinks.</p>
               <p>To prepare our ſelves for thoſe Delights, it is neceſſary to trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form our Souls into the love of them now; and to accuſtom our ſelves now; to the familiar and delightful Practice of thoſe Virtues, wherein the Felicity of another Life doth really conſiſt: Of which Virtues, a charitable Diſpoſition is one, and a very great one; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we ſhall be ſure to carry that Diſpoſition with us out of this World to continue with us everlaſtingly, and to make us hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:56571:34"/>
indeed in the enjoyment of a ſuitable Society of Bleſſed Spirits which are all made up of Love. <hi>Charity never faileth,</hi> ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 8. <hi>Whether there be Prophecies, they ſhall fail; whether there be Tongues, they ſhall ceaſe; whether there be Knowledge, it ſhall vaniſh away:</hi> But Charity endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth for ever; it is an inſeparable Glory of the Souls of juſt Men made perfect. And this is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Reaſon, why Charity is ſet above Faith and Hope, becauſe it is of infinite Duration: As it is the moſt beneficial, ſo it is the moſt laſting Virtue. <hi>Faith is the Evidence</hi> (or firm Perſwaſion) <hi>of Things not yet ſeen,</hi> Heb. 11. 1. And when we come to behold God Face to Face, it will be no longer Faith, but Viſion. And ſo Hope is the expectation of Things
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:56571:35"/>
that are future; and when we come to the actual Poſſeſſion of them, it will be no longer Hope, but Fruition or Enjoyment. But Love is of an unchangeable Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, nor will it ever ceaſe, becauſe it is a Ray of the Immutable and Everlaſting God. This is the Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of Heaven, that though there be different Ranks and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Angels; different States of Beautified Spirits, different De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Glory: And though God himſelf be infinitely exalted above all; yet Love is the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Principle and Perfection, which unites God, and all his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Creatures with him, into one inviolable Communion.</p>
               <p>This being the State of the other World, how can we be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the Enjoyment of it, or be fit to take pleaſure in it, unleſs
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:56571:35"/>
we be Connaturaliz'd to it by a correſpondence and agreeableneſs of Temper? Some thoughtful and wiſe Philoſophers among the old Heathens went upon this Principle, that <hi>all Happineſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in the Perfection of Nature.</hi> And they did not only believe, <q>That the Soul is Immortal, and ſhall find the Rewards of <note place="margin">Simptic. in Epicte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> Virtue, after its depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from the Body; But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved too, That its Felicity after Death lieth in ſuch a perfection of its Faculties, and Powers, as is moſt ſuitable to a Rational Being: That is, in perfectly knowing every Thing which it is capable of knowing; and in perfectly loving and doing Things that are moſt Excellent.</q> Theſe are great Notions from Men that had not the benefit of Divine Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:56571:36"/>
Nor do we find any thing in them, but what is highly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the Chriſtian Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, for <hi>when that which is perfect is come,</hi> we ſhall be like God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the Rectitude and Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of our Nature, according to the Capacities of Created Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: And Charity, being the greateſt and moſt God-like Virtue, every perfected Soul muſt needs be conformable to the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by it; which yet is not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for any Soul to be, but by exerciſing in this Life all thoſe good Acts, which ſerve to form it unto a Charitable Temper. For this Temper is acquired as other Habits are, by the conſtant Repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of Actions; which are therefore to be our Care and Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in this World, becauſe Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is a place not for the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:56571:36"/>
but for the conſummating of a Life of Virtue: Nor can Death ſo alter and change a Man's whole State, as to furniſh his Soul with Inclinations and Qualities, quite contrary to thoſe it contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in the Fleſh; ſo that if we be not charitably affected now, we do but flatter our ſelves with vain and lying Hopes of a Bleſſed Eternity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Though I have the Gift of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy, and underſtand all Myſteries, and all Knowledge, and though I have all Faith, ſo that I could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move Mountains, and have no Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, I am nothing. And though I beſtow all my Goods to feed the Poor, and though I give my Body to be burned, and have not Charity, it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth me nothing;</hi> ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 2, 3. For as it is
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:56571:37"/>
God's Will and Purpoſe, that Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable Souls ſhall not by any means come into his Preſence, ſo the very Nature of the Thing renders their Acceſs impoſſible; becauſe they are not fit to be Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of thoſe Pleaſures, which are at God's right hand for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. Hatred and Malice, Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour and Revenge, Spightfulneſs and Envy, are the Works of Hell, and the Diſpoſitions of thoſe who are going apace thither; nor are they fit to be in any Society, but that of Devils and damned Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, to whom they are already a-kin by Vice, and into whoſe Company they are prepared to be gathered by an aſſimilation and likeneſs of Nature. Upon this account it concerns us as much as our Everlaſting Happineſs is worth, by all poſſible Acts of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:56571:37"/>
Charity to bring our Minds to ſuch a loving Frame and Genius, as, when we die, may be ſuitable to the State and Condition of Heaven.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, ſome particular Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Charity will ceaſe there, becauſe there will be no need of them among the Bleſſed. There will be no need of Alms-giving, becauſe in Heaven there are no manner of Wants. There will be no need of Mutual Forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, becauſe in Heaven there are no Injuries and Affronts: Nor will there be any need of bearing with one another's Infirmities, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in Heaven there is neither Sin, nor Error: However, theſe and the like Acts of Charity muſt be performed and repeated by us here on Earth, becauſe in their kind they all ſerve as Means in
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:56571:38"/>
order to the main End; to cleanſe the Mind from all Leaven of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and Naughtineſs, to raiſe and improve the Soul by degrees, to perfect it inſenſibly by an Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Love, and to produce in it a true, Heavenly Temper, though they be of no further uſe to us, when once we come to the actual Poſſeſſion of an Heavenly State. To illuſtrate this a little by a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar Similitude: In the training up of a Youth in the ordinary courſe of Learning, many leſſer Rules are neceſſary in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; a long Method, great Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, many Obſervations, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſorts of Exerciſes, are neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary in the Progreſs; and all theſe help in their kind to improve ones Parts inſenſibly, and to make at laſt a compleat Scholar, though in the courſe of his Studies ſome
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:56571:38"/>
of theſe Things are apt to drop out of his Memory: And when he comes to be a Man, and a Man of great Knowledge and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, many of them are quite forgotten and loſt; becauſe they ceaſe from being of any further uſe, the Practice of them is no longer neceſſary; but yet the Noble Effect, which by the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Practice of them was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, doth remain to the laſt; namely, an Underſtanding now poliſhed and perfected to a very high pitch by an Univerſal Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: The ſubſervient Rules and Method are laid aſide, and gone, many of them; but the Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the main Faculties, and the Improvement of his Parts, holds as long as his Life conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues. It is much after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that a Man is trained up, and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:56571:39"/>
diſciplined into a perfect Saint. Several ſorts of Charity are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of us now, which are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to a Militant State, to a needy, ſuffering Condition; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they muſt ceaſe of courſe, when we come to a State of Bliſs and Glory.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs they are at preſent wonderfully Advantageous to us, becauſe they do more or leſs all contribute towards Perfection; they all ſerve in their kind, and in ſome meaſure, to bring the Soul to an habit of Univerſal Love, and ſo to fit it for that bleſſed Place above, into which nothing that is Uncharitable can enter.</p>
               <p>By the Co-operation of every Charitable Act, the Soul is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd by degrees, though we may not perceive its gradual Proficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy every moment: It is the more
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:56571:39"/>
and more improved and height<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned towards Heaven; and the more and more accompliſhed for it ſtill; ſo that when it departs out of the Body, a State of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Peace, and perfect Harmony, and perfect Love, is the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for it; nay, (if I may ſo ſpeak) the only <hi>Natural State</hi> for it to be in: And then the Soul finds the Noble Effects of every Work of Love; the Divine Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits which every Work helped to produce, and the Unſpeakable Perfection every Work did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare it for; though in its flight to Heaven it droppeth ſome Works, and leaves them behind it, as the Prophet did his Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle.</p>
               <p>Men talk at random when they ſpeak of going to Heaven with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Charitable Temper: they
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:56571:40"/>
may as well ſpeak of ſeeing the Lord <hi>without Holineſs;</hi> for Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is one great part of Holineſs. And therefore our great Care muſt be, to mould our Hearts into ſuch a Frame and Condition, that we may be fit and agreeable Company for the Glorious Family of Love. And this is not to be done, but by uſing and accuſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſelves to the conſtant Practice of Univerſal Charity now. For Habits are gotten by many Repeated Acts; and to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the ſeveral Offices of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is, both the effectual Means of gaining a Spirit of Charity, and a plain Argument and Token too, that there is ſuch a Spirit in us, eſpecially when thoſe Performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Acts are more and more abundant.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:56571:40"/>
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>3. Which brings me to the third Thing, that in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this Diſcourſe I propoſed to ſhew; namely, the Way and Manner after which our Chriſtian Charity is to be expreſſed. For thoſe Expreſſions are manifold and various; and thoſe People are mightily deceived, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain and limit all Charity to Alms-giving.</p>
               <p>That indeed is one Expreſſion of Charity, when our Alms come from a Charitable Heart; for if that be wanting, all our Alms loſeth the Name of Charity. <hi>Though I give all my Goods to feed the Poor, and have not Charity, it profiteth me nothing,</hi> 1 Cor. 13. 3. You ſee, that in the Apoſtle's ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:56571:41"/>
Alms-Deeds may be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Charity; that is, when Vanity or Oſtentation is the Principle from whence they flow. But though they come from a right Principle, from a kind and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate Heart, yet are they but a little part of Charity; as we find by St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Deſcription of its ſeveral Branches in the place above-mentioned.</p>
               <p>Now becauſe we cannot fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low a better Guide than St. <hi>Paul,</hi> I ſhall proceed upon this Subject according to thoſe Noble Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters which he himſelf gives there of Charity; intending as I go along to diſcourſe of thoſe Things after a particular and diſtinct man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; which the holy Apoſtle hath laid together within the compaſs of a few, but very ſignificant and comprehenſive Expreſſions.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:56571:41"/>
1. And there are two Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters given of Charity, in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to <hi>Anger.</hi> The firſt teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us to be very <hi>Slow to Anger-Charity</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Paul) ſuffereth long;</hi> Meaning, that a Charitable Man is not preſently moved out of a calm and compoſed State.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond teacheth us to <hi>moderate</hi> our Paſſion, that it may not ſwell beyond a due meaſure, when there is any juſt and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient cauſe of Reſentment, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 5. <hi>Charity,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>is not eaſily provoked;</hi> ſo indeed it is render'd in our Common Tranſlation; but rather it ſhould be render'd, <hi>Is not highly provoked,</hi> or <hi>exaſperated;</hi> Meaning, that for Charity-ſake no Man muſt ſuffer, no not any juſt Anger to turn into Fury, ſo as
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:56571:42"/>
to make him either to meditate Revenge, or to fall into indecent Rages.</p>
               <p>Now though theſe be two di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Subjects, the one touching the Riſe, the other touching the Progreſs of this Paſſion; yet becauſe both may eaſily fall under one Conſideration, I ſhall ſpeak of both at this time, and in this place, as far as they relate to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject Matter of Chriſtian Charity; leaving ſome other Things more particularly to be conſider'd, when I ſhall have opportunity and lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to form ſome Practical Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes more upon other Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Virtues, and upon that of <hi>Meekneſs</hi> among the reſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anger</hi> is not Univerſally Evil; for the Apoſtle's Direction is, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 26. <hi>Be ye angry, and ſin not:</hi> Which ſhews, that all manner of
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:56571:42"/>
Anger is not ſinful. But there are three ſorts which are inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with the Law of Charity, and very diſpleaſing unto God.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Raſh Anger; when a Man is apt to be ſoon offended, and to let his Paſſions take fire preſently, not fairly examining the Nature and Circumſtances of the ſuppoſed Provocation, nor conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering throughly, as he ought, whether there be juſt and reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable cauſe for Diſpleaſure. This is a wicked Diſpoſition, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from Pride, Capriciouſneſs, and ill Nature; and it looks as if the froward Creature <hi>watched</hi> for his Neighbours <hi>Haltings,</hi> and wanted only an opportunity of Quarrelling; and took Delight and Pleaſure in a Life of Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and in rendring himſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:56571:43"/>
and vexatious to others. This is far from favouring of the true Spirit of Charity, eſpecially as it is raiſed by the Law and Example of Jeſus Chriſt, whoſe Love to us ought to be the Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard, and Meaſure of our Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to one another. But beſides this, the Effects which follow our unreaſonable Paſſions are very hurtful and injurious, when Things are taken amiſs raſhly, and with ſuch a quick hand. For we are all apt to be miſtaken, and then moſt likely when Men's Actions are not permitted, to fall under our due Conſideration: But we run away headlong, and in great haſt upon indeliberate Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. In this caſe Innocence it ſelf too often ſuffers; by reaſon that the Merits of the Cauſe are not calmly inquired into at the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:56571:43"/>
firſt, and Men are hardly perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to examine them afterwards, becauſe few care to be thought guilty of an Error. By means hereof, a long Train of Miſchief followeth; Paſſion ſtill growing higher and hotter than at the firſt kindling. And therefore, when our Paſſions begin to be warm, we ſhould have an Eye to the Fewel; conſider the Cauſe which blows the Spark; give our ſelves time to think, and to think as candidly and favourably as we can, leſt we go on to puniſh Men quite contrary to the Laws of Charity, and Juſtice too, not ſo much for their Crimes, as for our own falſe Preſumptions; and if we would do this very careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that is, give room for Thought and favourable Conſideration, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we lift up the hand, it would
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:56571:44"/>
both leſſen the Paſſion, and either ſtop, or moderate the Effects of it.</p>
               <p>Secondly; Though Anger be Juſt, in reſpect of its Cauſe; yet if it laſteth a longer time than it ſhould, it is Sinful. The ſooner our Reſentments go out, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it is for our ſelves, and others: And beſt of all when they die preſently after they are conceiv'd; when a Man's Anger is like the Fool's Mirth, which <hi>Salomon</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares to the <hi>crackling of Thorns</hi> on a Flame, that vaniſheth in a few moments; for glowing Coals are very dangerous; the longer ones Diſpleaſure continues, the more averſe he is to Purpoſes and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of Charity; the ſtiffer in his Reſentments, the more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexible, and the harder to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled.
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:56571:44"/>
That which ſhould have been but a tranſient Fit, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitates in time, and ſetleth into a fixt Habit; and that ranckles and frets inwardly, and eateth ſo deep, and ſo venomouſly into the Bowels, that it proves a deadly Ulcer; and then it ends, as in the caſe of the Spleen, which was once a natural and innocent Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, but at laſt becomes a very painful and miſchievous Diſeaſe. The Apoſtle therefore gives us all this Noble Rule of Charity; <hi>Let not the Sun go down upon your Wrath,</hi> Epheſ. 4. 26. This looks as if it were a Branch of the Law of Nature: For <hi>Plutarch</hi> tells us of thoſe ancient <hi>Pagans</hi> the Diſciples of <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Plutarch de Frat. amore.</note> 
                  <q>That if there happen'd any Differences or Brawlings between them in the Day, their
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:56571:45"/>
cuſtom was to ſhake hands, and ſalute one another before the ſetting of the Sun.</q> Anger is ſuch a bruitiſh Thing, that they thought it unbecoming Men and Philoſophers, to carry it in their Boſoms to Bed. But St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Reaſon was of a higher Nature; for the Evening was ever a time of Devotion; and we muſt part with our Paſſions before the cloſe of the Day, leſt a mixture of Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred pollute our Evening Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and infect our Prayers, ſo as to turn them into an Abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The Learned <hi>Grotius</hi> looks upon it as a Phraſe, that was uſual among the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> when they meant the putting any Matter off to a longer time: And ſo indeed we find it in <hi>Deut.</hi> 24. 15. <hi>At his day thou ſhalt give the Hireling his hire, neither ſhall the Sun go down</hi>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:56571:45"/>
                  <hi>upon it.</hi> Which is otherwiſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd, though to the ſame effect, <hi>Lev.</hi> 19. 13. <hi>Thou ſhalt not defraud thy Neighbour, neither rob him, the Wages of him that is hired, ſhall not abide with thee all night until the morning.</hi> Well, though we ſuppoſe the Apoſtle's Expreſſion to be Proverbial, yet <hi>Grotius</hi> reckons it an Application of that Law, <hi>Deut.</hi> 21. 23. <hi>That the Body of every Criminal that was hanged, was to be buried before night.</hi> And then St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Argument is the ſtronger ſtill: For if Puniſhments inflicted by Publick Authority were not to continue till the Evening; much leſs may any Private Differences or Grudges hold till Sun-ſet.</p>
               <p>Anger is for the moſt part a Criminal, and too often proves an Homicide; and 'tis good to
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:56571:46"/>
throw it aſide, and to commit it unto the Grave betimes: If we let it ſleep with us, and not rid it quite out of the way, the next day's Sun will give it a new heat, and make it outrageous.</p>
               <p>For Thirdly, This Paſſion doth many times grow and ſwell to ſuch a bulk, that nothing will ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie it but Revenge: It riſeth by degrees, if not quell'd in time, from Raſh to Inordinate; from Inordinate to Implacable; from Implacable to Revengeful: And then is Anger ſinful in the higheſt degree of all; when it breedeth Gall and Choler to that extremity, that the Stomach will not be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied without a Glut of Revenge. This chiefly is that <hi>Bitterneſs</hi> and <hi>Wrath,</hi> which the Holy Scripture ſo ſeverely condemneth: <hi>For it</hi>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:56571:46"/>
                  <hi>worketh not the Righteouſneſs of God, Jam.</hi> 1. 20. It carrieth a Man beyond a poſſibility of doing Things that are right in God's Eyes; for its Deſigns and Actions are ſtill miſchievous, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is direct Enmity againſt God and Man. Charity is quite forgotten, though the Wretches own Pardon can never be ſealed without it. Juſtice is not heard, though it cry never ſo loud; The violent Creature conſiders not what is Juſt, but what may be Hurtful. The Laws of Chriſt are trampled under foot, though they were intended to ſweeten all our Tempers, to ſmooth and ſoften our Spirits, to render us Humane, Meek, Patient, Gentle, Courteous, Merciful and Benign. The Revengeful Man ſtands in ſturdy Oppoſition againſt all; nor
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:56571:47"/>
is there any Miſchief againſt his Inclinations, if it be within his power; eſpecially if he can act it with ſafety. Neither are ones Fortunes, nor ones Credit, nor ones very Life ſecure, if within the reach of a Revengeful Arm. Nor do I think, that Humane Nature is capable of a more Wicked Diſpoſition than this is; becauſe it ſticks at nothing which lies in its way, though never ſo Mean and Baſe, never ſo Diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and Scandalous, never ſo Barbarous and Cruel.</p>
               <p>Therefore, to beget in our Hearts a Spirit of true Chriſtian Charity, to Nouriſh and to Expreſs it alſo, here we ſhould begin to Subdue our Minds, to Tame and Govern our wild Paſſions, and to bring our ſelves to a due Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rament and Compoſure: Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:56571:47"/>
what a crowd of Buſineſs we are in here, and what a juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling World this is, we muſt not expect, but that there will be Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences. But then we ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that we are all of us one Man's Children; made of the ſame Fleſh and Blood, ſubject to the ſame Follies and Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and for that Reaſon are equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obliged all of us, to take Pity and Compaſſion upon one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. There is not one of us, but ſtands in need of an Atone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: And the right way of making it is, not by Sacrificing our Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; (that will encreaſe our Guilt, in ſtead of being an acceptable Oblation;) but to ſerve the brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh part of our Nature, our Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable Paſſions, as the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents were wont to ſerve their Cattel; to bring them to the Fire,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:56571:48"/>
and make them Victims. But to ſpeak more particularly: You ſee how many ways Anger becometh Sinful; and to keep our ſelves In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, we muſt be very careful to expreſs our Charity, by order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and behaving our ſelves Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably in every reſpect.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Govern the Beginnings of Paſſion, after a Charitable manner. Do not preſently give up Reaſon to Spleen; nor ceaſe to be Men, becauſe you conceive your ſelves affronted. But Pauſe a while; Conſider, Think, Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, Argue in your Minds with Calmneſs, with Deliberation, and with Candour. Before there be an Eruption of Choler, I wiſh People would attentively repeat the Lord's Prayer; it might be a good means of teaching them to
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:56571:48"/>
be Charitable unto others, by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Charitable unto themſelves; and by begging God's Pardon for their own Treſpaſſes, to forgive thoſe that Treſpaſs againſt them. It was the Advice of a Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher to <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> 
                  <q>That when he was moved, he ſhould Read over the <hi>Greek</hi> Alphabet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſpoke, or did any thing.</q> For Men ſeldom do any thing in Anger, but what they do amiſs, and aftewards repent of. Paſſion is an ill Councellor, and a worſe Executioner: And therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Foot or the Hand ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, 'tis good to Delay, and to take Time: In that Time, ask your ſelves a few Queſtions; Whether the Provocation be Juſt? Whether it be not Inconſiderable, and beneath the Cognizance of a Rational Creature, that ought to
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:56571:49"/>
have a great Mind, above the reach of every Trifle? Whether the Offender be not a good Man in the main? Whether he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf had no Provocations? Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he did it not through the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity and Weakneſs of Humane Nature? Whether it was not Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſigned? Whether Ignorance, Imprudence, or Inadvertency, was not the Cauſe of it? Whether your Folly will not be as great as his, or perhaps greater? Whether he doth not Repent? Whether you do not intend to Repent your ſelf? Why your Repentance ſhould be conſidered, and not his? Whether your Patience, Lenity, and Greatneſs of Mind, will not oblige him, and make him love you? And, Whether the poor Man may not have one time or other a fair opportunity of making
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:56571:49"/>
you Amends? 'Tis odds, but by that time theſe Things are well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, your Blood will cool, and be brought to a Temper; and then you will have gained a Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Nay, you will have gained your ſelf; you will have the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of your ſelf; you will be a Winner in both reſpects; you will go off with the Comfort and Honour of a double Conqueſt, and each gotten with a very gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Hand.</p>
               <p>If, for want of due Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Fit continueth ſome hours, you muſt, Secondly, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern the Fever ſo, as to keep it from being Hectick. There is a time for all Things under the Sun, and then it is high time for you to expreſs your Charity when the Sun is ready to ſet. Cool
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:56571:50"/>
Thoughts ſhould be for the Night; and when the Hurries of the Day are over, we ſhould leave off Wrath, and let go Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure too. An Implacable Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per is very Offenſive to the Divine Being, becauſe it is utterly void of Charity, and true Religion. By the Laws of Chriſtianity, every one hath a Right to his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour's Mercy; eſpecially if he be ſorry for his Faults, and deſires Forgiveneſs. That indeed every Offender is bound to do; and the leaſt he can do, is to ask Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don; yet that is enough, where the Injury is not ſo great, as to require Satisfaction. Repentance and Intreaties are Satisfaction ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient in common and ordinary Caſes: And when a Man hath gone thus far, he hath acted like a Chriſtian, and may ſafely put
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:56571:50"/>
his Cauſe into God's hand, who is an <hi>Avenger</hi> of all that are <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with Wrong.</hi> But the Wretch that hardeneth his Heart, and ſtoppeth his Ear againſt Chriſtian Application, contracteth Guilt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable: His own Sins are all bound; no outward Acts of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion avail him, for want of a Charitable Spirit within; his very Prayers are ſtopt; for how ſhall God hear him, that heareth not his Brother? He heapeth daily ſuch a Load of Sins upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as makes him uncapable of the Mercy of that good God, who expects no other Satisfaction at our hands, for the Affronts againſt his own Majeſty, but our Repentance and Prayers.</p>
               <p>Let us hear our Great Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver, <hi>Luke</hi> 17. 3, 4. <hi>Take heed unto your ſelves; If thy Brother</hi>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:56571:51"/>
                  <hi>treſpaſs againſt thee, rebuke him; and if he repent, forgive him: And if he treſpaſs againſt thee ſeven times in a day, and ſeven times in a day turn again to thee, ſaying, I Repent, thou ſhalt forgive him.</hi> Nay, I very much queſtion, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Chriſtian may ſtay for an Offender's Repentance in every Caſe. For St. <hi>Matthew</hi> delivers us that Law of Charity without that Condition, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. And if our Saviour's Love to us, be the Rule and Standard of our Love to one another; it ſeems to be our Duty, and that which beſt becomes the Generous Spirit of a Chriſtian, to be beforehand with our Enemies, as Chriſt was with his: And even for the Offended Party to endeavour for Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as He did; though but in hopes of their Repentance.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:56571:51"/>
But, Thirdly, Let a Provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be never ſo juſt, and Reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments never ſo long-liv'd, we muſt above all Things beware of all Actions, and of all Intentions that are Revengeful. For Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of this kind are a moſt horrible Violation of the Laws of Religion, Charity, and Humanity alſo. They are for Miſchief and Hurt only; and therefore Savour of the Devil's Temper, and Seal a Man up to Eternal Flames. It is a dreadful thing to want Bowels, I may call it, a great Curſe; for a Man ſeldom comes to that high pitch of Inhumanity, as to have a hardned Heart, but by the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, though the Work be a Man<hi>'s</hi> own; yet ſo it is, that a Trade of Uncharitableneſs draws on Cruelty: So that by
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:56571:52"/>
putting off the <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> People learn by degrees to throw aſide <hi>Man</hi> too; whereas the Deſign of our Religion is, rather to make us <hi>Angels.</hi> To this purpoſe we are ſtrictly commanded, not to Avenge our ſelves; not to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſe Evil for Evil; but to overcome Evil with Good; to be Patient, Merciful, and Kind; if an Enemy Hunger, to Feed him; if he Thirſt, to give him Drink; and thus to heap Coals of Fire upon his Head; not to hurt, but to in-tender and melt him.</p>
               <p>I do not deny, but great Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Caution may be uſed in Treating ſuch as have done us conſiderable Wrongs: For tho' we are bound to forgive them, and to wiſh them well, as ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as we wiſh our ſelves, and to do them good Offices; yet we
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:56571:52"/>
are not obliged to love them in an equal degree and proportion, nor to take them again into our Boſom, (at leaſt not preſently) who have already wounded us to the quick. However, all manner of Revenge is utterly unlawful. Revenge is, not when a Man puniſheth an Offender juſtly, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately, and with a charitable Purpoſe of doing him, or others Good, (ſo Parents puniſh their very Children, and Magiſtrates a Delinquent;) but when he thirſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to wreak, and execute his Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, only, or chiefly, to ſatisfie an enraged Mind, and with a cruel Deſign, to grieve, afflict, or tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment his Neighbour. This is extream Wickedneſs in a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; a Thing that was Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned even by the wiſer Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens: Nay, that which was not
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:56571:53"/>
permitted, the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves to do with their own private Hands, though ſome Things were permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them for the Hardneſs of their Hearts: They were allowed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to require <hi>an Eye for an Eye,</hi> and <hi>a Tooth for a Tooth;</hi> but this was to be done by the Magiſtrates Hand; the reſt of the <hi>Jews</hi> had a common ſtanding Law given them, <hi>Lev.</hi> 19. 18. <hi>Thou ſhalt not avenge</hi> (thy ſelf,) <hi>nor bear any Grudge againſt the Children of thy People.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All manner of Revenge is now ſinful, though it be ſought even of Publick Authority; and that too under another Name, and with ſpecious Colours. Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is the higheſt Improvement of Virtue; and the Laws of it are ſo ſtrict and perfect, ſo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime and pure, that all Tinctures
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:56571:53"/>
of Malice and Ill-will are a Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of them. The Spirits of Chriſtians ſhould be above all ſuch baſe Alloy; they ſhould be refined and raiſed to that high and noble Pitch, and true Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as to paſs by Affronts with Meekneſs and Charity, and (if it be poſſible) with Slightings and Diſdain. This is that true Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Nobleneſs of Mind, which becomes us all. For it is rightly obſerved by <hi>Plutarch,</hi> and other old Moraliſts who have written againſt our Unreaſonable and Fooliſh Paſſions, That Deſires of Revenge proceed from a Defect in Nature, from Infirmity and Weakneſs; from ſomething that is Little, and Mean; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thoſe Creatures are moſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to it, which are moſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible: Bees and Waſps, and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:56571:54"/>
thoſe Infects among Mankind too, which therefore bite, and ſting, and vex, and wound, becauſe they are of low and fordid Spirits. <q>Wrath (ſaith <hi>Plutarch)</hi> doth ſome Things that are terrible, and ſome that <note place="margin">Plutarch de ira cohib.</note> are ridiculous: And therefore of all the Paſſions we are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to, this is the moſt hated, and the moſt deſpiſed.</q> A plain Argument, that this Paſſion is of the meaneſt Extraction; that it proceeds from the moſt abject, degenerate, and fordid Natures; from Slime and Dirt that is utterly inconſiſtent with the Purity of Religion.</p>
               <p>That Holy and Juſt One, who deſcended from Heaven to cleanſe, raiſe, and perfect our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, took great care to rid us of all this Filth, by the nobleſt Precepts,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:56571:54"/>
and by his own (the nobleſt and moſt perfective) Example. The Infinite Excellence and Dignity of his Divine Nature, made all Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences againſt him ſwell to infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite degrees of Guilt, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently rendred the Actors of them liable to all the degrees of Puniſhment, which infinite Juſtice might have inflicted. And yet, with what evenneſs of Mind did he endure all Reproaches, Contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melies, Diſgrace, Stripes, Buffet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Wounds, Nails, and Croſs too? He bore all, though from the rudeſt, the vileſt, the moſt malicious Hands, with Patience and Lenity; with Meekneſs and Self-denial; with Humility and Reſignation; with Candour and the higheſt Charity to the laſt Gaſp. <hi>When he was reviled, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viled not again; when he ſuffered,</hi>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:56571:55"/>
                  <hi>he threatned not, but committed himſelf to him that judgeth righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly,</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 23. And what was this for? Why (ſaith the Apoſtle) Chriſt ſuffered for us, leaving us an Example, that we ſhould follow his Steps.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <p>4. Having thus diſcourſed of the two Characters of <hi>Charity</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to <hi>Anger,</hi> and ſhew'd how we are to expreſs this great Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Grace in each reſpect; by Commanding, Governing, and Moderating that miſchievous Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I proceed now to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the next Property, which is called Kindneſs; <hi>Charity ſuffereth long, and is Kind:</hi> Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that a Charitable Perſon is Compaſſionate, and Beneficent,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:56571:55"/>
both in Diſpoſition and Actions; ready in every reſpect to do all the Good he can. By giving us a Deſcription, St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſhews us a Duty; and he opens it particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly in another place, which ſeems to be an Explication of this whole Verſe; <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 31, 32. <hi>Let all Bitterneſs, and Wratb, and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and Clamour, and Evil-ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, be put away from you with all Malice; And be ye kind one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> The <hi>Greek</hi> Word in both places is in effect the ſame; and the Apoſtle's meaning is, that in ſtead of hating and maligning one another, we ſhould be tenderly affected, and uſeful to each other, ready from our Hearts to do one another all the good Offices which lie in our Power. Now for the due Practiſing of this Matter, the Laws of Charity
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:56571:56"/>
require of us theſe following Things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That we have a true inward <hi>Senſe</hi> of other Men's Wants and Afflictions. This is that which the Holy Scripture calls <hi>Tender-heartedneſs,</hi> Epheſ. 4. 32. <hi>Bowels of Mercy,</hi> Coloſ. 3. 12. And, <hi>Having Compaſſion one of another,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 8. By which Expreſſions is meant, that we ſhould Sympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thize with all that are in Diſtreſs, and have a Fellow-feeling of one anothers Afflictions. For where Men's Hearts are ſo hard, and cruſty, that their Brethren's Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities make little or no Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions upon them, there it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for Charity to be ſo Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Free, and Generous, as the Laws of Chriſtianity do require. <hi>Whoſo hath this World's good, and</hi>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:56571:56"/>
                  <hi>ſeeth his Brother hath need, and ſhutteth up his Bowels of Compaſſion from him; how dwelleth the Love of God</hi> (or of Man) <hi>in him?</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 3. 17. It holdeth true in all Caſes, as well as in that of Alms-giving; for the Heart is the Spring of all our Actions: And it is as hard for Charity to take its due courſe and ſcope, where the Bowels are ſhut up, as for a River to run, where the Fountain is quite dried up: Rocks many times yield a Stream, but a Stony Heart never; to be ſure, not that Liberal Supply of any kind, which the Neceſſities of miſerable Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects call for. Therefore thoſe Old Philoſophers were cruelly miſtaken, who, though they were for outward Offices of Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; yet thought it unbecoming Reaſonable Natures, and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:56571:57"/>
with a Man's Happineſs, to be moved with Compaſſion in the Mind, and to be pierced with a ſenſe of anothers Misfortunes. This is to commit a Rape upon all Mankind; to Raviſh them of their Bowels. Nay, it doth not only ſtifle the very Principle of Charity, but it prepares a way too, for the greateſt Injuſtice and Oppreſſion: For how can he ſtick at any thing, though never ſo hard, that hath no ſenſe of it? As long as the Affliction toucheth not himſelf, he feels no more his Neighbour's Smart, though he himſelf gives the blow, than a Flint, or an Adamant; and at ſuch Hands neither is Mercy nor Juſtice to be expected. This was one great Reaſon, why the Son of God was pleaſed to take Humane Nature upon him; that he might
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:56571:57"/>
be ſenſible of thoſe our common Miſeries, whereof a Spirit is not capable of feeling. <hi>In all things it behoved him to be made like unto his Brethren, that he might be a merciful and faithful High-Prieſt,</hi> Heb. 2. 17. <hi>We have not an High-Prieſt which cannot be touched with the feeling of our Infirmities, but was in all Points tempted</hi> (that is, tried by Afflictions, acquainted with Sorrows and Griefs,) <hi>like as we are,</hi> Hebr. 4. 15. His own through-ſenſe of the Hardſhips of the World, made him the more willingly go about doing good during his abode in the Fleſh, and the more merciful to Mankind now, ſince all Power in Earth and Heaven hath been put into his Hands. And this will be in us the Principle of right Chriſtian Charity to one another; to be
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:56571:58"/>
painfully affected with the Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of others: And to this end we ſhould uſe all poſſible means, to mould our Hearts rightly, to ſupple them into a very ſoft, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and compaſſionate Temper; and to let all moving Idea's ſink deep into them, becauſe we are the Body of Chriſt, and all of us Members of it, knit toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the ſame Ligaments of Faith and Hope; we ſhould be all animated with the ſame Spirit of Charity too; we ſhould have, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 25, 26. <hi>The ſame Care one for another; ſo that if one Member ſuffer, all the Members ſhould ſuffer with it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. But, Secondly, This is not enough, if it be all. 'Tis poor kindneſs juſt to be troubled for
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:56571:58"/>
another, and to ſay, <hi>God help him.</hi> Grief, and Sorrow, and Anguiſh, and good Wiſhes, muſt break out into Action; elſe, all the reſt is but good natur'd Compliment. The Laws of Charity bind us, not to be Barren, or Unfruitful, but to be full of Good Works, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as our own Capacities, and according as the Wants and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities of other People are.</p>
               <p>Firſt, To do their Souls all the Good we can. This is the nobleſt Work of Charity, becauſe it is done to the nobleſt Part of Man: And becauſe there is a neceſſity for the Soul, upon its parting from the Body, to paſs into an Everlaſting, Unchangeable State, either of Happineſs, or Miſery: Greater Charity there cannot be, than to miniſter ſuch Helps and
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:56571:59"/>
Means to it now, as ſerve to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare it for a Bleſſed Eternity: As, to inſtruct it in the right ſound Faith; to teach it the true Fear of God; to ſubdue its Sinful and Inordinate Luſts; and to bring it to an habitual Practice of all manner of Piety and Virtue. <hi>He which converteth a Sinner from the Error of his way, ſhall ſave a Soul from Death,</hi> Jam. 5. 20. Such a Man ſaveth ſeveral Souls at once; his Neighbour's, and his own too. A moſt Honourable Office cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly; the moſt Excellent Work, that is Crowned with a Reward ſo Glorious, ſo Infinite.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Charity obligeth us to expreſs a tender Regard to the Worldly Neceſſities of others al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, according to our Abilities. God, who hath ordered all Things
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:56571:59"/>
in Number, Meaſure, and Weight, hath of his great Goodneſs and Wiſdom, made variety of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions among Mankind, and hath ſo ſuited Men's Capacities, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, and Abilities, to their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral States of Life, that every one is to be uſeful in ſome reſpect or other to the reſt. And becauſe no Man can poſſibly live alone, or ſupport himſelf in a State of ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Separation from all others; Common Neceſſity ties us all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, like ſo many Limbs and Members into one Body, that each may miniſter its Aſſiſtance to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Maintenance of the whole. Now ſo far as any one wants, and becomes feeble, ſo far it is diſabled and hindred from lending its own help to its Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows: So that were nothing elſe to be conſider'd but the Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:56571:60"/>
and common Intereſt of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Society, that alone would be enough to ſet all Hands at work, upon extending themſelves in Acts of Charity.</p>
               <p>But our Obligations to it are the greater ſtill, becauſe the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Being, who careth for us all, hath made that which is a Civil Duty, to be a part of our Religion too; that which the Neceſſities of Humane Society call for, he himſelf requires as neceſſary in order to our Eternal Intereſt. Upon both accounts therefore, as we are Men, and Chriſtians alſo, we muſt be very careful to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the Benevolent Diſpoſition of our Hearts, by all outward Acts of Beneficence, according as our Stations and Capacities are, and according as the Needs and Sufferings of other People require
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:56571:60"/>
our helping Hand; as, to ſave Life, when it is in danger; to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver Captives; to relieve the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed; to take care of the Sick; to help the Infirm; to feed the Hungry; to cloath the Naked; to cheriſh the Comfortleſs; to lift up the Head that hangeth down; to viſit the Fatherleſs and Widow in their Affliction; and to ſend up to the God of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, our Charitable Interceſſions for all. It was a Pious and Noble Reflection, which <hi>Job</hi> made upon himſelf, in the midſt of his own Diſtreſs, <hi>Job</hi> 29. from Verſ. 11. to Verſ. 18. <hi>When the Ear heard me, then it bleſſed me; and when the Eye ſaw me, it gave witneſs to me: Becauſe I delivered the Poor when he cried, and the Fatherleſs, and him that had none to help him. The Bleſſing of him that was ready to</hi>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:56571:61"/>
                  <hi>periſh, came upon me, and I cauſed the Widow's Heart to ſing for joy. I put on Righteouſneſs, and it cloathed me; my Judgment was a Robe, and a Diadem. I was Eyes to the Blind; and Feet was I to the Lame. I was a Father to the Poor, and the Cauſe which I knew not, I ſearched out. And I brake the Jaws of the Wicked, and plucked the Spoil out of his Teeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly; Beſides our doing Good to the Souls and Bodies of Men after this manner, we are bound to expreſs our Charity by being kind to their Reputation alſo. Intereſt, Fortune, Comfort, Peace, Life it ſelf, depends upon this; and it is the more neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to be preſerved with Care, becauſe it is eaſie to be loſt, and the hardeſt Thing to be recover'd.
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:56571:61"/>
Nay, in ſome caſes, the common Welfare, and the very Honour of God depends upon it too. For if the Perſons, whoſe Credit is wounded, be placed in any pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Station either in Church, or State, it will be impoſſible for them, as long as the Wound re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, to do the World that Good, or God that Service, which is the end of their Office; and by this means the Blow ſtriketh very deep, and affects in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the whole Community: And therefore for the Love of God and Man, we ſhould always en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour either to prevent, or heal. If the Perſons reproach'd deſerve it not, 'tis but Juſtice to be their Advocates; if they do, 'tis Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity however: But what ever it be to them, to be ſure 'tis Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to the Publick; and perhaps
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:56571:62"/>
an Effectual, as well as Charitable Way, to ſhame and reclaim the falſe Accuſers themſelves, whoſe buſineſs is, not to convince or mend others, but to expoſe them. Beſides, rarely doth any one's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation bleed, but the firſt Drop is drawn by thoſe <hi>Backbitings and Whiſperings,</hi> which St. <hi>Paul</hi> mentions, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 20. by Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices in private, where the greateſt Innocence cannot ſtand upon the Defenſive; and then 'tis like the breaking in upon the Dead, that cannot help themſelves: In which caſe Common Charity ſhould move every Man to be for a Reſcue, Alas! even Crimes ſhould be buried, and lie quiet in the Grave; becauſe they cannot ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear above Ground without Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:56571:62"/>
               <head>V.</head>
               <p>5. Having ſhew'd you that Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of <hi>Charity,</hi> which conſiſteth in Kindneſs, or in doing others Good in every reſpect, I proceed now to the next Character the Apoſtle gives of it; <hi>Charity envy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not:</hi> That is, will not be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed or grieved at another's Happineſs; or at any Thing, wherein another excels. The Scripture calls this Paſſion, <hi>An Evil Eye,</hi> Matth. 20. 15. And <hi>Plutarch</hi> compares it to a Diſeaſe in the Eye, by means whereof it cannot endure to behold any ſplendid or bright Object.</p>
               <p>Of all the Diſtempers of the Mind, there is none that proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from a worſe, nor yet from a weaker Cauſe; for it is not
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:56571:63"/>
grounded upon any Perſonal Crime, but upon a Wicked Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Partiality in Providence, and upon an Abuſive Conceit of ones own Deſerts. Where is any Injuſtice or Blame in the Man, if God pleaſeth to bleſs him with outward or inward Gifts above his Neighbours? Yet this is the Original of Envy, that for Great and Wiſe Reaſons, God doth diſpenſe his Goodneſs to ſome with a more Liberal Hand, than what he extendeth unto others. And can any Thing be more wicked, than to quarrel with the Divine Being for his Bounty? Or can any Thing be more unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, than to find fault with a Man, becauſe he is happily made a Partaker of it? For Anger, and Hatred, and ſome other Vices, there might be ſome Tolerable
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:56571:63"/>
Pretence; did not the Laws of Religion forbid them. This Vice is the moſt unfortunate of all, that it hath no Covering, but an Evil Heart.</p>
               <p>But I am not now to conſider ſo much the Unreaſonable Nature of Envy, as how contrary and oppoſite it is to a Spirit of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; for, whereas a Charitable Perſon wiſheth well to all, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, as far as in him lies, to do Good to all; the Envious Wretch grieves and pines, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murs and complains, frets and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges at his Neighbour's Happineſs. Such a Wretch is not ſo much as Charitable to himſelf; becauſe his great (I had almoſt ſaid, his <hi>only)</hi> kindneſs is to a Vice, that is his crueleſt Enemy; to a Vice, that cuts and pierces him to the quick; to a Vice that eats daily upon his
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:56571:64"/>
Vitals, and into his Heart; and in return for its Entertainment, gives him nothing but Gall and Wormwood. And how can it be expected, that a Man ſo <hi>imbit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd</hi> ſhould be Charitable to any other. <hi>If you have Envying, and bitter Strife in your Hearts, glory not, and lye not againſt the Truth. This Wiſdom deſcendeth not from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, but is Earthly, Senſual, and Deviliſh: For where Envying and Strife is, there is Confuſion, and every Evil Work:</hi> Jam. 3. 14, 15, 16. There is Meaneſs of Spirit, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, Detraction, Hatred, Lying, Malice, Fraud, Oppreſſion, Partiality, Cruelty, and too often Blood-guiltineſs it ſelf. The firſt Blood that ever was ſhed upon the Earth, was ſhed out of meer Envy; becauſe <hi>the Lord had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect unto Abel, and to his Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:56571:64"/>
Gen. 4. 4. Yet how was it a Crime in <hi>Abel,</hi> or why was he to be blamed, that God loved him?</p>
               <p>An Envious Spirit being ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with Charity, ſo repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to it, ſo utterly deſtructive of it, we ſhould uſe all poſſible means to pluck out of our Souls this poiſonous Root of Bitterneſs: Then ſhall we be Charitable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed when we unfeignedly deſire, not only the Eternal, but even the Temporal Proſperity of all Men, and ſtrive according to our Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to Promote it. Then ſhall we expreſs our Charity indeed, when we ſeek not our own only, but conſider the Caſes, and ſuit our ſelves to the Circumſtances of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as if they were our own too; when we bleſs God for them, and are ſatisfied and pleaſed
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:56571:65"/>
to ſee our Neighbours ſit at Peace under their Vines, delighted and chearful with their Milk and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney about them. Then are we Charitable to all Men, when in ſtead of fretting againſt any, we take Compaſſion upon the worſt, lamenting and pitying their Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licities, as well as Sin, when they abuſe and miſapply the Mercies of God to them. Then are we Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable indeed, when we rejoyce for thoſe Gifts which the Divine Bounty beſtows, eſpecially upon Good Men; when we are Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for them, and make this Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Uſe of them, as to become our ſelves the Wiſer and Better for them. Then are we Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table indeed, when we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with our own preſent Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſatisfied with other Men's, entirely ſubmitting to the
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:56571:65"/>
Will of God, with this comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Perſwaſion, That in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Acts of his Providence to them and us, he doth that which is beſt for us all; if not that which we moſt Covet, yet that which we moſt Need. Briefly, to Acquieſce in his Goodneſs and Wiſdom, conſidering how much we Enjoy above what we really deſerve, how many Thouſands that deſerve as well come vaſtly ſhort of us, and how little ſhort we our ſelves comparatively come of thoſe who deſerve better; to put a due value upon every the leaſt Bleſſing of God, and with all modeſt Reſignation to leave our ſelves, our Fortunes, and our Brethren, to his Government and Diſpoſal: This is at once to be Wiſe, Patient, Pious, and Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table alſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:56571:66"/>
               <head>VI.</head>
               <p>6. The next Character which St. <hi>Paul</hi> gives of <hi>Charity,</hi> as a Rule for us to expreſs it by, is not ſo readily underſtood as the former, becauſe it admits of various Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations: The Expreſſions which the Apoſtle uſeth, is no where elſe to be found in the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Very probably it is a <hi>Latin</hi> word made <hi>Greek,</hi> as ſome other words in the New Teſtament are, and therefore it is no wonder, if it bears a very doubtful Senſe; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially conſidering, that it is no very common Word among the Old <hi>Latines</hi> neither: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, is the Expreſſion; which our Tranſlation rendreth, <hi>Doth not vaunt it ſelf:</hi> But this is included in the following Character of
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:56571:66"/>
Charity, that is, it is <hi>not puffed up.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If that Conſtruction be right which Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> mentions (though without any Credit) out of <hi>Phavorinus,</hi> it ſhould be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thus, Charity <hi>flattereth not;</hi> and certainly Flatterers are the moſt Uncharitable People in the World; for they carry a Feather in their Hands with a deſign to do <hi>ſoft</hi> Execution, and therefore are to be avoided as baſe and curſed Fellows, as Deſtroyers and Peſts, ſaith <hi>Plutarch, (De Lib. Educ.)</hi> To which purpoſe, that wiſe Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then hath written a large Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; <hi>(Plut. de Adul. &amp; Amici. Diſcrimine.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some Divines render the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle's Expreſſion thus, Charity is not <hi>Inconſtant;</hi> Others, Charity is not <hi>Pretending, Feigned,</hi> and <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritical;</hi>
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:56571:67"/>
in which ſenſe, <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> and St. <hi>Baſil</hi> ſeem to agree.</p>
               <p>There are no leſs than nine or ten Interpretations of the Phraſe: But the faireſt, and that which is moſt followed by the Learned, is that of St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> and <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian;</hi> Charity is not <hi>Precipitant;</hi> or, a Charitable Perſon doth not run headlong; doth not act raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, boiſterouſly, and without due conſideration.</p>
               <p>That Noble Faculty the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, being planted in the Soul by Almighty God, to direct us in all Caſes, Reaſon ought to be the Principle and Rule of our Moral Actions: We ſhould firſt propoſe to our ſelves a good End in all our Undertakings, and then make choice of ſuch good Means, as right Reaſon tells us are fit and
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:56571:67"/>
proper for the attaining it. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs we do manage our ſelves thus conſiderately, we do not act like Rational Beings, but like Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Fools, and Brutes.</p>
               <p>Therefore when we are about to deal with one another, we ſhould ſtrictly Examine before-hand, Whether the End we drive at be Charitable, or conſiſtent with our Neighbours Good and Welfare; and whether the Means we would uſe be Charitable in like manner. For if either the End, or the Means, be contrary to the Law of Charity, the Action it ſelf muſt needs be very ſinful, and defile the Conſcience; and therefore it ſhould be well weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and conſidered before-hand. Men ſhould not do Things, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially Things of this Nature, in an hurry; nor ſuffer their Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:56571:68"/>
to carry them violently on, before Right Reaſon hath had Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; becauſe when an Action is done hand over head, it is a very great Chance if it be not Evil. The Thing Intended may be Evil, for ought the Man knows; for he conſiders it not; and the courſe he takes to bring it about, may be Evil too, and ſeldom is an Action unadviſedly done, but it is ſo: And then Miſchiefs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidably follow, and ſome too that perhaps were not deſigned at the firſt. 'Tis St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, That Charity makes one Prudent, Cautious, Grave, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcending, and by bringing the Mind to Temper and Thought<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, preventeth Raſh and Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Proceedings. But if Spleen make head againſt Reaſon, and Inconſideration gets the Maſtery,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:56571:68"/>
Power ſtrikes at every Thing that ſtands in the way, which in that caſe is as a Knife in the Hand of a Mad-man.</p>
               <p>Therefore in the whole inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of thoſe Offices, which uſually paſs between Man and Man, we ſhould deliberate about our Actions in good time; and how Alluring ſoever any Thing appears, we ſhould narrowly look into the Nature of it, in ſtead of viewing the Face; and conſider throughly firſt, whether it be Juſt, then whether it be Charitable alſo, conſiſtent with that Goodneſs and Kindneſs of Mind which becomes a Chriſtian. If the Thing be contrary to the Law of Love, and ſuch as we would not have ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to do to our own ſelves, we muſt with a very quick Hand lay the Bridle upon our Paſſions, leſt
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:56571:69"/>
the Beaſt ſhould prove Heady, and by running away with us at all adventures, ruſh us headlong into a great many Sins. We ſhould ſit down a while and conſider, how ſhort our Life is at the beſt, and what little time in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon we have to do Good in the World; and how ſuddenly many drop into the Grave, before they have done any at all. We ſhould conſider, what baſe Vices Hatred and Malice are; what Diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and Wicked Purpoſes they tend to; what Mean and Helliſh Arts Men are driven to, for the putting of them in execution; what Diſorders they make in the World; how Prejudicial they are to the Intereſt of Mankind, to the Peace and Comfort of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Life; and what Irreparable Miſchiefs ariſe from them natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:56571:69"/>
not only to Single Perſons, but to Bodies, to Families, to Publick Societies, nay to the whole Church and State, when once they come to break out, as very often they do, into Epidemical Outrage. We ſhould conſider too, what Rewards they bring to the Actors themſelves, after all theſe Dreadful Conſequences; Vexation and Anguiſh of Spirit, a Polluted Conſcience, a loſt Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, an abbreviated Life, and in ſtead of any ſolid Satisfaction in the Courſe, or at the End of it, Eternal Damnation at laſt, both of Soul and Body. What Fruit will Men have then of thoſe Things, whereof they ought even now to be Aſhamed? I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, if People would but De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberate thus before-hand, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer their Minds kindly to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:56571:70"/>
theſe, or ſome of theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, it would be impoſſible for half ſo much Folly and Storm to be in the World<hi>:</hi> Such an excellent way this is, not only to expreſs, but to encreaſe Men's Charity to one another, and to keep them from tumbling precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſly into a vaſt Complication of Wickedneſſes and Misfortunes, which one day Uncharitable Wretches will repent of; tho' perhaps not till it be too late; till they have Sinned the time of their Peace away.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <head>VII.</head>
               <p>7. The next Character of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is, that it <hi>is not Puffed up;</hi> alloweth not People to be Proud and Arrogant, to be Haughty and Supercilious, to have an immodeſt,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:56571:70"/>
lofty, and over-high Conceit of a Man's own ſelf; or to behave himſelf with Contempt and Scorn towards thoſe, whom he looks down upon at a diſtance as his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriors.</p>
               <p>There is hardly another Vice that is more Fooliſh, more Hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, than Pride is; none that is ſo like to the Devil's Temper; I am ſure, none that ſtands in more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect oppoſition to all the Laws of Charity. An humble Mind ſtoops to all, though the meaneſt and loweſt Offices; nor is there any Act of Love, which it is not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to reach out a kind Hand unto, though it be to the waſhing of Feet: And the Reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a truly humble Man hath ſo modeſt an Opinion of himſelf, and ſo high an Eſteem of others, that he is apt to reckon all good
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:56571:71"/>
Offices to be a kind of Debt to them, and a very neceſſary, though a poor Tribute of Honour to the Meek and Lowly Jeſus. But Pride ſets Men ſo remote from their Neighbours, that to <hi>deſire</hi> their Friendſhip, looks like Incroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and for themſelves to <hi>offer</hi> it, ſeems to them a Tranſgreſſing the Rules of Greatneſs; and ſo in that diſtance and interval between <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Meanneſs,</hi> many Acts of True Charity are wanting, many Bleſſed Opportunities of doing Good drop to the Ground, and are quite loſt, and perhaps too when the Neceſſities of Poor Wretches are moſt preſſing. Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom do Proud Men think of God himſelf, <hi>They care not for God, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is God in all their Thoughts,</hi> ſaith <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 10. 4. They think not of him as their Maker
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:56571:71"/>
and Benefactor, by whom they live; or as their Law-giver and Judge, by whom they muſt be Sentenced to Eternity; at leaſt they think not with that Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, Reverence, and depth of Thought, which ſhould ſwallow up all their vain Imaginations. And if God be not in their Minds, it is no wonder if Men be not there, and if they be full of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Themſelves. But this is not all: The Caſe would be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter though they did no Good, if they did no Hurt neither. But Pride is ſuch an Injurious and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perious Vice, that where it Ruleth, it admits of no Bound but thoſe of its own ſetting, and thoſe are as uncertain, as precarious Priviledges under an Arbitrary Power. Pride commonly hath Covetouſneſs for its Factor, to Toil and Drudge for
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:56571:72"/>
its Maintenance; and when thoſe Vices go hand in hand, nothing is ſafe that is within reach, though it be <hi>Naboth</hi>'s Vineyard. <hi>Ahab</hi> was ſick at Heart for it, and to recover his Content, the Poor Man's Blood was ſought for too, as the ſpeedieſt Remedy. Men of ſuch Tempers are ſo bloated with an Opinion of their own Deſerts, that they fancy themſelves to have a kind of Right to every Thing, eſpecially if it be judged neceſſary and convenient; and how then can we hope for Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, when there is no room for Juſtice? Fraud, Rapine, and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, are the uſual deſigns of an elated Mind, and 'tis the harder to ſtop them, becauſe Proud Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are ever apt to over-look their Actions; think it a Diminution to obey ſuch a Thing as Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience;
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:56571:72"/>
are too Big to be taken to account; too High to ask themſelves; is there not Iniquity in my Right Hand?</p>
               <p>Indeed People who are thus puffed up, have not always power to hurt others much in their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes; but then they ſeldom fail to oppreſs them in their Fame; which is another Thing utterly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with that Candor and Goodneſs, which evermore attends a Charitable Temper. Pride is always very Cenſorious; though many times there is no other Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for the hard Character it gives, but this only, That it may have a Foil, to ſet off it ſelf. The greateſt Innocence is often Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached, becauſe Proud People care not what others deſerve, but would have you know how Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular their own Merits are; by
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:56571:73"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="139" facs="tcp:56571:73"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="140" facs="tcp:56571:74"/>
expoſing a Neighbour, they hope you will think the better and the more highly of them: By throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Dirt upon others Faces, they think their own will appear the more Beautiful; like the haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>Phariſee</hi> in the Goſpel, who thought to Recommend himſelf to God, by making Reflections; <hi>I am not as other Men are, Extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt, Adulterers, nor even as this Publican,</hi> Luke 18. 11.</p>
               <p>By this Injurious and Unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Practice, many Miſchiefs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fal Mankind; as Strife, Railings, Animoſities, Violence, and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Outrage. So that <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Prov.</hi> 13. 10. <hi>Only by Pride cometh Contention.</hi> 'Tis the only Natural Mother of Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: There are Accidental Cauſes of it, as Drunkenneſs, Paſſion, Revenge, and the like, which
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:56571:74"/>
bring forth Strife upon preceding Heats and Provocations; but Pride is the only Vice, that hath a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, natural Inclination that way; a Principle that tends to Strife, whether there be juſt Provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or no; the Vice that loves it, and delights in it; and indeed that Signalizeth it ſelf chiefly by it; for had we not Reaſon to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of Quarrels, and to be afraid of them, for the miſchievous Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Conſequence of them, very little notice would be taken of Proud People; they would be the moſt Slighted and Scorned, as now they are the moſt Hated Creatures in the World.</p>
               <p>Therefore that we may beget in us a right Spirit of Charity, and be able duly to expreſs it, we ſhould Learn of our great Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver and Exemplar, to be very
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:56571:75"/>
                  <hi>lowly in Heart,</hi> Matth. 11. 29. We ſhould firſt lay our ſelves low under an awful Apprehenſion of God's Greatneſs, and under a juſt Senſe of our own Vileneſs and Unworthineſs, to be ſure in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of Him; of whoſe Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and Glory there is no End. Then we ſhould conſider, with what admirable Wiſdom God hath ordered the World; that as all Things depend upon him, ſo under him one Thing dependeth upon another, and miniſtreth Help to another; and in this reſpect or that one Thing <hi>excelleth</hi> another too: That Man himſelf, though he ſtruts upon the Earth with ſuch Pomp and State, is behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the meaneſt Creature for Succour and Aſſiſtance: That the moſt Valuable Things any Man hath are all borrowed, and that
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:56571:75"/>
but for a little time too. That though the Righteous be more Excellent than his Neighbour, yet it is God that makes the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and that we have nothing of our own but our Follies and our Sins. Few think it reaſonable to be proud of theſe; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all the reſt are Debts, there is no reaſon for any to be proud of them neither. Upon theſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts we ſhould prick the Bubble in our Minds, which hath nothing in it but Air, nothing about it but Phantaſtical Gaiety, to pleaſe Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and Fools. The buſineſs of a <hi>Man</hi> is to do Good; and in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thereunto, we ſhould <hi>Prefer one another in Honour,</hi> Rom. 12. 10. <hi>Condeſcend to Men of low Eſtate,</hi> Verſ. 16. <hi>Do nothing through Strife or Vain-glory, but in lowlineſs of Mind each ſhould eſteem other better</hi>
                  <pb n="144" facs="tcp:56571:76"/>
                  <hi>than themſelves,</hi> Philip. 2. 3. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe how great ſoever one Man's Gifts may be, thoſe of the moſt inferior Rank have in ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect or other greater Gifts than he hath. Briefly we ſhould imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the great <hi>Humility</hi> of the Lord Jeſus, as a ſure way of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing his great Charity too; who though He was in Form of God, and thought it no Robbery to be Equal with God, yet made himſelf of no Reputation. As he laid aſide his Glory for the Form of a Servant; ſo he laid aſide his Garments for the loweſt Miniſtration, to waſh the Feet of his Diſciples with thoſe moſt holy Hands, which had wrought ſo many Miracles, nay to waſh the Feet of <hi>Judas</hi> himſelf, that was now going to betray him. But I ſhall ſpeak no more at preſent of
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:56571:76"/>
this Virtue, <hi>Humility,</hi> becauſe it will require a particular Diſcourſe by it ſelf.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="part">
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <p>8. The Eighth Character of <hi>Charity</hi> is, That <hi>it doth not behave it ſelf <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſeemly;</hi> doth nothing to others that is Indecent, Foul, or Unſuitable, to the Excellence and Honour of Chriſt's Religion.</p>
               <p>One great Reaſon is, becauſe diſorderly and diſgraceful Actions are not only Evil in their own Nature, but are Evil in their Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, Scandalous and very Hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in their Conſequences; they carry a ſtrong Infection with them, which is of Evil Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; they ſerve to taint the Minds, and corrupt the good Manners of other People, that behold them;
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:56571:77"/>
and ſo are apt to draw a great many more to the Practice of them. This is that which the Scripture meaneth, when it ſpeaks of <hi>making Men to Sin;</hi> of <hi>laying a Stumbling-Block</hi> in their way; of <hi>wounding their Conſciences;</hi> of <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending,</hi> and <hi>giving Offences;</hi> as thoſe two wicked Sons of <hi>Eli</hi> did, <hi>Hophni</hi> and <hi>Phineas,</hi> when they abuſed Women in that ſhameful manner, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. And ſo it is always, when People are allured into the Communion of any Guilt; when they are encouraged and tempted to do an Evil Thing by ſeeing others do it. Nothing is more Natural than Imitation, eſpecially in bad Things. Such is the Corruption of our Nature, that every one is of a ſoft, waxy Diſpoſition on that ſide, apt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive deeper Impreſſions from one
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:56571:77"/>
ill Example, than from many good ones. There is a Conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in Vice, which inſenſibly goes from one to another, till the Diſeaſe becomes General. A Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly Maſter teacheth his whole Family Licentiouſneſs and Irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. An Unjuſt, Malicious, and Diſſolute Neighbour, is a Plague to a whole Society, and ſhews others the way how to be ſo too. A Seditious Subject em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldens many more to diſturb the Publick Peace; and one Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Preacher is enough to raiſe Animoſities, Quarrels, and Schiſms in a whole Church; when once the Infection ſpreads, God knows where it will end; the Sin and Miſchief runs on, and is ſtill pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagated with the Example.</p>
               <p>Upon this account every Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous and Shameful Action is
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:56571:78"/>
utterly Repugnant to the Rule of Charity, becauſe it is Injurious, and Injurious in the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree; Injurious to the Souls of Men, to thoſe Precious and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Spirits of Men, for which the Lord Jeſus was pleaſed of his own meer Goodneſs and Charity to die. This is a Sin of a very high Nature, a <hi>Sin againſt Chriſt,</hi> faith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 12. that doth after a more peculiar man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and with a particular ſort of Spear, wound that infinite Lover of Souls.</p>
               <p>For the opening this Matter a little further, it will be very uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for us to conſider two famous Caſes, that were in the beginning of Chriſtianity, even in the Days of the Apoſtles. Then there were two hot Controverſies in the Church; and it is obſervable, that
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:56571:78"/>
in each Caſe the Controverſie was about a Thing that was pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly indifferent; no particular Law, whether from the Nature of the Thing, or from God, or from the Church, binding People to act the one way or the other: And yet in both Caſes, Charity was the great General Rule, which the Apoſtles ordered Men to go by, for fear of tempting others into Sin; which plainly ſhews, that to give a Scandalous Example, by any ſhameful or foul Action, is a moſt abominable Practice.</p>
               <p>The firſt Caſe related to thoſe <hi>Jews,</hi> who were newly brought over to Chriſtianity. Many of them were ſo weak in their Faith, ſo uninſtructed as yet in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſtian Liberty, that they thought it ſtill neceſſary for
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:56571:79"/>
them to obſerve the old <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Sabbath, and other Solemn Days, which <hi>Moſes</hi> had appointed, and to abſtain totally from ſome ſorts of Meats, which had been forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by <hi>Moſes:</hi> Others again made no ſcruple about theſe Things, but look'd upon thoſe Days and Meats as Indifferent now under the Goſpel; and accordingly they uſed their Chriſtian Liberty as to both. Now though St. <hi>Paul</hi> gave this Rule to each Party, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 3. <hi>Let not him that eateth, deſpiſe him that eateth not; and let not him that eateth not, judge him that eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</hi> Yet the Apoſtle ſeems moſt inclined (as Charitable Men are apt to be) to the weaker ſide; and that Charity might have the caſting Hand in the whole Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie. He directed thoſe who were throughly Inſtructed, not to
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:56571:79"/>
uſe their full lawful Liberty in the preſence of a weak Brother, leſt he ſhould be tempted, either to do as others did, though againſt his Conſcience, or elſe to forſake the Chriſtian Communion; either of which would have been a deadly Sin. <hi>Judge this,</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>that no Man put a ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling Block, or an occaſion to fall, in his Brother's way,</hi> Rom. 14. 13. And again, <hi>If thy Brother be grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi> (or ſcandalized) <hi>by thy Meat, now walkeſt thou not Charitably; deſtroy not him with thy Meat, for whom Chriſt died,</hi> V. 15. And again, <hi>For Meat deſtroy not the Work of Gods; all Things indeed are pure, but it is evil for that Man who eateth with Offence. It is good neither to eat Fleſh, nor to drink Wine, nor any thing whereby thy Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtumbleth, or is offended, or made weak;</hi> V. 20, 21.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="152" facs="tcp:56571:80"/>
The other Caſe related to thoſe Proſelites, who had been brought over to Chriſtianity from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſm. Whereas there was an old General Cuſtom among the Heathens, to eat part of thoſe Sacrifices, which had been offered to their ſuppoſed Deities, many of them, though they had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Chriſtian Faith, continued this Cuſtom nevertheleſs; belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſtill, that the Things they Worſhipped were Real Beings, and that they themſelves were better by much for partaking of thoſe their Sacrifices. Others knew, that theſe were groſly miſtaken; and were convinced, that thoſe Idols were nothing but Fictitious and Imaginary Deities: However theſe too reſorted to the Idol-Feaſts for Compliance-ſake,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:56571:80"/>
yet believing them not to be Religious, but ordinary Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Meals. Now this was a very Shameful and Evil Practice: For though the eating of thoſe Meats, abſtractedly and ſimply conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, was a Thing indifferent, yet the Scandal it gave, made it ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly unlawful, becauſe it was a Violation of Charity; it confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med others in their old Heathen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Opinion, and encouraged them to go on ſtill in their old Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh ſinful Courſe. To rectifie this Matter therefore, St. <hi>Paul</hi> diſcourſeth in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. ſhewing, that though he and others had a very vile Opinion of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then-Idols, yet it was a moſt ſhameful and wicked thing to lay a ſtumbling Block in their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren's way, (that is the Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion again;) that is, to Miniſter
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:56571:81"/>
unto them any occaſion of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into, or of continuing in a ſinful Practice. <hi>Meat commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us not unto God; for neither if we eat are we the better, neither if we eat not are we the worſe. But take heed, leſt by any means this Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of yours become a ſtumbling Block to them that are weak. For if a Man ſee thee, who haſt know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, ſit at Meat in the Idols Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſhall not the Conſcience of him that is weak, be embolden'd to eat thoſe Things which are offered to Idols? And through thy knowledge ſhall the weak Brother periſh, for whom Chriſt died?</hi> Verſ. 8, 9, 10, 11. And at the cloſe of that Chapter he declared his own Peremptory Reſolution; <hi>That if Meat made his Brother to offend, he would eat no Fleſh while the World ſtood, leſt he ſhould make his Brother to offend.</hi>
                  <pb n="155" facs="tcp:56571:81"/>
Here then is a noble Rule of Charity for us all to go by, <hi>viz.</hi> To be very careful that we do not at any time encourage others to do Evil, by our Indecent and Scandalous Examples in any caſe: Not ſo much as in the uſe of Things purely Indifferent, much leſs by doing Things that have a Moral and Natural Turpitude in them: Such Things are of a moſt ſhameful Nature, and of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dangerous Conſequence; and therefore we ſhould always be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of them, leſt we be anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able for other Men's Blood and Ruine, as well as our own.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> underſtands the Apoſtle thus, Charity is <hi>not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed,</hi> and he inſtanceth in our Bleſſed Saviour, who was not at all aſhamed, when the Harlot waſhed his Feet with Tears, and
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:56571:82"/>
wiped them with the Hairs of her Head, kiſs'd his Feet, and anointed them; nor when he was ſpit up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and abuſed by baſe Fellows, nor when he carried a Thief and Murderer with him into <hi>Paradiſe.</hi> The meaning of that great Man is, That true Charity doth not permit one to do a foul Thing, a Thing which he hath juſt Reaſon to be aſhamed of. The Lord Jeſus did all Things with a Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Purpoſe, and to Charitable Ends: And we that are his Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, ſhould follow him in this, To win as many Souls to him as we can, in ſtead of Diſcouraging or Offending any; to gain all that are about us, at leaſt to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour it. This is Chriſtian Charity indeed, to become ones Brother's Keeper; to lift him him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf out of the Pit, whatever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:56571:82"/>
of his Ox or Aſs; to ſave his Soul from Death; to be ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly concerned for that Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Part; to Convert him from the Error of his Way; to take him up like a wandring Loſt Sheep upon the Shoulders; and by a Good Example and Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Directions, to ſhew him the Way to Everlaſting Life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="part">
               <head>IX.</head>
               <p>9. The Reaſon why Charity requires theſe and the like Offices at our hands is, becauſe it is a publick-ſpirited Grace. And that is another noble Character the Apoſtle gives of a Charitable Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that he <hi>ſeeketh not his own;</hi> not his own Private Advantage only, but the Profit of others too; and eſpecially the good of
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:56571:83"/>
the whole Community, to which he ſtands related. This is inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the very Notion of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; for it is a kind, benevolent Diſpoſition, that makes us lend an helping hand, wherever it is want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. The truth is, this is Charity to ones ſelf too, as well as to others, if you conſider the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter rightly. That we may be tied, and linked, and bound cloſe together by mutual Love and Kindneſs, God hath ſo ordered the State of this World, that all Men have a neceſſary Dependance one upon another; nor would there be ſuch a ſhiftleſs, pitiful, miſerable Creature in the World as a Man, were he to live alone, and by himſelf. Every one of us ſtands in need of the Society and Help of others, as much as we need Food or Air. He needs
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:56571:83"/>
the Magiſtrate, to Protect him under God; the Stateſman, to Conſult and Adviſe for him; the Divine, to Inſtruct him; the Tradeſman, to Supply him with a World of Neceſſities; the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, to Fight for him; the pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Husbandman, to find him Bread; the poor Servant, to Work and Sweat for him; nay, the Greateſt and Richeſt Man on Earth needs the very Beggar to do him good too: He needs even the Blind, and the Lame; the Hungry, and Naked; the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſs Mother, and her ſucking Child: For what? Why to lay up his Treaſure in Heaven for him; for theſe are God's Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers; by their Hands it is that Men lend unto the Lord, that they may receive themſelves Ten thouſand fold at the hands of
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:56571:84"/>
Chriſt. Every one's Good is lodged more or leſs every where, juſt as his Neceſſities are; ſome part in one hand, ſome in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and the greateſt part in the Common Good, in the joint Stock of the Community, in the Proſperity and Good of the whole Kingdom. 'Tis a great miſtake for a Man to think, that all his Intereſt lieth at Home, in his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, and in Himſelf, and within the compaſs of his own Propriety. There indeed lieth his particular and private Intereſt: But what is that worth, if his publick Intereſt be deſtroyed? If the Welfare of the whole Nation be deſtroyed, and gone? Every Man's particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Happineſs is bound and wrapt up in that, and depends on that; nor is it poſſible for the Body to ſuffer, but each Member muſt
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:56571:84"/>
ſuffer in proportion. And hence it follows, that he is a Fool, as well as an ill Neighbour, that ſeeks his own private Welfare only, neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting and overlooking the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Good, which is the main, and which Supports and Preſerves all the reſt. It is ſinful Self-Love that looks at Home only, and is buſie altogether within its own Walls. The Office of Charity is to look abroad; to ſee how the Publick fares; to conſult and mind the publick Good; to lend a helping Hand in all publick Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities; and with all poſſible care to avoid every Thing that is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly Injurious to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Happineſs, and deſtructive of it.</p>
               <p>To expreſs our Charity there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this reſpect alſo, as <hi>every one ſhould ſeek not his own, but ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi>
                  <pb n="162" facs="tcp:56571:85"/>
                  <hi>Wealth,</hi> 1 Cor. 10. 24. So all of us are obliged after an eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial manner, to ſtudy and provide for the <hi>Peace</hi> of the Society, whereunto we all belong. <hi>Peace</hi> is the greateſt Happineſs upon Earth; as it is the State of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; the Bleſſing that gives a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh to all the reſt; that makes all other Enjoyments ſweet and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful; and for that Reaſon the Holy Scripture is wont to expreſs all manner of Happineſs by the General Name of <hi>Peace.</hi> To de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy or diſturb this, is to be a publick Enemy; and where a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Contention reigneth and ſtriveth, the War muſt be very dangerous to the whole Body, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is in the Bowels. 'Twere better living in a Deſert, and to wait for ones Food, as <hi>Elijah</hi> did, by the miniſtry of Ravens,
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:56571:85"/>
than with a Generation of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that are Enemies to Peace; Reſtleſs, Froward, Troubleſom, Malicious, ready for any oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to Vex and Scourge one another. In ſuch a caſe, Society, which ſhould be ones great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, is his greateſt Plague, for Men are thereby the ſtronger to hurt him; Spleen works till it raiſeth a Confederacy, and then Miſchiefs run with an Inundation; like Calamities in a Civil War, where Force carries it, and Armed Enemies conſider not what they <hi>ſhould,</hi> but what they <hi>can</hi> do.</p>
               <p>To prevent the Plagues of this Life, as well as the Torments of another; the Laws of the moſt Holy and Charitable Jeſus require us to be <hi>Peacemakers,</hi> Matth. 5. 9. To <hi>live in Peace,</hi> 2 Cor. 13. 11.
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:56571:86"/>
                  <hi>To follow Peace with all Men,</hi> Hebr. 12. 14. <hi>To ſeek Peace, and enſue it,</hi> 1 Pet. 3. 11. <hi>To keep the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Spirit, in the bond of Peace,</hi> Eph. 4. 3. <hi>If it be poſſible, as much as lieth in us, to live peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably with all Men,</hi> Rom. 12. 18. And, <hi>To follow after the Things that belong to our Peace,</hi> Rom. 14. 19. And certainly, if it be Charity to wiſh others, and to do others all the Good we can, it muſt be the greateſt Charity to ſeek that which is the beſt Thing in the World for them, in what Capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſoever we conſider them, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as Inhabitants of the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood, or as Members of a Church, or as conſtituent Parts of a whole Kingdom; and when our Charity is thus Large and Exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, it will in ſome meaſure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble the Goodneſs of God,
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:56571:86"/>
whoſe Mercy is over all his Works.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, We are to expreſs our Charity, by ſeeking and enſuring Peace in the Neighbourhoods we belong to. How great a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort is it when Neighbours ſit quietly and contentedly under their Vines and Fig-trees, Loving and Kind to one another, each reaching out his Cluſters to the reſt, all rejoycing together in the Innocent and Friendly Participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God's Mercies; and all Bleſſing God for them? What a Good, what a Beautiful, what a Delightful Thing it is, when Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple thus dwell together in Love, Unity, and Peace? What an Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly State is this, in compariſon of their wretched Condition, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whom Envy and Strife
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:56571:87"/>
rageth; where Hatred ſeeketh continually, how it may Grieve and Oppreſs, where <hi>Iſhmael</hi>'s Hand is againſt every Man, and every Man's Hand againſt him? Where one Tormenteth another, as if there were not Croſſes enough in the World, but they muſt make new ones to Crucifie one another? Is this conſiſtent with the Nature and Laws of Charity? Is this to be Long-ſuffering, to be Kind? To behave our ſelves ſeemly, and as it becometh Brethren? Is this to love our Neighbours as our ſelves? And to love one another, as our Bleſſed Saviour hath loved us? No, no; there is no more Charity in this, than there is in Hell. If we bite and devour one another, whom do we reſemble but that wicked One, who was a Murderer from the beginning?
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:56571:87"/>
                  <hi>If ye have bitter Envying and Strife in your Hearts, glory not, and lye not againſt the Truth. This Wiſdom deſcendeth not from above, but is Earthly, Senſual, and Deviliſh. For where Envying and Strife is, there is Confuſion, and every Evil Work. But the Wiſdom that is from above is, firſt Pure, then Peaceable, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, eaſie to be Intreated, full of Mercy, and good Fruits, without Partiality, and without Hypocriſie:</hi> Jam. 3. 14, 15, 16, 17.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We muſt expreſs our Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity alſo, by an orderly and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Temper, as to Church-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion; not ſeeking our own Satisfaction, our own Ends, our own Ways, but the General Good of that Myſtical Body, whereof Chriſt is the Head.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="168" facs="tcp:56571:88"/>
Seeing it is impoſſible to order all Church Matters ſo, as to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the Opinion, and to gratifie the Deſires of every individual Member, Charity ſhould teach us all to conſider, whether the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances which vary from our own private Fancies, be not really for the Publick Good, for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Profit, and in ſome meaſure and reſpect for the Common Peace and Edification of the whole Body. This is eaſie to be ſeen, if Men would attentively behold the whole Stru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, and examine the Uſefulneſs of the ſeveral Parts; eſpecially if they would conſider Things with Hearts prepared to make Candid and Charitable Conſtructions. Charity alone would ſtifle many Hot Controverſies, without the uſe of ſome other Arguments, which for the moſt part help to
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:56571:88"/>
Fan the Fire, in ſtead of Quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it. In leſſer Matters, where my own Judgment chanceth to differ from the Publick Judgment of my Superiors, Charity ſhould teach me to ſubmit my Private Sentiments, and ſet them aſide from being an hindrance to Unity and Peace.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Give none Offence, neither to the Jews, nor to the Gentiles, nor to the Church of God,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul; Even as I pleaſe all Men in all Things, not ſeeking my own Profit, but the Profit of many, that they may be ſaved;</hi> 1 Cor. 10. 32, 33. He had a moſt difficult Task (though he was an Apoſtle) to pleaſe all Men in all Things: But his meaning is, that he took a ready way to pleaſe them if it were poſſible; by ſuiting himſelf to them in every thing he could do
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:56571:89"/>
for them without Sin. And thus are we bound in Charity to our Fellow-Chriſtians, and in Duty to the Church of God, as far as it lieth in our power to Comply in all Things, eſpecially in Things Eſtabliſhed by Publick Authority: Becauſe differences in Religion are highly Scandalous, hurtful greatly to the very Souls of Men; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with a world of Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour and Uncharitableneſs, and always tending to Confuſion, and to all Evil Works, which naturally go along with Schiſm from the Church. Therefore for meer Charity and Peace-ſake (were there nothing elſe) we ſhould be all of the ſame mind; and if un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily there be ſome difference in our Conceits, we ſhould never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, whereunto we have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy attained, all walk by the ſame
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:56571:89"/>
Rule, all mind the ſame Thing, in hopes that in time, by ſome means or other, God will Reveal to us the Truth and Reaſonableneſs of thoſe Matters, about which we are as yet differently perſwaded, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. This is a ſure Rule in ſuch caſes; <hi>Haſt thou Faith? have it to thy ſelf before God,</hi> Rom. 14. 22. That is, rather than occaſion the leaſt Sin, or Scandal, or Miſchief in the Church, keep thy Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion private if it be ſingular.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A Thing which we ſhould be the more careful of, becauſe Differences which begin in the Church, are commonly carried off into Corners; there to be fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented and ripened, till at laſt they break out into the State, and ſometimes into the open Field, to the great Diſturbance of the
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:56571:90"/>
Peace and Government of a whole Kingdom. It is the Will of God, that <hi>under Kings, and all that are in Authority, we ſhould lead quiet and peaceable Lives in all Godlineſs and Honeſty,</hi> 1 Tim. 2. 2. And to this end we are commanded, to <hi>ſtudy to be quiet, and to do our own buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 4. 11. Here then we muſt expreſs our Charity in the third place; by ſeeking, not our own, but the General Good of the Civil, as well as Sacred Community, we belong to. Great are the Obligations which Nature it ſelf hath laid upon Men to their Country; inſomuch, that St. <hi>Paul wiſh'd himſelf accurſed from Chriſt for his Brethren, his Kinſmen accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Fleſh,</hi> Rom. 9. 3. Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, not that he might be Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally Damned, (that Charity, if yet it be true Charity, is unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:56571:90"/>
and too much even for a Chriſtian,) but that he might be cut off from the Body of Chriſt here, and from all the preſent Priviledges of Chriſtians; and if this were not enough, that he might be delivered up to Satan, in this World to inflict upon him all the Temporal Calamities he was capable of Suffering, Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Miſeries of all ſorts, Death it ſelf, and whatſoever is moſt Grievous on this ſide Hell; if thereby he might become an Expiation for his Country-men. Like Zeal of Charity to that of <hi>Moſes, Exod.</hi> 32. 32. where he prayed to God to <hi>forgive the Sin of his People; or,</hi> if not, <hi>to blot him out of his Book;</hi> That is, not out of the Book of Eternal Life, but out of the Book of this Life; that he might not behold the
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:56571:91"/>
great Puniſhments which ſhould come upon them. Theſe two noble Inſtances of Charity ſhew, what Fervent Affections we ought to have for a whole Nation, that is, after a more peculiar man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, Bone of our Bone, and Fleſh of our Fleſh; and how Paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately we ſhould wiſh for, as well their Temporal, as Eternal Good; and conſequently ſeek it, much rather than our own. A very Learned Caſuiſt and Prelate of our own calls this, <hi>Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance to our Country;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Biſhop</hi> Sander. <hi>Caſe of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagem.</hi>
                  </note> whence the Allegiance we owe the Sovereign Prince ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth Originally, becauſe he is the Head of the whole Community: So that it is with reſpect to the whole, and in relation to the whole, that the Duty to him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes neceſſary by the Laws of
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:56571:91"/>
Nature. And hence it follows, that Men's firſt Care ſhould be, for the Peace and Proſperity of the Community, where the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Reaſon of it lies. The Truth is, a Chriſtian's Charity can hardly be extenſive enough; Prince and People, and the whole World, ought to have a Share of it: Nor is any Thing more mean and unbecoming, (not to ſay Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religious) than a Narrow, Sordid, Hateful Spirit, which ſeeketh its own Private Good only.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="part">
               <head>X.</head>
               <p>10. Another Character of <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> that followeth now is, that it is <hi>not eaſily Provoked,</hi> or <hi>highly Exaſperated.</hi> But having already ſpoken of it, I ſhall proceed to that which is next at hand; <hi>it</hi>
                  <pb n="176" facs="tcp:56571:92"/>
                  <hi>thinketh no Evil.</hi> Some Learned Divines think the Apoſtle's mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be, That Charity doth not permit a Man to <hi>impute</hi> another's Faults and Miſcarriages to him, ſo as to <hi>upbraid</hi> him with them, and to <hi>deſign</hi> him <hi>Evil,</hi> or Hurt for them. And indeed this is a Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue very becoming and ſuitable, to the Generoſity of a Mind, that is truly Charitable and Great; and it is the more Laudable, becauſe it is not very common. For ſuch is the Temper of moſt People, that they Treaſure up Provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt a Time of Wrath, ſo that the Offender ſhall be ſure to hear of them, and to ſmart for them another day. Nay, it often happens, that let a Man's Merits be never ſo conſiderable in other Reſpects, they are forgotten or diſregarded for one diſtaſtful
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:56571:92"/>
Action: No Allowance is made for Humane Infirmities, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Circumſtances, which might well be pleaded in Abatement and Excuſe of the Fault; but the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of it continues, and return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſtill, like the Pains of an old Sore againſt foul Weather. All his Righteouſneſs that he hath done, ſhall not be mentioned ſo as to come into Account; but for that <hi>one</hi> thing wherein he hath ſinned, he ſhall feel the weight of an Avenging Hand, whether he Repenteth and Retracteth or no; that is all one to the Uncharitable Perſon that meditateth Evil.</p>
               <p>But with Submiſſion to better Judgments, I conceive, this cannot be the Genuine Senſe of St. <hi>Paul</hi> here; becauſe it doth not come up to the Spirit and Height of this Chriſtian Grace. Not to deſign
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:56571:93"/>
Miſchief, though it be an Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Part, yet it is no ſuch great Commendation of that Charity which is properly <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> for Heathens themſelves, upon a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of common Virtue, and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, have condemned all Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous and Revengeful Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. And beſides, this is a Thing, which hath already fallen under another Head, that relateth to the moderating of Anger: And to bring it in here again, would be Tautology; which we may be ſure the Apoſtle did induſtriouſly avoid, eſpecially where he Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth after ſuch a conciſe and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct manner of the ſeveral Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of Charity.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s Interpretation ſeems the moſt Appoſite and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural; that Charitable Men are not <hi>Suſpicious</hi> of Evil Deſigns at
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:56571:93"/>
every turn; are not <hi>Jealous-headed;</hi> are ſo far from working Evil themſelves, that they are not apt to entertain a wicked <hi>Miſtraſt</hi> of others working Evil againſt them. A ſuſpicious Temper muſt needs be contrary to true <hi>Chriſtian Charity,</hi> becauſe (as St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> rightly obſerves) it is the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of Anger; and conſequently, the Original Cauſe of thoſe mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Miſchiefs which follow that wild and outragious Paſſion. Not only Families and Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods, but whole Churches and Kingdoms alſo have ſuffered in an high degree, by reaſon of Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies; and thoſe too ſometimes very Unreaſonable and Ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs.</p>
               <p>Therefore to expreſs our Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in this reſpect too, we ſhould always judge of Men with all
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:56571:94"/>
poſſible <hi>Candour;</hi> put as favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Conſtructions as we can up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Actions, and conceive ſuch a kind Opinion of them, though the Action be ſomewhat hard, as we are wont to have of the Miſcarriages of a Friend, which we are willing to call ſo many Slips, Errors, and Indiſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions only. <q>Every Thing (ſaith <hi>Epictetus)</hi> hath two Handles; and ill-natur'd People are ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more apt to lay hold of the wrong one.</q> When a Fault is done, they are ready ſtrait to think, the Injury or Affront was intended, and that maliciouſly; whereas a Man of Thought, and Temper, and of a Chriſtian Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, would take the Thing by the other Handle; and call it Human Weakneſs, or Inadvertency, or by ſome other ſuch ſoft Name,
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:56571:94"/>
which Charity might eaſily find out, to cover the Nakedneſs of a poor Man, like unto ones ſelf. Sometimes indeed Malice cannot be hid under all its Pretences and Diſguiſes. When a Man comes into <hi>David</hi>'s condition, who ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Enemies, ſaith, <hi>They have privily laid a Net, to deſtroy me without a cauſe. Falſe Witneſſes roſe up, and laid to my Charge Things that I knew not. They whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per together againſt me. Their Words were ſmoother than Oyl, and yet they be very Swords. They daily miſtake my Words; all that they imagine is to do me Evil: They hold all together, and keep themſelves cloſe; and mark my Steps. They encourage themſelves in Miſchief, and commune among themſelves, how they may lay Snares. They have Rewarded me Evil for Good, and</hi>
                  <pb n="182" facs="tcp:56571:95"/>
                  <hi>Harted for my Good Will;</hi> and the like. I ſay, when there is ſuch Overt Acts, the inward Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is plain and palpable; and yet even in ſuch a caſe there muſt be Charity, though mix'd with Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; The Wiſdom of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, with the Innocence of the Dove. But till the blackneſs of the Heart appears clearly, we muſt not judge of Men with ſuch Severity, as if we had God's Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſcience, and were able to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Malignity of the very In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention. Favourable and candid Interpretations from Unſuſpicious Hearts, are always the ſafeſt and beſt; and the true way to bring us all to that Temper is, to be ſincere and ſimple-minded our own ſelves, as we would have all others be; free from Arts, Guile, or Siniſter Purpoſes. For cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly,
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:56571:95"/>
none are ſo Jealous of other Men, as they who are Conſcious to themſelves of their own Guilt; they that Practice the Arts of Diſſimulation, and Diſhoneſty; they that leave the plain and eaſie Methods of Sincerity, to deal in the Intricate Myſteries of Subtilty and Craft, without regard to a Good Conſcience. In the moſt ancient Times, People for the moſt part deſerved <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Character; Plain Men; Honeſt and Good; Free and Innocent in their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation; Ingenuous in their Friendſhip; Open-breaſted in their Promiſes; Faithful in their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts; without Evil Deſigns; without Hypocriſie. Fraud and Treachery, Lying and Tricking, increaſed in the World as the World degenerated, and as the Manners of Men became more
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:56571:96"/>
and more corrupt, and theſe brought on Evil Jealouſies; and it was a ſad Age when the Inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and Falſe Diſpoſition of the <hi>Jews</hi> made our Saviour give his Diſciples that Rule of Common Prudence, to <hi>beware of Men,</hi> Mat. 10. 17. In the firſt Ages of our Religion, it was the Noble Character of Chriſtians, that they did Things in <hi>Singleneſs of Heart,</hi> in Sincerity, and Godly Simplicity; keeping the Mean between two Extreams, neither turning Simpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city into Folly, nor Prudence into Craft. And in thoſe Times, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience was Law enough to them; they were not afraid, nor ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious of one another, no more than ſome <hi>Indians</hi> are now, who uſe neither Sealing nor Signing in their Dealings with one another, unleſs the Diſhoneſty of ſome
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:56571:96"/>
Chriſtians hath taught them of late the Neceſſity of taking ſuch Securities. Where Men live in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocently together, there cannot be ſuſpicious of Evil, becauſe there is no occaſion for them; they have as little reaſon to be afraid of one another, as Parents for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly had to be afraid of their Children, when the Sin of Parri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide was not ſo much as heard of in the World. The Laws which were made againſt it after a long Tract of Time, were ſhameful Monuments of ſome Children's Impiety: And ſo are Laws againſt Diſhoneſty now; Upbraidings of Corrupt Manners; Publick Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the World's Degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy; and of the Miſeries of Mankind. For the Ends of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Society are loſt, where Truth and Simpleneſs of Mind fail; and
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:56571:97"/>
that Confidence which ſupports Converſation and Commerce is gone, where Hearts and Tongues are of different Pieces; where Civilities are Traps; where Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes are only to draw Men in; where a Smile is an Artificial Gloſs upon a Treacherous Mind; where Contracts are Methods of Oppreſſion; where fair Pretences are Flattering Ways of Robbing in the Dark; and where ſhews of Friendſhip are to do the Work of an Enemy, but with greater Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and with more certain Succeſs. Where there is ſuch Falſeneſs, ſuch Hypocriſie, and Deceit, People muſt needs be as ſhy and fearful of each other, as if they were in danger of Wolves and Bears. And for the curing of all Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, nothing is ſo neceſſary, as that Simplicity of Heart I am now
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:56571:97"/>
ſpeaking of; Sincere Meanings, Openneſs in Traffick, Plainneſs in Speech, Innocence in Society, Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racity in Expreſſions, Ingenuity in Promiſes, Fidelity in Covenants, Truth in Friendſhip, Honeſty and Peaceableneſs in Deſigns, Sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in Behaviour, Good Nature in our Mutual Offices, and all other poſſible Expreſſions of a pure, harmleſs, and undiſguiſed Religion: And this is the Great Work of Chriſtian Charity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="part">
               <head>XI.</head>
               <p>11. The Eleventh Character of <hi>Charity</hi> is, that <hi>it Rejoyceth not in Iniquity:</hi> Which may admit of a Twofold Interpretation, and each very conſiſtent with the other. The one is, That Charitable Men are far from taking Pleaſure in the
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:56571:98"/>
                  <hi>Sins</hi> and <hi>Impieties</hi> which a Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour committeth. The next is, That they are far too from being delighted in the <hi>Calamities</hi> which a Neighbour ſuffers by <hi>another</hi>'s Iniquity. Whether St. <hi>Paul</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended both theſe Things here, I cannot tell; perhaps he might mean both in a few Words: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, becauſe both are great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of Charity, and the latter is not diſtinctly mentioned elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where in this Chapter, I ſhall here take occaſion to ſpeak ſomething of both in their Order.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt and moſt received Interpretation is, That <hi>Charity</hi> teacheth us, to be far from being Pleaſed and Delighted with the <hi>Sins</hi> and <hi>Iniquities</hi> we ſee other Men commit. There are ſome of that Baſe and Inhumane Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition,
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:56571:98"/>
that what to all Pious Souls is a Torment, and a kind of Hell, is to them a Paradiſe; to hear <hi>ill</hi> Things of other Men, eſpecially of thoſe they have no Kindneſs for; that they may have a colourable Pretence to Defame and Depreſs them, to bring them into Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and to uſe them Contume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liouſly; and that they may ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der themſelves the better Men (as they think) in the Eſteem of the World. Such were thoſe <hi>Jews,</hi> Jer. 20. 10, <hi>I heard,</hi> ſaith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>the Defaming of many; fear on every ſide: Report, ſay they, and we will report it: All my fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liars watched for my halting, ſaying, Peradventure he will be enticed, and we ſhall prevail againſt him; and we ſhall take our Revenge on him.</hi> Meaning, that they wiſh'd and ſought for ways how to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:56571:99"/>
ſome Miſcarriages or other in him, that they might proceed againſt him, and puniſh him in the <hi>Sanhedrim.</hi> People of ſuch a Temper are moſt highly Unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and reſemble the very De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, who makes it his buſineſs to tempt Men to Sin, and delights to bring the greateſt Evil upon us, the Hurt and Ruine of our Souls; nay, to have God himſelf Diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured by us.</p>
               <p>A Spirit of Charity teacheth us to Grieve and Mourn at anothers Sins, though he be an Enemy; becauſe every Soul God hath made, is Precious; and the more Precious, becauſe it is Immortal; and its Caſe is thereby the ſadder when it drops into the Pit, where the Worm dieth not, nor is the Fire to be quenched. This we ſhould conſider, and lay ſeriouſly
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:56571:99"/>
to Heart, when we ſee or hear of any of thoſe Iniquities; Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Adultery, Theft, Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Drunkenneſs, Revellings, Strife, Sedition, Hereſies, Envyings, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and the like; of which St. <hi>Paul</hi> expreſly tells us, <hi>That they who do ſuch Things, ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God,</hi> Gal. 5. 21. None are ſo to be pitied as ſuch Workers of Iniquity, how pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous and flouriſhing ſoever their Condition may ſeem to be here; even for that too they are to be pitied, becauſe God ſetteth them in flippery Places; and when they fall, they fall into Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, without God's immediate Help; which yet he hath no where promiſed without their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. And when Men are juſt going, Repentance is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly too late, becauſe it hath
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:56571:100"/>
no time to be fruitful, and is ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom true. Conſidering therefore that our own Charity to ſuch will then be too late alſo, we ſhould ſhew it them in time; do them Good while we have an Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity; while it is called to Day; while it is yet our Hour, and the Day of Salvation. Our Bowels ſhould yern upon a Brother, as <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s did upon his Brother <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jamin, Gen.</hi> 43. and we ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, as he did, into our Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and weep there: Weep and Mourn for the Sin now acted, and earneſtly Pray for the Pardon of it; and with the United Aſſiſtance of an Holy Example, Kind Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs, and Charitable Counſels, we ſhould endeavour to recover the Miſerable Wretch out of the Snares of the Devil; if peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture God will be pleaſed to give
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:56571:100"/>
him Repentance in time. <hi>Who is weak, and I am not weak? Who is offended, and I burn not?</hi> Said that great Lover of Souls, St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 29. This is fervent Charity indeed, to be Paſſionately Afflicted, to be on a Fire, for the Crimes and Offences of others; 'tis like the Charity of the Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-hearted Jeſus, that melted him into Tears, when he beheld that perverſe and bloody City; <hi>O Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, Jeruſalem, thou that killeſt the Prophets, and ſtoneſt them that are ſent unto thee; how often would I have gathered thy Children toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as an Hen gathereth her Chickens under her Wings, and ye would not,</hi> Luke 13. 34.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But (as I ſaid) there is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Interpretation yet of theſe Words, <hi>Rejoyceth not in Iniquity:</hi>
                  <pb n="194" facs="tcp:56571:101"/>
It is St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s; and I like it the rather, becauſe it is his; <hi>viz.</hi> That Charitable Men are far from Rejoycing at the <hi>Calamity</hi> of thoſe that <hi>Suffer,</hi> eſpecially that wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Suffer by means of another's <hi>Iniquity.</hi> To Triumph and Dance upon a Ruined Neighbour, to Laugh at his Adverſity, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Delight, as thoſe Men did at <hi>David</hi>'s Misfortunes, <hi>There, there, ſo would we have it:</hi> This is a ſore Evil, a very horrible Viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Charity, which obligeth us to <hi>Rejoyce with them that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, and to Weep with them that Weep,</hi> Rom. 12. 15. That is, to Sympathize with our Brethren in every State and Condition.</p>
               <p>This carrieth its own Light with it. Now, for our Practice of this Matter, we muſt be careful to do two Things.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="195" facs="tcp:56571:101"/>
Firſt, We muſt conſtrue the Diſpenſations of Providence after a fair and <hi>kind</hi> manner. This is not a Place or Time for <hi>Rewards;</hi> thoſe are laid up for us in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: The preſent Life is for Trials and Diſcipline, to Train us up, and to Prepare us for a Bleſſed Eternity, by ſuch ways as God ſeeth beſt, and fitteſt for us. Many times Good Men fare Ill in this World, as well as the Bad, and ſometimes worſe; becauſe in ſome caſes they can do themſelves and others much more Good by their Hardſhips, than it is poſſible for them to do by any other means. Therefore we ſhould not look upon the ill Uſages Men meet with here as Arguments, either of Diſpleaſure in God, or of Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in his poor Suffering Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures;
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:56571:102"/>
But as ſo many Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of God's Wiſdom and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, who acteth after his own way, which is always for the beſt. Conſequently, to trample upon one in Diſtreſs, and to exult over him, as if he were out of the Divine Favour, becauſe his Caſe is hard; is both Uncharitableneſs towards the Man, and Irreligion towards God too; whoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings are always Wiſe and Good, though many times Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, till the Event opens the Meaning of them. God doth nothing in vain. As he is Good, and never grieves the Children of Men, but for good Purpoſes; ſo he is Juſt and Righteous too, and never ſpares the Workers of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity but for good Purpoſes alſo: For their Repentance, if they will be led to it; if not, for the full
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:56571:102"/>
manifeſtation of their Sins, and for his own Honour and Glory in the end, by making them Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to the World. <hi>Therefore,</hi> ſaith our Apoſtle, <hi>judge nothing before the time, till the Lord come, who both will bring to light the hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den things of Darkneſs, and will make manifeſt the Counſels of the Hearts; and then ſhall every Man have Praiſe of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 4. 5.</p>
               <p>The Second Thing we are to be careful of is, To <hi>help</hi> thoſe who want the Aſſiſtance of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable Hands; thoſe that Suffer by the <hi>Hand of Iniquity;</hi> thoſe that are Oppreſſed with Wrong. When the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Charity rejoyceth not</hi> in Iniquity, or in Men's Sufferings <hi>by</hi> Iniquity, there is much more intended, than what is Literally expreſs'd. Charitable
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:56571:103"/>
Men muſt ſhew their Grief for thoſe Sufferings, by <hi>Relieving</hi> and <hi>Aiding</hi> the Sufferers. Proſperity hath Friends enough; if we may call them Friends, who Congra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulate and Careſs us, while we are able to Reward them, or to do them Service. But if <hi>Job</hi> be caſt upon the Dunghil, or Chriſt be brought near the Croſs; the one is forſaken of his Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and the other of his very Diſciples. 'Tis Adverſity that ſhews the real, the <hi>faſt</hi> Friend; and then is our Time to expreſs our Charity, when another <hi>wants</hi> it, whether Friend, or Enemy; by endeavouring to Relieve him that Suffers by Iniquity: For if we uſe not our Endeavours for his Deliverance, it is to be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, that we are well enough pleaſed with his Condition; well
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:56571:103"/>
enough ſatisfied, though he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in it. And is this Charity? That Active, Generous, Reſtleſs Virtue, that knows no Bounds, but Impoſſibilities? That Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Grace, which is ready to offer up Life it ſelf? That God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Spirit, which is made up of Goodneſs, Mercy, and Love? No, no: Charity Befriendeth all, doeth Good to all, extendeth Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief and Compaſſion to all; to him that Suffers, and even to thoſe that do the Wrong; to thoſe that <hi>ſeek Counſel againſt the Juſt, and gnaſh upon him with their Teeth, Pſal.</hi> 37. 12. Their Caſe is to be Pitied indeed, becauſe their Day is coming; the Day, <hi>when God will render to every Man according to his VVorks: To them who by pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient continuance in well doing, ſeek for Glory, and Honour, and Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality,</hi>
                  <pb n="200" facs="tcp:56571:104"/>
                  <hi>God will give Eternal Life. But to thoſe who are Contentious, and do not obey the Truth, but obey <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs, he will render In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation and VVrath, Tribulation and Anguiſh, upon every Soul of Man that doeth Evil,</hi> Rom. 2. 6, 7, 8, 9.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="part">
               <head>XII.</head>
               <p>12. But I muſt haſten to the next Character St. <hi>Paul</hi> gives of <hi>Charity;</hi> which is, That <hi>it Rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth in the Truth.</hi> The beſt Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines take the Word here, not in a ſtrict, limited Senſe, as it ſignifies <hi>Truth</hi> in <hi>Speech</hi> only, in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to <hi>Lying;</hi> but in a very large Notion, as it ſignifies <hi>Probity of Heart, Sincerity</hi> in all <hi>Things,</hi> Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Uprightneſs, and Rectitude of Life, in oppoſition to all <hi>Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</hi> Charity is of no narrow
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:56571:104"/>
Spirit; but as diffuſive as the Ocean, as wide and ſpreading as the Univerſe; and therefore it is not fit to bound it up here within a narrow Senſe. In ſhort, it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the <hi>Entire</hi> and <hi>True Practice</hi> of Religion; and ſo the Apoſtle's meaning is, That Charitable Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are overjoy'd when Religion proſpereth and encreaſeth; when Truth and Righteouſneſs take Place, and gain Ground; when the Power of Godlineſs appeareth in Chriſtians Lives; when they perform their reſpective Duties truly, uprightly, and ſincerely, as it becometh their Profeſſion, and is ſuitable to their high Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</p>
               <p>This is peculiarly Applicable to thoſe of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Function, who cannot but be paſſionately affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with Joy unſpeakable, when
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:56571:105"/>
they find their Labours ſucceſsful; when the Work and Pleaſure of God proſpers in their Hands; when they ſee of the Travel of their Souls, and behold the Fruit of it to their Satisfaction: Nor can there be any ſuch great En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to Men of that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Office, as to be able to call their ſeveral Charges, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> did the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> their <hi>Joy and Crown of Rejoycing,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 2. 19. Or to ſay as St. <hi>John</hi> did in the like caſe, 3 <hi>John</hi> 4. <hi>I have no greater Joy, than to hear that my Children walk in the Truth:</hi> That is, as becometh the Truth; in Holineſs and Sobriety, in Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Meekneſs, in Peace and Love; and in all thoſe Virtues which Adorn the Doctrine of God their Saviour.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="203" facs="tcp:56571:105"/>
But this Matter doth not only concern Miniſters of the Goſpel. All People ſhould be their Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants in their reſpective Stations and Degrees, to forward the true Intereſt and Advancement of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. This is the moſt Zealous Expreſſion of our hearty Love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God; the moſt ſignificant Argument of Charity towards our Brethren; the trueſt Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of an Enlarged and Noble Mind: To take Pleaſure in ſeeing Virtue and Holineſs thrive, and the Kingdom of Chriſt advanced in the World. In order there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, every one ſhould be Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in his Place and Capacity in Encouraging the Growth of true Piety, and in helping to Promote the Ends of the Goſpel: So that Vice and Irreligion may be, not only out of Faſhion, but out of
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:56571:106"/>
Countenance too. This is the greateſt Charity in the World, becauſe on this depends the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Souls, which every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Member of the Church is obliged to help on, and ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, as much as in him lieth. Begin at <hi>Home,</hi> and Encourage your Families to be truly Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious in the firſt place. The holy Pſalmiſt ſets you a great Example, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101. from Verſ. 2. to Verſ. 8. <hi>I will walk in my Houſe with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Heart. I will take no wicked Thing in hand: I hate the Sins of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfaithfulneſs; there ſhall no ſuch cleave unto me. A froward Heart ſhall depart from me; I will not know</hi> (or countenance) <hi>a wicked Perſon. VVhoſo privily ſlandereth his Neighbour, him will I deſtroy: VVhoſo hath alſo a proud Look and high Stomach, I will not ſuffer him.</hi>
                  <pb n="205" facs="tcp:56571:106"/>
                  <hi>Mine Eyes look upon ſuch as are faithful in the Land, that they may dwell with me: VVhoſo leadeth a Godly Life, he ſhall be my Servant. There ſhall no deceitful Perſon dwell in my Houſe; he that telleth Lies, ſhall not tarry in my ſight.</hi> Our great Buſineſs in this Life, is not to raiſe our ſelves Fortunes, but to do God Service, and to do the greateſt Good we can to thoſe about us: And the true way of doing both is, by our Examples, Councels, and Authority; to En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage all under our Care, to live Soberly, Righteouſly, and Godly, in this preſent World.</p>
               <p>And next to our Private Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, the <hi>Neighbourhood</hi> we belong to, muſt have a due ſhare of our Zeal alſo. As we go about, we ſhould ſow Righteouſneſs, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially where we find the Soyl
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:56571:107"/>
good: Weed out the Cockle and Thiſtles; Suppreſs every Thing that is Scandalous and Hurtful; Mend Breaches; Reform Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; Reprove Immorality; Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Honeſty; Countenance the Meek and Gentle; Teach Men to be Humble and Peaceable, to be Orderly and Pious, to be Juſt and Charitable; to go to their Prayers, to live in Unity, to ſubmit to thoſe who have the Rule over them in the Lord; we ſhould teach Men how to Love, and how to be Beloved: In a word, we ſhould make it our buſineſs to Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and Aſſiſt one another, ſo that in this World we may all lead Quiet and Peaceable Lives, in all Godlineſs and Honeſty. This is the way to ſerve the Truth, to promote the Truth, to advance its Intereſt and Honour, to make
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:56571:107"/>
it ſpread, flouriſh, and proſper ſo, that we may have cauſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing indeed; what Joy had St. <hi>Paul</hi> to ſee Religion propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, though it was ſometimes by the help of thoſe, who were ſpur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red on chiefly by Emulation, that they might outſhine him, and leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen the Glory of his Zeal and Succeſs? <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. Some indeed preach Chriſt even of Envy and Strife, and ſome alſo of Good Will: The one preach Chriſt of Contention, the other of Love. What then? Why notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every way, whether in Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, or in Truth; <hi>Chriſt is preached, and therein</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I do rejoyce; yea, and I will rejoyce.</hi> Some Portion of this Joy ſhall every one have, that helpeth to ſerve and advance Truth in his Place and Vocation, and according
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:56571:108"/>
to his Abilities. Chriſt is thereby ſerved in ſome meaſure, and the Comfort of it will return into the Charitable and Good Man's Boſom, though he doeth no more than what a good Example com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to. I am ſure, that when we come to lie upon our Death-beds, where Conſcience uſeth to ſpeak plain and home, a greater Joy and Comfort there cannot be, than to reflect upon the good Examples we have given our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and the many good Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces we have done them; and to conſider, that in doing to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry leaſt of theſe, we have done them unto Chriſt, and ſerved Chriſt. Then there will be room for that Prayer of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> Iſa. 38. 3. <hi>Remember now, O Lord, I beſeech thee, how I have walked be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee in Truth, and with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect</hi>
                  <pb n="209" facs="tcp:56571:108"/>
                  <hi>Heart, and have done that which is good in thy ſight.</hi> What Joy and Comfort thoſe will then have, who hinder the Progreſs of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, by diſſeminating Evil Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, by ſomenting Diſſentions and Animoſities, and by other Antichriſtian Practiſes, that Day at fartheſt will ſhew; when every one's Conſcience, (if he hath any left) how drowſie ſoever it may be now, will be ſure to awake, and tell him his own.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="part">
               <head>XIII.</head>
               <p>13. The Character of <hi>Charity</hi> which followeth is, <hi>That it beareth all Things.</hi> 'Twere more agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to render this place thus; Charity <hi>covereth</hi> or <hi>concealeth</hi> all Things, (which are done amiſs;) for this ſeems here to be the moſt
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:56571:109"/>
natural Senſe of the <hi>Greek</hi> Word; the other Notion of it, which concerneth the <hi>bearing</hi> or <hi>ſuffering</hi> all Things, belonging rather to the laſt Character of <hi>Charity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To lay Things to ones Charge, which he is not Guilty of, is very Unjuſt; to blame him upon meer Suſpicion, is very Raſh; and to divulge every Fault, though we certainly know it, is very Uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable.</p>
               <p>In order to our due Practice as to this point, we are to note by way of Caution; That the Laws of Charity do not oblige us to conceal the Crimes of another in theſe five Caſes:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Where the Criminal him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf hath made the Fact Noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="211" facs="tcp:56571:109"/>
2. Where the Intereſt of an whole Society is nearly concern'd.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Where Publick Juſtice ought to be done.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Where Charity to the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender requires the taking notice of it.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Where the diſcovering of a Sin is abſolutely neceſſary for ones own Vindication.</p>
               <p>In all Caſes the greateſt Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity muſt take place. But where the End of making anothers Faults known, is not Good, Neceſſary, Juſt, or Charitable, but Mean, and Hurtful rather, we ſhould be as tender of a Neighbour's Fame, as of our own; and no more ſpeak of his Crimes, than we durſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover <hi>Secrets,</hi> which in Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Honour we are bound to keep in the dark.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="212" facs="tcp:56571:110"/>
There are two great Reaſons, for which <hi>Charity</hi> requires us to to be very careful of this.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the divulging of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Offences is ſo far from do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him any Good, that it is a probable way to harden him in a courſe of Wickedneſs. Shame is ſometimes the ſtrongeſt Bridle, to reſtrain People from Things that are of bad Report: If you take off that Check, there is no ſtaying them; but <hi>they turn to their Courſe, as the Horſe ruſheth into the Battel,</hi> Jer. 8. 6. Nor is there a more ready means to make them Shameleſs, than to expoſe thoſe Miſcarriages to open view, which they cannot but like the leſs, becauſe they are afraid of a Diſcovery: Private Admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, if kindly and diſcreetly ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:56571:110"/>
to them themſelves, often prove a ſucceſsful Method of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming thoſe who have as yet a Brow; becauſe thoſe Admonitions are an Argument of Friendſhip, which makes the ſofteſt and deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Impreſſion: For which reaſon, ſaith our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. 15. <hi>If thy Brother treſpaſs againſt thee, go and tell him his fault between thee and him alone.</hi> This is the moſt likely way to gain (or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form) him; whereas to proclaim, or whiſper out his Faults, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to Perſons unconcerned, and that too with Pleaſure, and as a ſort of Entertainment, is the ready means of rendring his Heart obdurate, and of making all Councels recoyl, as from a Flint: Becauſe in this caſe, it is not Charity that ſpeaks, but ill Nature, and a deſigning Mind.
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:56571:111"/>
Many times it happens, that while a Man's Sins lie cloſe under Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert, he is brought to a Senſe and Reformation of them, by the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Convictions of Conſcience, and by God's Bleſſing from the Pulpit. There is the greater En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to amend, becauſe he feareth not Reproach. But if he be brought upon the open Stage, and expoſed to the Scof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fings of the Multitude; like a Deer hunted with a publick Cry, and brought at laſt to the Bay, 'tis odds but he will adventure upon any Dangers, the Clamors of the World will make him deſperate; ſo that in ſtead of Reforming, he will purſue his Sins the more gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, preſuming that the future Pleaſures, or Gainfulneſs of them, will pay ſomething for the loſs of his former Reputation.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="215" facs="tcp:56571:111"/>
2. Beſides the Miſchief done to the Actor by Uncharitable Dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, no little Hurt is done to thoſe to whom the Sin is told; which ſtill confirms that of the Wiſe Man, <hi>Prov.</hi> 10. 12. <hi>Love co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereth all Sins.</hi> By hearing of ill Things, People learn inſenſibly to do them; becauſe there is a Contagion in all Wickedneſs; whereby the Minds of thoſe to whom it is diſcovered, are infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by degrees, if there be not a very ſtrong Antidote to keep out the Peſtilence, which is rarely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided in thoſe caſes. For 'tis not uſual with us to lend an Ear, but to Things we are very <hi>willing</hi> to hear of; and by this means an Evil Report doth naturally caſt the ſtronger Influence, and doth naturally make the deeper Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, the Mind being <hi>diſpoſed</hi> for
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:56571:112"/>
it before-hand. Upon which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, 'tis neceſſary for every good Man with all poſſible care to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve his <hi>Ear</hi> from Infection, leſt it paſs through <hi>that</hi> to the Heart: For a Relation many times be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes an Example; ſo that by being made acquainted with the Faults of others, People are much the worſe themſelves. The Sin is propoſed for imitation, which the Tale-bearer ſeemeth to reprehend; it is like the opening of a Plague-Sore, which a Charitable Hand will be tender of doing, for fear of propagating the Diſeaſe. Our Minds are apt to be ſtrangely wrought upon by every Thing about us, becauſe there is not in our Nature that ſtrong defenſive Faculty, which is in ſome other Creatures. Fiſh indeed retain their freſh Taſte, although they ſwim
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:56571:112"/>
in the ſalteſt Waters; but Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature is apt to participate of the Temper of the People, and of the Condition of the Climate where we live, and our Diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions alter accordingly; juſt as Waters, which paſs through the Channels of the Earth, vary their Savour with the Veins of the Soyls through which they ſlide. In a corrupt Place, 'tis an eaſie thing to be corrupted; and one great Reaſon is, becauſe the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of a Neighbour's Vices is apt to breed in another an Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the ſame Evils; it worketh in another preſently and inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly, if not a full <hi>Approbation,</hi> yet <hi>a leſs Diſlike</hi> of thoſe Corruptions, which their Eyes and Ears are uſed to the Senſe of: So that when one comes to be familiarly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the Irreligious
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:56571:113"/>
Courſes of bad Neighbours, he is in a great Hazard; and 'tis great odds, if he doth not in time make thoſe Courſes his own Choice; becauſe this is a great Encouragement to Vice, that it wants not a Precedent.</p>
               <p>Therefore to expreſs our Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in this caſe, let us carefully obſerve that Advice of the Son of <hi>Sirach,</hi> Ecclus. 19. 7, 8. <hi>Rehearſe not unto another what is told unto thee, and thou ſhalt fare never the worſe. Whether it be friend or foe, talk not of other Men's Lives; and if thou canſt without Offence, reveal them not.</hi> For Charity-ſake eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Story is not to be told; for though it be true, it may be hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; though it be not hurtful in the firſt Report, it may be ſo in the conſequence; becauſe Fame is like the Cloud which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet's
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:56571:113"/>
Servant ſaw, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18. 44. the further it ſpreads, the greater it grows, till there be no more compariſon between its Original, and its Increaſe, than there is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the breadth of a Man's Hand, and the Dimenſions of the Firmament; and who can tell how Miſchievous and Terrible the End will be? <hi>The Tongue is a world of Iniquity,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>James,</hi> ch. 3. v. 6. And for the preventing of a great deal, let me recommend theſe few Things in ſhort to your Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Practice.</p>
               <p>With all poſſible Art and ſpeed, ſtop the Mouths of thoſe, <hi>who, like the old Athenians, ſpend their Time in nothing elſe,</hi> (for the moſt part) <hi>but either to tell, or to hear ſome new Thing,</hi> Act. 17. 21. In ſpight of good Neighbourhood, and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:56571:114"/>
too, ſome <hi>will wander about from Houſe to Houſe, Tatlers, Buſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bodies, ſpeaking Things that they ought not,</hi> 1 Tim. 5. 13. The on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Buſineſs of ſuch idle People is, to lay open the Lives of others, to ſtain their good Name, and to ſpoil the Savour of that which is better than precious Ointment; by caſting in ſuch dead Flies, as turn the Perfume into a Stink. And what Injuries come by this Evil Practice, not only to parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Perſons, but to whole So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties, is too too manifeſt. The leaſt is that which <hi>Salomon</hi> mentions, (though that is too great, and ſometimes irreparable,) <hi>a Whiſperer ſeparateth chief Friends,</hi> Prov. 16. 28. A good Remedy in this caſe is, to turn the Ear aſide, and not ſuffer it to receive any hurtful Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Such Stories are not wont
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:56571:114"/>
to be told People that are deaf, becauſe there the Ends of the Whiſperer cannot be anſwered. 'Twould be an Effectual and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable Means of deſtroying thoſe Works of Darkneſs, to diſcourage the Authors of them, by letting them ſee, how Unprofitable their Works are in the firſt Practiſe.</p>
               <p>If another's Sin chance to fall under thine Eye, expreſs your Charity, by laying a Mantle over it with a quick Hand, that it may not indanger the reſt by being expoſed to publick View. It is thy Brother's Nakedneſs that is ſeen; and where there is ſuch a ſhameful Spectacle, Love ſhould imitate the Piety of <hi>Noah</hi>'s two Sons, <hi>Shem</hi> and <hi>Japhet;</hi> who, that they might not caſt the leaſt glance upon their Father's Naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, went backward with a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:56571:115"/>
upon their Shoulders; ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turing rather their ſtumbling at his Feet, than they would behold his Shame. Curſed was <hi>Cham,</hi> that not content to have been an Eye-witneſs of the Indecent Sight, Scoff'd at it too, and became the Proclaimer of it.</p>
               <p>If the Sin be ſo manifeſt that it cannot, or ſo foul that it muſt not be hid, expreſs your Charity by ſpeaking of it (and that with Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Kindneſs alſo) to the Criminal himſelf, who is the Party concerned to Repent, and to mend his Life for the future. The way to cure a Flaw, is not to run to ſuch as are whole, but to dreſs the Side where the Wound lieth. Though it be Oyl and Wine too, which you pour in there, the Smart is tolerable, becauſe the Operation is proper; and the Hand
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:56571:115"/>
that works, is Charitable and Friendly. Other Methods are to be avoided, becauſe they always Fret, and very rarely Heal.</p>
               <p>After all, in ſtead of diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring other Men's Faults, it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for every one to look into his own. And if People would but turn their Eyes homeward, they would find ſo much Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment for them there, that they would have neither Need, nor Leiſure to look abroad. There is in every Breaſt ſo much Nature, whatever there be of Grace, that our continual Care is neceſſary to Cleanſe our ſelves from the one, and to Increaſe the other. Nor is this poſſible to be done, but by ſearching narrowly into ones own State; which if all Inquiſitive Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple would do, they could not but diſcover preſently this one great
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:56571:116"/>
Fault of their own, that by prying curiouſly after others, they have all along overlook'd themſelves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="part">
               <head>XIV.</head>
               <p>14. So far is <hi>Charity</hi> from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting to reveal the Failings and Miſcarriages of others, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> gives this further Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of a Charitable Perſon, that <hi>he believeth all Things;</hi> that is, all Things that are <hi>Good,</hi> and all Things that are Reaſonable for a Good Man to believe. Credulity at large is no Virtue; or, if it be, 'tis no ſafe one; becauſe 'tis ſo eaſie a matter to be deceiv'd; eſpecially in <hi>Men,</hi> which upon the Weights are the moſt deceitful; and becauſe it is ſometimes ſuch a woeful and calamitous Thing to be deceived indeed. There are many
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:56571:116"/>
Dangers, which Religion doth not require us to run into, by Truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without Reſerve; and the Queſtion may be Undeterminable, which of the two is moſt to be blamed, He that believes <hi>every Thing;</hi> or he that believes <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi> that is told him? On each hand it is not Charity, but Folly that is the Aſcendant. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle's meaning therefore is, That in Caſes which are not plain and clear beyond juſt Reaſon of Doubtfulneſs, true Chriſtian Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity inclines one to believe favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably, and to Err rather on the right Hand, by entertaining a kind Opinion even when it is not apparently deſerved. St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſo well underſtood the Operations of Virtue, was ſenſible what good Effects this is apt to produce; and how naturally it tendeth to
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:56571:117"/>
make the Minds and Lives of People eaſie; and, on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, how hurtful it is to the Peace and Comfort of particular Men, and whole Societies, to take up hard Conceits without ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and plain Grounds; to run away with them, and to act upon them. Hatreds and Miſchief fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in the end; witneſs thoſe Outrages which he himſelf com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, upon his own groundleſs Apprehenſions. He believed once, that Jeſus Chriſt was a Deceiver; and that his Diſciples were a very Dangerous and Heretical Sect. Upon which falſe and groundleſs Principle, he verily thought with himſelf, that <hi>he ought to do many Things contrary to the Name of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus of Nazareth,</hi> Act. 26. 9. And how fatal and miſchievous was that one <hi>Thought</hi> to the Church
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:56571:117"/>
of Chriſt? What a world of Vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Miſery did it not put them to? And yet all the while the People he Perſecuted were In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent; and the Perſecution was bottom'd upon nothing, but his own unreaſonable and wild Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions. Thus it is, when Men believe without Judgment and Candor; believe Evil Things up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Evil Surmiſes, and ſide with Siniſter Notions, as their firſt Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations and Paſſions ſway them. Havock, and Outrage, are the uſual Conſequents; Peace, and a good Conſcience, and Charity, and whatſoever elſe is deſirable, all goes to wrack in the Storm, which ſometimes cannot be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed without a Sacrifice of Blood too.</p>
               <p>Now for the increaſing in us a Spirit of Charity, and for the due
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:56571:118"/>
expreſſing it as to this Point, this General Rule muſt be carefully, obſerved; <hi>To take Things always in the beſt Senſe;</hi> and never to give way to Hard Thoughts, where there is room for kind or favourable Conſtructions. Many times indeed Men's Guilt appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſo foul and open, that the Evidence is too ſtrong for thoſe that are willing to be Scepticks in that particular. In which caſe, Charity no more requires you to believe contrary to your Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, than it binds you to diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit the Teſtimony of all your Senſes. As, where People act ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſly every Day, in ſpight of all the Charity in the World; you cannot but look upon them as very ill Men. But where the Matter is doubtful and uncertain, Charity ſhould always ſet it in the
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:56571:118"/>
faireſt Light; or rather I ſhould ſay, in the <hi>darkeſt</hi> Corner, to blind the Guilt as much as is poſſible, and to hide it even from our own Eyes. Remember the Charity of the Lord Jeſus upon the Croſs, when his Blood-thirſty Enemies had now done their very worſt againſt Him. One would have thought, their Malice was open enough: For <hi>Pilate</hi> himſelf was ſatisfied of his Innocence; <hi>He knew</hi> (ſaith the Evangeliſt) <hi>that for Envy they had delivered him,</hi> Mat. 27. 18. And yet to cover their Sin in ſome meaſure, He himſelf pleaded their Ignorance in that Charitable Prayer for them; <hi>Father, forgive them, for they know not what they do,</hi> Luke 23. 34. Had it been poſſible, he could have found in his Heart to have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed their Guilt from his Father's
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:56571:119"/>
view. But God ſeeth the very Secrets of the Heart; all Things are naked and open to him, with whom we have to do. But this is one of God's incommunicable Attributes. We ſee at beſt but through a Glaſs; a dark and dim View; and our Sight is much the dimmer, when we would look into Men's Breaſts, where we have no Glaſs at all to look through. Therefore where we are left to Conjecture, our Opinion ſhould be on the Charitable ſide, becauſe our Eye can have a direct Stroke upon the Principle of another's Action. Perhaps it was Inadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency; perhaps it proceeded from Ignorance; perhaps from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Humane Frailties: Many Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes Charity will help us to find out, before we need charge it upon the Heart.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="231" facs="tcp:56571:119"/>
This General Rule, of putting the beſt Senſe upon Men's Actions, being laid before you, I ſhall add theſe few Particulars for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Practice of it. Not to be eaſie in believing the <hi>firſt</hi> Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations. By our daily Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence we may find, that the firſt Account of Things is commonly the Falſeſt, becauſe it is uſually attended with Partiality, to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs the Minds of People with a Prejudice before-hand; it is ſo in Men's relating Things of others, eſpecially of their Superiors in Church or State; Partiality is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver wanting there. Some have a ſort of Itch, both in their Minds and Tongues, to ſpeak Evil of thoſe they care not for. Upon which account, when an ill Thing is offered to our Belief, before Credit be given to a foul Story,
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:56571:120"/>
we ſhould conſider, Whether the Suggeſtion may not proceed from Hearts which are touch'd with a Diſeaſe ſomewhat reſembling the Botch of <hi>Egypt,</hi> Many are apt to take up hard Opinions upon Truſt; which is not only Uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable, but Unrighteous too: Becauſe the Party is thereby rifled of his Reputation at all adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. If the Story be falſe, the Injuſtice is manifeſt; if it be but probable, there is Probability a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it too; if it be altogether uncertain, it is not Judgment, but Partiality, that Governs the Belief of it: And after all, if Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be enough, every Man muſt lie at Mercy for his Innocence, though his own Conſcience ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit him. 'Tis neceſſary there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in all ill Reports, to ſuſpend ones Perſwaſion till the Truth
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:56571:120"/>
appears; and rather to be for the Charitable Senſe, becauſe to be ſure no Wrong is done in that caſe; whereas Judgment is Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty when it paſſeth upon Surmiſe; and he that Suffers by the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, Suffers not for his own, but for another's Fault; that is, for another's too quick and raſh Judgment.</p>
               <p>In ſhort, That Charity may make us believe all the Good we hear, and hardly any thing but what is Good; let it teach our Hearts to be <hi>in Love with Peace.</hi> Reports, whether they be true or falſe, are <hi>diſquieting,</hi> and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the firſt Deſign of them be, the End is Quarrel; a Miſchief that is attended with ſuch a Train of ill Conſequences, that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be too careful in uſing our utmoſt Endeavours to choak the
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:56571:121"/>
Original Cauſe. <hi>Study to be quiet, and to do your own buſineſs,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 4. 11. If Men's Hearts and Hands were thus ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly and wiſely employed, it would be a conciſe, but a very effectual way of ſetting their Ears and Tongues much more at reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="part">
               <head>XV.</head>
               <p>15. The Fifteenth Character of <hi>Charity</hi> is, That it <hi>hopeth all Things.</hi> As by the former Deſcription St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſhews, how we are to think as to Things <hi>preſent,</hi> or <hi>paſt;</hi> ſo by this he directs us, what Thoughts we are to entertain as to the <hi>future.</hi> However Men be repreſented, or may appear, we muſt not deſpair of them, or give them utterly for gone, as Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:56571:121"/>
and Caſtaways; undone and loſt to all Eternity. The Reaſons of this are taken from the Office of <hi>Charity;</hi> which is, to do all the Good we can in every re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Now, firſt, to account a Man paſt all Recovery, is the ready way to ſuperſede the uſe of thoſe Means, which in ordinary Caſes are thought fit and proper to bring People to Repentance. Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is a moſt Active and Zealous Grace, eſpecially when it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd about a Soul. No good Methods are wanting there, as long as there are Hopes. True Charity is apt to uſe Reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, Reaſonings, Counſels, Warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Prayers; every Thing that the miſerable Creature needs; and ſometimes the greateſt Pains are
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:56571:122"/>
little enough; I am loth to ſay, too little. But all is thought ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous, and to no purpoſe, in a Caſe that is judged deſperate: All Endeavours, as well as Hopes, are given over; becauſe none will undertake a Task, which he verily believes impoſſible: It would be all one, as if he ſhould Preach or Pray over a Rock, with a vain Deſign to remove it out of its Place with his Breath. It is a great Diſcouragement even to a Charitable Man, to have to do with thoſe, whoſe Spirits and Courſes are wicked, though they make great Profeſſions of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: And their Caſe is the more deplorable, if they truſt in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that they are Righteous, while their Hearts and Souls are out of frame. Yet an Hypocrite may be Reclaimed, though with
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:56571:122"/>
much difficulty. The Shame of the World, or the Gnawings of Conſcience, or the Melancholy Circumſtances of a Sick Bed, or the Frightful Proſpect of Hell, or ſome outward extraordinary Judgment, may in time bring him to a ſenſe of his ſad Condition. Captivity and Chains humbled <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> himſelf; and one day God will be too hard for the ſturdieſt Sons of <hi>Belial.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, as long as there are ſome, though but faint and glimmering Hopes, there are ſome Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements, ſuch as they be. But for Labour, which Men think will be certainly and utterly loſt, they can find no Reaſon; and this is one great Miſchief which comes by Uncharitableneſs of this kind, that it damps the Minds and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours of Men, and violently
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:56571:123"/>
hinders the carrying on of the Cauſe of the Son of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But, Secondly, more than this; ſuch deſperate Perſwaſions touching the forlorn State of others, are a moſt powerful Temptation to thoſe Uncharitable Wretches, to Treat them with the extreameſt Outrage, who have the ill Luck to fall under their deadly Sentence. Witneſs thoſe Cruelties which have been acted by ſome <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> as they have had the Power in their Hands over ſuch as they are pleaſed to call <hi>Hereticks.</hi> How falſe ſoever the Premiſſes be, the Conſequence is Natural. For how can any gentle Dealings be expected by thoſe, who are preſumed by theſe Zealots to be in a Damned State? If God hath Curſed them, why may not they? If God hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:56571:123"/>
them to Eternal Flames, why may not ſuch as think ſo, caſt them into the Fire here? This they believe, is but the beginning of God's Work; and where is the Fault, if they do like God? It is thus in all Caſes, where Men have the confidence to Uſurp Chriſt's Authority, and to Judge before the time; whom they will, they Save; and whom they can, they Puniſh; with this Difference, That in the midſt of Wrath, they think not, as God doth, upon Mercy.</p>
               <p>Alas! what becomes all this while of the great Chriſtian Rule, <hi>Charity hopeth all Things?</hi> And the beſt it can of all Men? Charity requires us to do others all the Good Offices which lie in our Power; and when all is done, the ſame Charity doth bind us alſo to
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:56571:124"/>
leave every one to <hi>ſtand or fall to his own Maſter.</hi> Lord! that any Men ſhould proceed to that ſinful degree of Immoderation and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolence, as to confine all true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion within a Party; and to make another's Diſſent the Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Mark of an Apoſtate and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate. 'Tis well for us all, that a Good God governs the World; that he hath the Cuſtody of our Souls; and that he is to be the Judge, who was the Redeemer of them: For were we to determine one another's final Lot, who is there almoſt that could be ſaved? Suppoſe there were Five hundred Parties in the World, after this rate it would be Five hundred to Nothing, but every Man would be Damned, becauſe each Party would Damn all but it ſelf; and if that were Damned too by Four
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:56571:124"/>
hundred ninety and nine, it would be very great Fortune for it to eſcape. Now, what is all this, but to thruſt the Lord Jeſus out of his Throne, and for us to leap upon the Bench, who muſt our ſelves be Arraigned at his Tribunal? In the Name of God, let us all walk by the ſame Rule, and hope the beſt of all Men. Perhaps we may be ſometimes miſtaken in our Hopes; but an Error of that kind hath an eaſie Pardon, if it ſtands in any need of it: I am ſure we can be no Loſers by our Charity. Our Caſe may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate for want of it, eſpecially if our Uncharitableneſs drive us on to kindle Eternal Fires for our Brethren: There the Loſs is likely to be Infinite, without any eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping. We ſhall periſh our ſelves by the Flames which we have
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:56571:125"/>
raiſed; as the King of <hi>Babylon</hi>'s Servants did, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. 22. when they threw <hi>Shadrach, Meſhach,</hi> and <hi>Abednego,</hi> into the burning fiery Furnace. <hi>Judge not,</hi> ſaith our Bleſſed Saviour, <hi>that ye be not judged: For with what Judgment ye judge, ye ſhall be judged; and with what Meaſure ye mete, it ſhall be meaſured to you again,</hi> Mat. 7. 1, 2. St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, though he had ſuch abundance of Revelations; yet he durſt not take upon him to paſs Sentence, no not upon profeſs'd Infidels: <hi>What have I to do to judge them that are without?</hi> 1. Cor. 5. 12. They and all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind muſt be left to God's Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, who is the only Searcher of Hearts; the only Judge that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Infallibly who is, or ſhall be his. His Mercies are infinite, his Paths are as yet paſt finding out: <hi>His</hi>
                  <pb n="243" facs="tcp:56571:125"/>
                  <hi>Ways are not as our Ways, nor are his Thoughts as our Thoughts: For as the Heavens are higher than the Earth, ſo are his Ways higher than our Ways, and his Thoughts than our Thoughts,</hi> Iſa. 55. 8, 9. He hath indeed affix'd a dreadful Penalty to his Laws, eſpecially under the Goſpel: But whether he hath not reſerved to himſelf a Power of Remitting the Penalty, in ſome ſpecial and extraordinary Caſes, is to us a Secret. There is indeed but one ordinary and ſtrait Path to Heaven, by Faith and true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; yet who can tell, but that the Wiſdom and Providence of God may bring it ſo about, that ſome little By-Paths, wherein People of good and honeſt Minds, though of different Perſwaſions, do go now, may in the end fall into the ready Road? There is
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:56571:126"/>
indeed this Doom annexed to the Promulgation of the Goſpel, <hi>He that believeth not, ſhall be damned;</hi> and yet Charity will not ſuffer us to paſs the Sentence of Eternal Ruine, either upon thoſe Children which die Unbaptized; or upon that vaſt Number of poor well-meaning Heathens, who never heard of Chriſt; and therefore lived and died in Infidelity. For ought we know, God may have ſome ſecret Ways of applying the Merits of Jeſus Chriſt to the Souls of ſome People, whom Cenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and Uncharitable Wretches look upon now, as utterly loſt and gone. In all Caſes we ſhould judge Charitably of others, as hoping for a favourable Judgment our ſelves: And if in our Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity we chance to err, 'tis an Error on the Right Hand however; and
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:56571:126"/>
rather to be ventured on, than a rigid Truth, if it be uncertain. In Heaven there are many Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; room enough to hold us all, if all of us will make it our buſineſs to get thither. But the loſs of my Neighbour's Glory will not make any addition unto mine; and therefore we ſhould wiſh, that the whole World may be ſaved. Till we are better ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the Counſels of God, we muſt take heed, how we determine the Bounds of Men's Habitations to Eternity, or ſet out their Lots. Remember they are your Brethren; Men for whom Chriſt died, and for whom God may have Mercy in ſtore, whatever others raſhly think. And certainly you may well afford them your Charity, whom God himſelf, for ought you know,
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:56571:127"/>
may youchſafe with Everlaſting Salvation.</p>
               <p>To expreſs then our Charity aright as to this particular, we ſhould never quite deſpair of any Men, nor give over all Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours for them, as if their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition were altogether deſperate; but uſe ſuch Means, as are neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary and proper to bring the moſt miſerable Wretches to a Senſe of their true State. For who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, but one time or other God may give a Bleſſing to our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours? Who knoweth but perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture he will give ſuch Souls Repentance to the acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Truth, that they may recover themſelves out of the Snare of the Devil? Theſe are true Expreſſions of Charity in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, to be always one the Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hand; to be ſtill upon apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:56571:127"/>
Means, upon uſing Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, to let our hearty Wiſhes and Prayers accompany our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, and ſo to leave the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of all to God; and all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, eſpecially our Brethren in the Common Faith; to God's merciful Judgment; hoping and thinking the beſt we can of them to the very laſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="part">
               <head>XVI.</head>
               <p>16. This being ſufficiently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, I come at length to the Sixteenth and laſt Character, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> gives in this his Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Charity;</hi> that it <hi>Endureth all Things:</hi> That is, it teacheth and helps us to be <hi>Patient</hi> under all our Sufferings. Howſoever we fall into a Suffering Condition; whether by the particular Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:56571:128"/>
of God, for our Tryal and Correction; or by the Rage and Power of Tyrants, for Truth and Righteouſneſs-ſake; or by ſome Infirmity, or Diſtemper in our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; or by ſome outward Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingence; or by the Wickedneſs of private Men; by their Pride, Covetouſneſs, Revengeful Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, and the like; or by means of the different Perſwaſions, which others entertain about Matters of Religion. Whenſoever, and how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever any Things happen to us, which are Grievous and Afflictive, we ſhould endure them; ſo as becomes Men trained up under a Suffering Saviour, with Temper, and Fortitude, and <hi>patient Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance in Well-doing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Apoſtle hath very fitly placed this Character of <hi>Charity</hi> laſt; for Patience is a Virtue
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:56571:128"/>
that followeth others in the Rear. Notwithſtanding all our Virtues, our Lot may be to Suffer at laſt; and therefore we have need to be armed with Patience after all. <hi>Ye have need of Patience, that after ye have done the Will of God, ye may receive the Promiſe,</hi> Heb. 10. 36.</p>
               <p>The Truth is, it is a Virtue that is attended with a great Retinue; as, with Meekneſs, Humility, Self-Denial, Charity, Modeſty, Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs of Mind; Chriſtian Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimity, Conſtancy, Piety, Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and the like: For without theſe, it is impoſſible to be Patient after a Chriſtian manner, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when Injuries and Indignities are beyond the common Size. But at this time, I ſhall diſcourſe of it only as it bears relation to Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
               <pb n="246" facs="tcp:56571:129"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="247" facs="tcp:56571:129"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="248" facs="tcp:56571:130"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="249" facs="tcp:56571:130"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <p>
                  <pb n="250" facs="tcp:56571:131"/>
Now any one that duly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the various Injuries which are done by Men of Unquiet and Stormy Tempers, may eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern how perfective of Charity this Virtue is.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Impatient People are not ſo much as Friends to themſelves. Though one would think they were ſecure of their <hi>own</hi> Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and their Unquietneſs ſeems to argue, that they have very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Affection for any elſe; yet in Reality they are their own moſt hurtful Enemies. Every croſs Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident puts them upon the Fret; and the more active and buſie their Thoughts are, the greater ſtill is the Fermentation: Either Pride, or Envy, or Covetouſneſs, or Intemperance; nay, many times bare Imagination, helps to raiſe
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:56571:131"/>
the Diſtemper of the Mind to ſuch an high pitch, that it termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates in Frenzy, or in a Symptome that is very like it: And what Comfort can there be in ſuch a ones Life, where there is ſo much Uproar? Or what Peace and Complacency can there be in a Mind, which upon every Breath of Air falls into an Agitation, and is Rolling and Reſtleſs, like the Waves of the Sea, which in a Tempeſt yields nothing but Noiſe and Foam, beſides the danger of Shipwracks? Patience keeps a Calm upon the Coaſt; ſo that there is either a perfect Serenity, or, at worſt, but a little Cloud; which upon deliberate Thoughts doth ſoon vaniſh: And by this means, the reſt of the Divine Graces con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in an indiſturbed Condition, and the Soul becomes every day
<pb n="252" facs="tcp:56571:132"/>
more and more fruitful in Good Works; like the <hi>Halcyon,</hi> (to which ſome Divines have compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Church) a Sea-Bird, whoſe only Breeding-time is in a great Tranquility.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It were the better, if Impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Spirits did injure none but themſelves: That Wrong they are bound to bear, if they will bear any thing. But the Miſchief of this Vice is, That it loves to be Vexatious and Hurtful to all that are round about it. A petulant, froward piece of Carnality; that is ready at hand to Avenge the Quarrel of every other Luſt, and to be an Executioner in its Cauſe. Hence come Malicious Deſigns; Uncharitable Conſtructions; Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probrious Speeches; Revengeful Arts; Studied Oppreſſions; Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary
<pb n="253" facs="tcp:56571:132"/>
Suits at Law; Sangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Proceedings; and moſt of thoſe Wicked and Mean Things, which are a Diſgrace to Humane Nature, as well as Religion; and a Nuſance to all Societies. The Patient Man doth not lay and throw about him after a ſpightful manner, or to baſe Ends, or with vile and lewd Purpoſes; becauſe there is a Principle of true Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity, and a Spirit of Fortitude and Conſtancy which he acteth upon. This makes his Mind great, and ſets him much above thoſe Odious and Low Methods which are plain Arguments of a Mind that is Sordid and Degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate. 'Tis infinitely Greater to bear a Wrong, than to do it. The Pooreſt and moſt Contemptible Creature can <hi>annoy;</hi> but 'tis the <hi>Man</hi> only, and the <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> that
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:56571:133"/>
paſſeth it by, diſdaining to be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved out of himſelf; eſpecially by thoſe ordinary and common Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations, which are rather Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary, than Real Injuries. I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in <hi>Words;</hi> which are wont to make as deep, if not deeper Impreſſions, than the Hand: Yet they neither impoveriſh Land, nor break the Skin; no not that about the Ear: So that thus far there is no Real Harm done. And if they touch the Soul, (as ſome times they do to the very Quick) the Fault is indeed in our ſelves; becauſe it is our own Paſſion that ſharpens them, and makes their ready way to the Heart; Which, were it fortified with Patience, would turn it off with an eaſie and ſafe Hand; as a Bolt ſhot from a weak Man's Mouth; and then there would be no harm
<pb n="255" facs="tcp:56571:133"/>
there neither. Theſe Things are Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious; and were it only for want of Philoſophy, that People know not how to avoid Nettles, there would be ſome Excuſe for thoſe, who have not been bleſt with a Liberal Education. But the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Reaſon of all Mankind can tell us, that when we are Affected by a Fooliſh Expreſſion, the Sting comes rather from our own Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, than from a few Syllables; and that the Hurt we feel, is in the Imagination, that Works powerfully, but too raſhly upon the Brutiſh Appetite, to ſeek Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge and Satisfaction for Trifles. <hi>In Patience poſſeſs ye your Souls,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>Luke</hi> 21. 19. It is a certain way to be Eaſie <hi>in</hi> the World, and <hi>to</hi> the World; which I am ſure is no little piece of Charity. Conſidering the vaſt
<pb n="256" facs="tcp:56571:134"/>
Diſadvantages which come to Mankind by our Boiſterous Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and the Common Hurt which one ſingle Perſon may do to a great many by them, hardly can any particular Man endure too much: Even a Real Injury to himſelf is to be born with Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, till great Charity requires him to ſeek for ſome Redreſs, and that too muſt be done with a Charitable Mind, and after as juſt and as kind a manner as may be. And after all, it ſhould be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, that the Reparation gotten may not anſwer the Damage, wherein a Man involves himſelf and others, for want of Patience at firſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. There is yet a third Reaſon, why <hi>Charity</hi> ſhould teach us to <hi>endure all Things;</hi> and it is taken
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:56571:134"/>
from the Kindneſs we owe even thoſe our Enemies, that bring us into Affliction, and perhaps de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignedly. As Unjuſt as they be, Chriſtian Charity obligeth us to do our beſt, to bring them to a Senſe of their Wickedneſs, that ſo they may be led to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Now Patience is a very probable means of bringing this about, becauſe it is a moſt amiable Virtue; and the Sight of it is very moving, very apt to work upon the Affections. It is enough to make a deep Impreſſion upon any Hearts, that do not conſiſt of Iron, or Flint, to ſee Men take it patiently when they do well, and yet ſuffer for it. Compaſſion is many times a much ſtronger. Thing than Argument; and it hath often made the Spirits of Cruel Men relent, when hardly
<pb n="258" facs="tcp:56571:135"/>
any Thing elſe could. It is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a common Saying, <hi>That by bearing one Injury, you do invite and encourage wicked People to load you with more.</hi> But ſuch Inſtances are very rare, where there is a true Senſe of Religion, or Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; and thoſe Natures muſt needs be very foul and dreggy, which take Delight and Pleaſure in heaping up Injuries upon Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: Yet even in that caſe, Time and Patience do Miracles; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Conſcience, if it ſtirs once, is a very troubleſome Thing to a Wicked Man, and that which makes the purſuing of Miſchief a very troubleſome Work; ſo that many times baſe Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions tire of themſelves, when the Patience of an Innocent Oppreſſed Perſon holds out; and they tire the ſooner by it. Witneſs the
<pb n="259" facs="tcp:56571:135"/>
great Changes which were made in the Minds of Perſecutors, chiefly, if not merely, by the wonderful Patience of Chriſtians in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Ages. <hi>Tiberian</hi> the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of <hi>Paleſtine</hi> ſent the Emperor <hi>Trajan</hi> word, <hi>That he was weary of his Proceedings</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Uſher Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend. Ignat. p.</hi> 9.</note> 
                  <hi>againſt the Galileans;</hi> (as Chriſtians were then commonly called:) Their Invincible Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and Conſtancy, and Calm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Minds, notwithſtanding all their ſharpeſt Sufferings, made multitudes of the Heathens, not only weary of Perſecuting them, but weary too of their own Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples; for they concluded, that Religion was from God indeed, for which ſuch vaſt Numbers of Men and Women did ſuffer the moſt exquiſite Torments with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaken Minds, and evenneſs of
<pb n="260" facs="tcp:56571:136"/>
Temper; without any Tranſport, unleſs it were of Joy for their Tribulations. <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth, that it was the Thing that Converted him to <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apol.</hi> 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>p.</hi> 50.</note> 
                  <hi>For</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>when I ſaw the Chriſtians go to their Torments and Deaths ſo <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndauntedly, I thought it impoſſible that ſuch People ſhould live in Wickedneſs, and the Love of Pleaſures; becauſe it concerns all Vicious and Voluptuous Perſons to avoid Death.</hi> Their Unconquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Patience was an Argument that Truth was on their ſide; and this made Proſelites even of their Enemies; ſo that in times of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution their Numbers increaſed. For which reaſon that Politick Emperor <hi>Julian,</hi> that hated Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity ſo, many times hindred its Profeſſors from being put to Death, becauſe their Patience
<pb n="261" facs="tcp:56571:136"/>
wrought ſuch wonderful Effects upon the Hearts of the very <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans.</hi> Where Patience is, there is God; the Power and Spirit of God: And who knoweth how ſoon, and how powerfully that Holy Spirit may work upon the Hearts even of the Children of Diſobedience.</p>
               <p>I told you before, That the Law of Charity ties us to endure all Things with Patience; however Troubles come upon us, whether by the Injuſtice and Enmity of ſome; or by means of the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Perſwaſions of others, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Matters of Religion: And before I ſhut up this Diſcourſe, it will be neceſſary for me to ſay ſomething upon that Point of Charity.</p>
               <p>Any one may ſee, how vaſtly Prejudicial it is to the Peace and
<pb n="262" facs="tcp:56571:137"/>
Intereſt, not only of particular Perſons, but of the Publick State, that even thoſe whom we may reaſonably preſume to be Pious and Sincere Chriſtians, cannot differ in their Judgments as to ſome Opinions that are in Vogue; but on each ſide, they are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hardly thought, and very hardly ſpoke of. Nay, as if the Perſecutions of the Tongue were not keen enough, the Unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tableneſs of Heady People hath proceeded to Confiſcations and Flames alſo.</p>
               <p>Before I go on upon this Theme, I muſt lay down theſe two Cautions:</p>
               <p n="1">1. That I do not take upon me to Preſcribe to the Civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, whoſe Office it is to look after the Good of the whole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity;
<pb n="263" facs="tcp:56571:137"/>
what is moſt Neceſſary or Prudent for him, whether to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, or to prohibit Differences of Opinion, I do not preſume to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine here. Nor,</p>
               <p n="2">2. Is it my Meaning, That all Opinions ſhould paſs abroad without Lett or Contradiction, though they directly tend, ſome of them, to Subvert the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the common Chriſtian Faith, or to corrupt Good Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, or to deſtroy or injure Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Societies.</p>
               <p>But when Men are not Legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors for others, but Judges for themſelves only; when Points are knotty and Diſputable, and hard to be clearly determined; and when Opinions are harmleſs e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, eſpecially while they lodge in the Minds of peaceable and
<pb n="264" facs="tcp:56571:138"/>
modeſt Men; we ſhould expreſs our Charity to each other, by al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing every one the Liberty of his own private Judgment, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out denying thoſe of a different Perſwaſion from us, either our Communion, or our Affections. 'Tis unreaſonable to make Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions Arguments to ſet up ſtrait a ſeparate Party; and to uſe them as the Men of <hi>Gilead</hi> did the word <hi>Shibboleth,</hi> Judg. 12. 6. for a Note of Diſcrimination between a Friend and an Enemy. Opinions ſhould keep their own proper Station in the Brain, without Tainting the Heart; and tho' in ſome Points we have various Perſwaſions, as the Members of the Body have various Uſes and Offices; yet Chriſtian Charity ſhould be like one Common Soul, to Animate, to Influence, and to Comfort the
<pb n="265" facs="tcp:56571:138"/>
whole. The Reaſons of it are many; but I ſhall mention only theſe Two, as ſufficient Grounds for our Mutual Charity in this caſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. There are a great many Doctrines, which are not ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily neceſſary to Salvation; and conſequently we cannot ſuppoſe them to be Revealed to us after ſuch a clear manner, as neceſſary Things are: Yet theſe are for the moſt part thoſe Doctrines which have made ſo much Noiſe, and done ſo much Miſchief in the World. The Way to Heaven is obvious enough, and eaſie to be diſcover'd; <hi>viz.</hi> By believing the plain, common, and ſtanding Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of Chriſtianity; and by leading a Godly, Righteous, and Sober Life. But there are divers
<pb n="266" facs="tcp:56571:139"/>
By Speculations that are Intricate, and ſome of them hardly worth the Time and Pains beſtowed on them; becauſe the Enquiry is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Things, that are not only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote from our Faculties, but very diſtant too from our great and neceſſary Buſineſs. And what do we get by all our Enquiries after Matters that are thus Foreign and Dark? Truly very little: Perhaps a ſlight Tranſitory Glimpſe at the long run, which brings ſomething of preſent Pleaſure to the Fancy, but nothing of real Advantage to the poor Soul. 'Tis pity indeed that Men ſhould trifle away their precious Time thus: But if they will be at ſo much Pains for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a little Delight for the time, methinks 'tis pity too, that other wiſer Men ſhould be ſo Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable, as to begrudge them
<pb n="267" facs="tcp:56571:139"/>
that after all their hard Labours: Nor is there any Reaſon for thoſe Heats and Animoſities about Things that are out of our way to Everlaſting Reſt. For why ſhould I Condemn or Hate ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe I conceive he Erreth in ſuch and ſuch Points, when God hath not peremptorily required either him or me to know them at all; but both of us may be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of them with ſafety? Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fierce Diſputes, and hot Words, have paſs'd between <hi>Lutherans</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts</hi> abroad, and between ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of our ſelves here at home; and that about Things not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to Salvation. And what have Men gained by all this, but the Vain-glory of having been very warm Diſputants on each hand? Charity would give us all a far better Title: I am ſure it
<pb n="268" facs="tcp:56571:140"/>
would Intitle us to a far better Place, which we are concerned to ſtrive how to gain, infinitely more than to turn Digladiators about <hi>Logick</hi> and <hi>Metaphyſicks,</hi> and to run the hazard of Sacrificing all in a fooliſh Quarrel, who hath the beſt Skill in managing the Sword's Point; where there is no need at all of any ſuch Weapon. Where a Thing is doubtful, we ſhould fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly propoſe our Thoughts, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Reaſons for them; and ſo let it reſt, with Hearts full of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity on both ſides. I doubt not but many good Chriſtians have arrived at the Gate of <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> notwithſtanding ſome ſlight Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors they happen'd to entertain by the way. As long as an Error doth not hurt the Foundation, nor gives Encouragement to a Wicked Life, nor deſtroys Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity;
<pb n="269" facs="tcp:56571:140"/>
I do not underſtand, but a Perſon ſo erring may well be ſaved; though he ſuffers the loſs of the Hay and Stubble, which through Ignorance and Unskilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs he built upon the right ſound Faith.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As all Doctrines are not equally neceſſary, and manifeſt, ſo all Men's <hi>Apprehenſions</hi> are not of an equal Capacity, nor their Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities and Means of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge equal neither. I will not enter into that nice Diſpute, whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther all Souls are equal? This is certain, that the more or leſs the Advantages of Education are, the more or leſs is a Man's Judgment and Faculties improved. Some Men may live in more Learned Times, or be bleſs'd with more Skilful Inſtructers, or be furniſh'd
<pb n="270" facs="tcp:56571:141"/>
with more uſeful Books; or may find out a better Method, or may be encouraged with greater Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, or may ſearch after Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters with more Impartiality, and freedom of Thought. Divers ways it happeneth, that as one Man exceedeth another in Stature, ſo one Man excelleth another in Knowledge too. And would it not be monſtrous <hi>Impatience,</hi> not to <hi>endure</hi> to ſee another's Bulk? And to fall foul upon him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is not of an equal Growth with his Neighbour? Or becauſe he is not of the ſame Aſpect, of the ſame Features and Lineaments with his Neighbour? Why, the Uncharitableneſs is ſuch when one quarrels with another, becauſe he hath not the ſame pitch of Underſtanding with his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; and becauſe he is not of
<pb n="271" facs="tcp:56571:141"/>
the ſame Meaſure in his Capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and of the ſame Judgment in all Things. He may truly love God, and God may everlaſtingly love him; though his Senſe in a Controverſie be different from anothers, who loves, and is belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of God too: At beſt we ſee but through a Glaſs; and our Sight is very dim in compariſon. It may happen that ones Eye may be naturally very weak, that he cannot, no not by the help of the Glaſs, ſee Things ſo well as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth: Or perhaps there may be a little Habitual Prejudice in the caſe, which like an Eye trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with the Jaundiſe, may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colour the Object, and preſent it to the Underſtanding with a little Tincture upon it: Or though the Senſe it ſelf be ſound and clear, yet there may be ſome Specks in
<pb n="272" facs="tcp:56571:142"/>
the very Glaſs. And the Reſult of all is this; That we are at the very beſt but <hi>Men,</hi> ſubject to Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and Miſapprehenſions: And why ſhould you be Uncharitable to another Man, and not bear with his Infirmities, becauſe God hath made him a Man, and not an Angel? In ſhort, one Man ſeeth more, and further than another, and to Perſecute him for this, to be Impatient and Uncharitable for this, would be ſuch Cruelty, as if I ſhould cut off his Head, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is higher than mine own.</p>
               <p>Before I let this Conſideration go, I cannot but Reflect upon the Wretched Uncharitableneſs of thoſe, who are ſo out of patience at all Diſſentings in Religion, that they even kill Men for Hereſie, whatever Genſures ſuch deſerve,
<pb n="273" facs="tcp:56571:142"/>
they ought to be Spiritual; and ſuch Cenſures are Charitable. I will add, that whatever a Prince may do in ſuch a caſe, to ſecure the publick Peace, which he is bound in Conſcience to provide for; yet for Hereſie alone, and if it be not aggravated with any Criminal Actions, he ought not to inflict upon any the Puniſhment of Death. The firſt Inſtance we find of this Nature, was the kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of <hi>Priſcillian</hi> and his Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices about the Year 385: But it was done by <hi>Maximus</hi> that Cruel Prince, that deſtroyed ſome Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, and Catholicks too, without Diſcrimination. And Sulpitious <hi>Severus</hi> gives this Account of the Fact: <hi>Hoc modo homines Luce in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digniſſimi peſſimo exemplo necati ſunt;</hi> 
                  <q>Though the Men deſerv'd not to ſee the Light, yet the kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="274" facs="tcp:56571:143"/>
of them was a moſt Evil Example.</q> An Example that in latter Ages hath been ſcandalouſly followed by the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and 'tis the more to be Lamented, becauſe ſome furious Proteſtants followed it too. The Burning of <hi>Servetus</hi> at <hi>Geneva</hi> was a Fact, which the beſt Men of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation would never go about to Juſtifie: And the Author of the Hiſtory of the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> tell us; <hi>It was to the Admiration of many, that the Firſt Reformers did ſhed Blood in the Cauſe of Religion.</hi> The Truth is, ſuch is the Spirit and Genius of Right Chriſtianity, that it ſavours of nothing but what is Pure and Deſireable; ſuch as Meekneſs, Patience, Humility, Goodneſs: And with theſe moſt amiable Virtues; Love, Charity, Peaceableneſs, Moderation, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="275" facs="tcp:56571:143"/>
Mercy, and great Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Temper. Though Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity it ſelf may ſometimes hold out a Rod, to terrifie People from thoſe Scandalous Diſorders, which Kindneſs alone cannot many times put a ſtop to; yet to Vindicate even the true Faith with the cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Arguments of Steel, or by the Torments of the Stake, is a Sign rather of a Barbarous, than a Religious and Chriſtian Mind. Such Burning and Flaming Zeal as this, the gentle Spirit of Chriſt doth not kindle.</p>
               <p>I have now ended the Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of thoſe things, which I propoſed at my Entrance upon this Diſcourſe concerning <hi>Charity,</hi> and in the moſt Uſeful (becauſe the moſt Practical) Part of it; I have, as near as I could, trod in
<pb n="276" facs="tcp:56571:144"/>
the Steps of St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, who left us no leſs than Fifteen ſeveral Characters of <hi>Charity,</hi> as a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Direction for us, how to expreſs this moſt Neceſſary, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and Comprehenſive Virtue. It is one great Argument of the Truth of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> that as its <hi>Doctrines</hi> are Reconcileable unto, ſo the <hi>Duties</hi> of it are Founded upon the beſt <hi>Reaſon;</hi> and are for the moſt part adapted to the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities and Intereſts of Humane Societies. This particular Duty of <hi>Charity</hi> is one, without which Societies cannot poſſibly ſubſiſt; not in that happy Condition, to be ſure, which Chriſtianity hath an Eye upon in the Duties it lays before us; if we were ſo wiſe, as to conſider and ſee where our Real Good lieth, even in this World. The Motions whether
<pb n="277" facs="tcp:56571:144"/>
or Virtue, or Vice, carry a great Stroke with them; and affect not our ſelves only, but thoſe alſo that are round about us. And when the Apoſtle delineated this Virtue, <hi>Charity,</hi> it was upon great Conſideration, both of the Good Effects which attend it, and of thoſe very Evil Conſequences which follow the ſeveral Vices to which <hi>Charity</hi> ſtands in oppoſition, and they to it. Hence it was, that in ſhewing you the ſeveral ways of expreſſing your <hi>Charity,</hi> I was concerned of courſe, and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, to take ſome Notice of thoſe Operations and Conſequences, which Argue the great Reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs of your Practice as to this particular. And hence too it was, that in ſpeaking of thoſe Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, I have uſed all poſſible Plainneſs for every ones Convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction;
<pb n="278" facs="tcp:56571:145"/>
and this, in purſuance of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s great Deſign, to bring all our Hearts to a right Chriſtian, and Charitable Temper; the Thing that is <hi>above all Things;</hi> the Thing that we muſt mind very dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, if we expect ever to be ſaved.</p>
               <p>We muſt not think to preſcribe to our ſelves the Way to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but we muſt take the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of it at the Hand of God, who alone hath a Right and Power to propoſe them; and who alone knoweth which is the beſt way for us. And Charity is the Way that he hath laid out before us in the Holy Scripture: The ſame Jeſus Chriſt, that hath brought Life and Immortality to Light through the Goſpel, hath alſo revealed this as a Means of bringing us to that Life Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal:
<pb n="279" facs="tcp:56571:145"/>
So that we muſt take the whole <hi>Revelation</hi> as it is; and as well make the one part of it the Meaſure of our Practice, as we make the other the Ground of our Faith and Hopes; becauſe the very ſame <hi>Revelation</hi> which gives us Authority to believe a future Bleſſed State, ſhews us like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Neceſſity of a Charitable Temper in order to it. There is one and the ſame Warrant for both; and for that reaſon we muſt believe both, or neither.</p>
               <p>Indeed 'tis very Suſpicious, that Uncharitable People believe very little of God, and a future State, (whatever they pretend) at leaſt that they think not of theſe Things with that Seriouſneſs and Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Mind, which is neceſſary to prepare them for the Practice of Charity: For ſuch Divine
<pb n="280" facs="tcp:56571:146"/>
Thoughts could not but affect them, and work powerfully upon them, did they really believe, (what is moſt certainly true) that by wanting Charity, they muſt needs come ſhort of Heaven.</p>
               <p>Charity is as indiſpenſably ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary as Faith, or as any other Act of Religion. And that we may apply our Hearts in good earneſt to the Study and Exerciſe of it, let us at the cloſe of this Subject conſider briefly this one Thing only, beſides thoſe Motives which have been conſidered al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready: Namely, What an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable</hi> Condition People of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable Spirits involve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in continually. How great ſoever their Health, or Strength, or Fortunes, or their other outward Enjoyments may be, they are the moſt miſerable People in the
<pb n="281" facs="tcp:56571:146"/>
World; becauſe all this while they are in an Unpardon'd State: They go about with all their Sins bound, and in danger of Eternal Damnation every moment; for God is their Enemy, and they his. The Words of our Saviour are plain, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. 15. <hi>If ye forgive not Men their Treſpaſſes, neither will your Father forgive your Treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</hi> And to the ſame purpoſe ſaith the Diſciple of his Boſom, 1 John 3. 14. <hi>He that loveth not his Brother, abideth in Death.</hi> Hence it follows, that the Ordinances of God, though they be the ſtanding Means of Grace and Salvation, do ſuch Uncharitable People no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Good, but Hurt rather; which is a great addition to their Miſery. The Hearing of God's Word doth but increaſe their Guilt. The Sacraments of Chriſt's
<pb n="282" facs="tcp:56571:147"/>
Body and Blood are like Poiſon to their Souls; and their very Prayers, which of all People they have moſt need to ſend up unto Heaven day and night, are ſo far from availing them, that <hi>they are turned into Abomination,</hi> Prov. 28. 9. And what if Death ſhould ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe ſuch People unawares, ſuch Accidents do commonly happen; nor is any Man ſecure, but his Turn ſhall be the next, to drop into the Grave on a ſudden. And what a deſperate Condition doth he drop into, who falls thus un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares with his Conſcience bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened with ſuch a heavy Sin, and in a State of Enmity againſt the Laws of God, and againſt the Saviour of the World? <hi>It had been good for that Man, had he not been born,</hi> Mat. 26. 23.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="283" facs="tcp:56571:147"/>
But 'tis more than probable, that Uncharitable Wretches ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom think of Dying, much leſs of dying a ſudden Death; though Apoplexies, and unexpected Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents happen every where, and are Daily Monitors to us all. Let them preſume then, that ſome Lingering Diſeaſe will ſeize them at the laſt, and allow them ſome Time, to prepare for another Life. But what if they have not an Heart to Prepare themſelves duly then, though they may have Time? 'Tis poſſible for Men to Sin away the Grace of God, and the Day of Salvation. 'Tis poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to harden the Heart ſo, as to render it Uncapable of Good Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions. 'Tis poſſible alſo to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke the Holy and Juſt God, to ſuch an high degree, as that he will refuſe to Soften and Intender
<pb n="284" facs="tcp:56571:148"/>
it, and to liſten to their Cries, that would not call upon him while he was near. They are dreadful Threatnings, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1. from Verſ. 24. to Verſ. 30. <hi>Becauſe I have called, and ye refuſed; I have ſtretched out my Hand, and no Man regarded it. But ye have ſet at nought all my Counſel, and would none of my Reproof. I alſo will laugh at your Calamity, and will mock when your Fear cometh. When your Fear cometh as Deſolation, and your De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction cometh as a Whirlwind; when Diſtreſs and Anguiſh cometh upon you. Then ſhall they call upon me, but I will not anſwer; they ſhall ſeek me early, but they ſhall not find me: For that they hated Knowledge, and did not chooſe the Fear of the Lord.</hi> This I fear is the uſual Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult of Habitual Wickedneſs; and eſpecially of Men's living in a
<pb n="285" facs="tcp:56571:148"/>
courſe and habit of Uncharitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; becauſe it is a Sin (or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Complication of Sins) ſo Diametrically oppoſite to the Laws of Jeſus Chriſt, and to the Spirit of his Religion, that of all others now, it ſeemeth to come the neareſt to the very Sin againſt the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſe ſuch People ſhould at laſt expreſs ſome Grief and Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for their Wicked Temper, and for thoſe manifold Injuries and Miſchiefs, which are the uſual Effects of Uncharitableneſs; yet who can tell, whether this Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row proceedeth from the Love of God, and from a true Senſe and Hatred of the Sin; or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it doth not come merely from an Apprehenſion of thoſe Torments whereof their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences are now afraid? If it be
<pb n="286" facs="tcp:56571:149"/>
only the Fear of Puniſhment which extorteth thoſe Expreſſions, this is very conſiſtent with an Evil Mind; that would act over the ſame Sins again, could they but renew their Lives. And therefore this Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row is no better than Nothing in God's Account; becauſe it is not ſuch <hi>a Godly Sorrow, as worketh Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance unto Salvation not to be repented of,</hi> 2 Cor. 7. 10.</p>
               <p>Let it be granted, Laſtly, That the Sorrow is Genuine and Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, yet little Comfort can come by it to the Dying Perſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath no <hi>Time</hi> now to <hi>try,</hi> whether his Mind be changed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and whether he be become a <hi>New Man,</hi> and a <hi>New Creature.</hi> So that at the beſt, his Caſe is very bad, becauſe, though he be a True Penitent, yet it is more than he knows; and conſequently nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="287" facs="tcp:56571:149"/>
can his Comfort be ſolid, nor can his Hopes of Pardon be built upon a ſure Foundation.</p>
               <p>In ſuch a Labyrinth of Miſery doth an Uncharitable Temper plunge every inconſiderate Wretch, that the Pleaſure he takes, and the Profit he gets by Acts of Malice and Revenge, doth not counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail the Thouſandth Part of thoſe Calamities and Dangers he expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth himſelf to unavoidably.</p>
               <p>Therefore it deeply concerns us all, to be Wiſe in time, to mend in time, to Subdue and Rectifie our Diſpoſitions in time, and to new-mould our Hearts into a Reſemblance of that Holy and Excellent Being, who is a God of Compaſſion, the Father of Mercies; the Author of Peace, and the Lover of Concord. Men may fancy what they pleaſe; but
<pb n="288" facs="tcp:56571:150"/>
I take it for a certain Truth, that <hi>according as our Tempers are, either Good or Evil, ſo God loves or hates us; and ſo our Portion will be at the laſt. If any Man have not the Spirit of Chriſt,</hi> (that is, the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition and Temper of Chriſt) <hi>he is none of his,</hi> faith St. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 8. 9. And what was Chriſt's Spirit, but a Spirit of Love? His Doctrines tended to Peace and Charity. His Miracles were Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable; he ſhewed his Power, as God doth, in doing Works of Pity and Compaſſion: <hi>He went about doing Good.</hi> And when his Hands and Feet were now Nailed to the Croſs, and hindred from doing any more, he employed his Tongue and Heart in a Work of the greateſt Charity of all; in ſending up a Charitable Prayer for the Pardon of his Enemies.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="289" facs="tcp:56571:150"/>
Here then is the Pattern that we muſt follow, if we expect any Benefit by his Crucifixion: As of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as we <hi>look on him, whom they pierced,</hi> we muſt have an Eye up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his <hi>Temper,</hi> as well as upon his <hi>Blood;</hi> and we muſt make the one our <hi>Example,</hi> as well as lay hold on the other for our <hi>Peace.</hi> In ſtead of <hi>ſeeking</hi> the Hurt, or <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending</hi> the Hurt, or <hi>wiſhing</hi> the Hurt of any; we muſt apply and ſet our Hearts as the Lord Jeſus did, to do every one all the Good we can; and then are we his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed. To ſum up all then in the Words of St. <hi>Paul; Let all Bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs, and Wrath, and Anger, and Clamour, and Evil-ſpeaking, be put away from you, with all Malice. Be ye Kind one to another, and Tender-hearted. Put on (as the Elect of God, Holy and Beloved) Bowels of</hi>
                  <pb n="290" facs="tcp:56571:151"/>
                  <hi>Mercy, Goodneſs, Humbleneſs of Mind, Meekneſs, Long-ſuffering; forbearing one another, and forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another: If any Man have a Quarrel againſt any; even as Chriſt forgave you, ſo alſo do ye. And above all theſe Things, put on Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which is the Bond of Perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. And let the Peace of God Rule in your Hearts, to the which alſo ye are called in one Body.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>O <hi>Lord, who haſt taught us, That all our Doings without Charity are nothing worth; ſend thy Holy Ghoſt, and pour into our Hearts that moſt excellent Gift of Charity, the very Bond of Peace, and of all Virtues; without which, whoſoever Liveth, is counted Dead before thee: Grant this for thine only Son Jeſus Chriſt's ſake.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="291" facs="tcp:56571:151"/>
                  <hi>ALmighty and Everlaſting God, give unto us the Increaſe of Faith, Hope, and Charity; and that we may obtain that which thou doſt Promiſe, make us to Love that which thou doſt Command; through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ALmighty Father, who haſt Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thine only Son to Die for our Sins, and to Riſe again for our Juſtification; Grant us ſo to put away the Leaven of Malice and Wickedneſs, that we may alway ſerve Thee in Pureneſs of Living and Truth; through the Merits of thy Son Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>O <hi>Almighty God, who haſt knit together thine Elect, in one Communion and Fellowſhip in the</hi>
                  <pb n="292" facs="tcp:56571:152"/>
                  <hi>Myſtical Body of thy Son Jeſus Chriſt our Lord; Grant us Grace ſo to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low thy Bleſſed Saints in all Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and Godly Living, that we may come to thoſe <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſpeakable Joys, which thou haſt Prepared for them that <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfeignedly love Thee; through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:56571:152"/>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
